<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title type="text">Tag: aikido :: phly, boy, phly</title>
  <updated>2004-09-20T12:46:44-05:00</updated>
  <generator uri="http://framework.zend.com" version="2.0.0beta3">Zend_Feed_Writer</generator>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mwop.net/blog/tag/aikido.html"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://mwop.net/blog/tag/aikido-atom.xml"/>
  <id>http://mwop.net/blog/tag/aikido.html</id>
  <entry xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Random thoughts of violence]]></title>
    <published>2004-02-09T21:25:56-06:00</published>
    <updated>2004-09-20T12:46:44-05:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mwop.net/blog/29-Random-thoughts-of-violence.html"/>
    <id>http://mwop.net/blog/29-Random-thoughts-of-violence.html</id>
    <author>
      <name>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</name>
      <email>me@mwop.net</email>
      <uri>http://mwop.net</uri>
    </author>
    <content xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" type="xhtml">
      <xhtml:div xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><xhtml:p>I began the day with sudden images and body remembrances of an
escrima or arnis drill Morgan used to teach during weapons class
years ago -- it utilizes a short stick or wakazashi in one hand,
the other hand free, and consists of five steps on each side; when
you finish one side, you do the other, because the drill is done
with a partner.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>I haven't done the drill for years, but I remembered all the
nuances, all the little tips and secrets Morgan showed me over the
year or two he continued teaching it. And I wanted desperately to
do it with someone right that moment as I was getting out of bed so
that I wouldn't lose it. But, of course, I had no such opportunity.
The movement is still tracing its way through my body.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>And this evening, we watched Fight Club. I still remember
watching it in the theater, and how it affected me then -- and it
affects me in many of the same ways now. There's some cultural
references I 'get' more now -- references to Ikea, and now I
understand groups and guided meditation and therapy better. And
there's new references, too -- the image of the buildings falling
is much different now that the WTC buildings have been viewed
collapsing.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>But the message, the message is still the same, still present.
Do things own us, or do we own them? What do I most want to do
before I die, and am I doing it? These are big questions for a film
to raise, and I'm still surprised that Fight Club remains such a
huge hit and success because of them. And they're not necessarily
buried in the film -- though I can see how many people might simply
glorify the violence in the film, and pass over the message. I find
the violence is a part of the message -- can you teach yourself to
live with pain, that pain is transient and ceases? can you learn to
stop living in fear?</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>So my day was marked by violence, beginning and end. The middle
was all consumer fluff. And hedonism. But hey, that's okay,
too.</xhtml:p>
</xhtml:div>
    </content>
  </entry>
</feed>
