<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title type="text">Tag: conferences :: phly, boy, phly</title>
  <updated>2008-06-20T15:56:28+0000</updated>
  <generator uri="http://framework.zend.com" version="2.1.4dev">Zend_Feed_Writer</generator>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mwop.net/blog/tag/conferences.html"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://mwop.net/blog/tag/conferences-atom.xml"/>
  <id>http://mwop.net/blog/tag/conferences.html</id>
  <entry xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[DPC08 Wrapup]]></title>
    <published>2008-06-20T11:33:45+0000</published>
    <updated>2008-06-20T15:56:28+0000</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mwop.net/blog/179-DPC08-Wrapup.html"/>
    <id>http://mwop.net/blog/179-DPC08-Wrapup.html</id>
    <author>
      <name>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</name>
      <email>me@mwop.net</email>
      <uri>http://mwop.net</uri>
    </author>
    <content xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" type="xhtml">
      <xhtml:div xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><xhtml:p>Last Friday and Saturday I spent at <xhtml:a href="http://phpconference.nl/">the Dutch PHP Conference</xhtml:a>, hosted by
<xhtml:a href="http://ibuildings.nl/">Ibuildings</xhtml:a>. Unfortunately, I
had very little time to blog while there. I'd prepared my outlines
and basic slides before heading to the conference, but had a large
number of screenshots and images to prepare that kept me up until
the wee hours of the morning each day. In addition, the conference
was extremely well organized -- which meant that any time not spent
speaking was spent interacting with attendees or other speakers --
never a bad thing!</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>First off, the big impression I had when the conference finished
is that either PHP developers in Holland are incredibly
professional, or that the best practices advocated by various
community leaders are finally taking hold. My last talk was one
addressing development best practices, and I was constantly amazed
at how many people were <xhtml:em>already</xhtml:em> using most if not all the
best practices I touched on in my talk. This is really fantastic
news, as far as I'm concerned; hopefully all those PHP detractors
out there are going to start taking notice that PHP development has
matured, and, in fact become very quality oriented. Here's that
presentation:</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:div style="width:425px;text-align:left" id="__ss_472388">
<xhtml:object style="margin:0px" width="425" height="355"><xhtml:param name="movie" value="http://static.slideshare.net/swf/ssplayer2.swf?doc=20080614bestpractices-1213726335523088-9"/>
<xhtml:param name="allowFullScreen" value="true"/>
<xhtml:param name="allowScriptAccess" value="always"/>
<xhtml:embed src="http://static.slideshare.net/swf/ssplayer2.swf?doc=20080614bestpractices-1213726335523088-9" type="application/x-shockwave-flash" allowscriptaccess="always" allowfullscreen="true" width="425" height="355"/></xhtml:object>
<xhtml:div style="font-size:11px;font-family:tahoma,arial;height:26px;padding-top:2px;">
<xhtml:a href="http://www.slideshare.net/?src=embed"><xhtml:img src="http://static.slideshare.net/swf/logo_embd.png" style="border:0px none;margin-bottom:-5px" alt="SlideShare"/></xhtml:a> |
<xhtml:a href="http://www.slideshare.net/weierophinney/everyday-best-practices-of-php-development?src=embed" title="View Everyday Best Practices of PHP Development on SlideShare">View</xhtml:a>
| <xhtml:a href="http://www.slideshare.net/upload?src=embed">Upload your
own</xhtml:a></xhtml:div>
</xhtml:div>
<xhtml:p>The big event for me, of course, was the full day Zend Framework
workshop. My two regrets: a) not having a better script for the
final hour, when I covered a simple demo bugapp used for developing
the workshop, and b) running opposite <xhtml:a href="http://sebastian-bergmann.de">Sebastian Bergmann</xhtml:a> -- as I
wanted to see what he's been working on recently with <xhtml:a href="http://phpunit.de/">PHPUnit</xhtml:a>. That said, I feel the workshop
went over very well; I was able to finish each section early enough
that we had time for 5 - 15 minutes of questions over the material
just covered, and there were excellent questions from those
attending. The funny part was that with two of the questions, I
simply fired up my browser to the tutorials I wrote on <xhtml:a href="http://devzone.zend.com/">DevZone</xhtml:a>, and used the examples and
materials from them to answer the questions.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:div style="width:425px;text-align:left" id="__ss_472382">
<xhtml:object style="margin:0px" width="425" height="355"><xhtml:param name="movie" value="http://static.slideshare.net/swf/ssplayer2.swf?doc=20080613zendframeworkworkshop-1213725963433006-9"/>
<xhtml:param name="allowFullScreen" value="true"/>
<xhtml:param name="allowScriptAccess" value="always"/>
<xhtml:embed src="http://static.slideshare.net/swf/ssplayer2.swf?doc=20080613zendframeworkworkshop-1213725963433006-9" type="application/x-shockwave-flash" allowscriptaccess="always" allowfullscreen="true" width="425" height="355"/></xhtml:object>
<xhtml:div style="font-size:11px;font-family:tahoma,arial;height:26px;padding-top:2px;">
<xhtml:a href="http://www.slideshare.net/?src=embed"><xhtml:img src="http://static.slideshare.net/swf/logo_embd.png" style="border:0px none;margin-bottom:-5px" alt="SlideShare"/></xhtml:a> |
<xhtml:a href="http://www.slideshare.net/weierophinney/zend-framework-workshop?src=embed" title="View Zend Framework Workshop on SlideShare">View</xhtml:a> |
<xhtml:a href="http://www.slideshare.net/upload?src=embed">Upload your
own</xhtml:a></xhtml:div>
</xhtml:div>
<xhtml:p>As promised, I've <xhtml:a href="/uploads/bugapp.tar.gz">uploaded the
bug application</xhtml:a> I worked up to create the session. Be aware
that it's incomplete; the main thing was to see how each of the
various pieces could interact so I'd know what to cover and when in
the workshop.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Following the night of the workshops, Ibuildings had a dinner
for their employees, and I was invited to tag along. I had some
great conversations with <xhtml:a href="http://www.lornajane.net">Lorna
Jane</xhtml:a> and one of her colleagues, Bill, discussing topics ranging
from family to training, from travel to PHP, and more. Dinner was
timed to end as the big match between Holland and France began, and
all I have to say about that is: if you've never witnessed the fans
of a big football match in Holland when Oranje is winning, you
haven't lived. 'Nuff said. :-)</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>I had a number of good conversations with a variety of people,
really -- <xhtml:a href="http://inside.e-novative.de/">Stefan
Priebsch</xhtml:a>, <xhtml:a href="http://sebastian-bergmann.de/">Sebastian</xhtml:a>, <xhtml:a href="http://suraski.net/blog/">Zeev</xhtml:a>, <xhtml:a href="http://mtabini.blogspot.com">Marco Tabini</xhtml:a>, Lorna Jane, Stefan
Koopfmanschap, <xhtml:a href="http://www.aide-de-camp.org/">Fabien
Potencier</xhtml:a>, and more. (Believe it or not, you <xhtml:em>can</xhtml:em> get
more than one framework lead in the same room and have things stay
civil; Fabien and I swapped some information regarding plans for
our next major releases, what issues we've seen, and what features
we're excited about.) <xhtml:a href="http://felix.phpbelgium.be/blog/">Felix De Vliegher</xhtml:a> and
<xhtml:a href="http://www.dragonbe.com/">Michelangelo Van Damme</xhtml:a> were
also there, representing PHP Belgium, and it was great to hear how
their region's PHP community is starting to come together.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>I also got a chance to meet a few people from the Zend Framework
lists and IRC in person: Andries Seutens, Jurrien Stutterheim, and
Bart McLeod -- and a few others whose names I most regrettably
forget. I wish I could have had more time to talk with each of you,
and discuss your projects more.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Now, while the conference was fantastic, probably the best part
for me personally was the day prior. My good friend <xhtml:a href="http://www.wolerized.com/">Remi</xhtml:a>, with whom I've worked on some
projects at Zend a number of times over the past year, came up from
Gouda to hang with me for the day. We walked all over the city --
through the Vondelpark, up by the Rijksmuseum and Van Gogh museums,
along and over countless canals, near (but not through) the red
light district, by the RAI (where the conference was held) and all
the way up to Grand Centraal. I complained about sore feet and legs
all weekend, but it was the best tour I could have imagined of the
city, and one I shan't forget any time soon. And the reason we went
to Grand Centraal was to meet up with <xhtml:a href="http://www.leftontheweb.com/">Stefan Koopmanschap</xhtml:a>, with whom
we would then have dinner and drinks that night. I feel very
fortunate to have had the chance to spend some uninterrupted time
with each of these fantastic developers and individuals.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>So, the short summary: excellent conference, excellent friends,
excellent city. Looking forward to DPC '09!</xhtml:p>
</xhtml:div>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Speaking at the Dutch PHP Conference]]></title>
    <published>2008-05-18T19:08:33+0000</published>
    <updated>2008-05-20T10:10:37+0000</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mwop.net/blog/175-Speaking-at-the-Dutch-PHP-Conference.html"/>
    <id>http://mwop.net/blog/175-Speaking-at-the-Dutch-PHP-Conference.html</id>
    <author>
      <name>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</name>
      <email>me@mwop.net</email>
      <uri>http://mwop.net</uri>
    </author>
    <content xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" type="xhtml">
      <xhtml:div xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><xhtml:p>I've known for some time, but was reluctant to blog about it
until the plane tickets were purchased and in hand: I've been
invited to speak at the <xhtml:a href="http://phpconference.nl/">Dutch
PHP Conference</xhtml:a> this coming June:</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p style="text-align: center"><xhtml:img src="http://phpconference.nl/img/dpc08/logoDPC08_small.png" alt="DPC" height="149" width="217"/></xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>I'll be presenting two separate sessions: <xhtml:a href="http://phpconference.nl/workshops/">an all day tutorial</xhtml:a> on 13
June 2008 covering Zend Framework, and a regular session on 14 June
2008 covering <xhtml:a href="http://phpconference.nl/schedule/bestpractices">Best Practices for
PHP development</xhtml:a>, which will focus on how to utilize Zend
Framework coding standards and methodologies to help deliver
efficient, high quality code for your organization.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>I'm looking forward to meeting old and new friends alike at the
conference!</xhtml:p>
</xhtml:div>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ZendCon is over at last]]></title>
    <published>2007-10-12T00:50:47+0000</published>
    <updated>2007-10-18T07:19:41+0000</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mwop.net/blog/146-ZendCon-is-over-at-last.html"/>
    <id>http://mwop.net/blog/146-ZendCon-is-over-at-last.html</id>
    <author>
      <name>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</name>
      <email>me@mwop.net</email>
      <uri>http://mwop.net</uri>
    </author>
    <content xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" type="xhtml">
      <xhtml:div xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><xhtml:p><xhtml:a href="http://www.zendcon.com/">ZendCon '07</xhtml:a> is finally
over, the dust has settled, and I finally find myself with some
time alone... practically the first I've had since Sunday. The week
was fantastic, and I had many good conversations and brainstorming
sessions. Oh, and I ended up giving three different sessions, so
it's time for links to slides and materials:</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:ul>
<xhtml:li><xhtml:a href="/uploads/2007-ZendCon-BestPractices.odp">Best
Practices of PHP Development</xhtml:a>. <xhtml:a href="http://sebastian-bergmann.de/">Sebastian</xhtml:a>, <xhtml:a href="http://mikenaberezny.com/">Mike</xhtml:a>, and I presented a full-day
tutorial on PHP development best practices, focussing primarily on
testing and testing strategies, but also covering coding standards,
usage of SCM tools, and deployment. There were a ton of questions
from the attendees, and Sebastian even whipped out some extra
slides at the end showing new and little-known features of PHPUnit.
Basically, reading the slides won't really indicate what we
covered, but is more of a general outline. It was an honor and
pleasure to work with Sebastian and Mike on this, and I hope we can
do it again in the future some time.</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li><xhtml:a href="/uploads/2007-ZendCon-MVC.ppt">Zend Framework MVC
Quick Start</xhtml:a>. This was basically the same session I did in my
<xhtml:a href="http://www.zend.com/webinar">webinar</xhtml:a> a couple weeks
ago, with a few corrections and a small demonstration. Cal put me
on directly following <xhtml:a href="http://terrychay.com/blog">Terry
Chay</xhtml:a>, in the largest of the four session rooms -- the one where
all the keynotes occurred -- talk about intimidating! Amazingly,
the session was really well attended -- others I talked to estimate
between 100 and 150 people showed up. The most amazing part,
though, was that when I asked how many people knew what 'MVC' was,
I don't think there was a single person who didn't raise their hand
-- definitely a sign of how well accepted the pattern now is in
PHP.</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li><xhtml:a href="/uploads/2007-ZendCon-AjaxPresentation.odp">AJAX-Enabling Your
Zend Framework Controllers</xhtml:a>. I did this talk for the <xhtml:a href="http://www.zendcon.com/wiki/index.php?title=Uncon">Unconference</xhtml:a>,
mainly because its a topic I've been interested in and wanted to
present. In it, I detailed how to ajax-enable an application
through some easy tricks with Action and View Helpers and using JS
to decorate your existing application. The reference app I used was
a pastebin, and I've got code for both <xhtml:a href="http://dojotoolkit.org">Dojo</xhtml:a> and <xhtml:a href="http://prototypejs.org">Prototype</xhtml:a> flavors available:
<xhtml:ul>
<xhtml:li><xhtml:a href="/uploads/PastebinDojo.tar.gz">Dojo pastebin</xhtml:a></xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li><xhtml:a href="/uploads/PastebinPrototype.tar.gz">Prototype
pastebin</xhtml:a></xhtml:li>
</xhtml:ul>
</xhtml:li>
</xhtml:ul>
<xhtml:p>The two highlight keynote speakers, for me, were definitely
<xhtml:a href="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/">Joel Spolsky</xhtml:a> and
<xhtml:a href="http://craphound.com/">Cory Doctorow</xhtml:a>. Neither spoke
about PHP, but both spoke about topics that PHP developers should
take to heart. Perhaps I'll elaborate on those in another post.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Another bonus for me was the number of old and new friends alike
I got to see -- I had many good conversations with Paul M. Jones,
Nate Abele, Ivo Jansch, and Ralph Schindler, and opportunities to
finally meet fellow co-author Lig Turmelle, Ben Ramsey, Chris
Shifflet (dude, we've been to four conferences together, and never
yet met!), and many, many others. I was also overwhelmed by the
number of Zend Framework users who sought me out either to ask me
questions or simply thank me and the others on the team for the
project; I'm deeply honored that I can work on a project that
affects so many developers.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>And now for some down time to recuperate...</xhtml:p>
</xhtml:div>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[oh, yeah, zendcon...]]></title>
    <published>2007-10-02T11:27:29+0000</published>
    <updated>2007-10-04T04:46:07+0000</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mwop.net/blog/145-oh,-yeah,-zendcon....html"/>
    <id>http://mwop.net/blog/145-oh,-yeah,-zendcon....html</id>
    <author>
      <name>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</name>
      <email>me@mwop.net</email>
      <uri>http://mwop.net</uri>
    </author>
    <content xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" type="xhtml">
      <xhtml:div xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><xhtml:p>I don't know why I haven't blogged this sooner, but, yes, I'll
be speaking once again at <xhtml:a href="http://www.zendcon.com/">ZendCon:</xhtml:a></xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p style="text-align:center;"><xhtml:a href="http://www.zend.com.com"><xhtml:img src="http://s3.amazonaws.com/zendcon/ZendCon07_SpeakerBadge.gif" border="0"/></xhtml:a></xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>I'll be presenting a number of times:</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:ul>
<xhtml:li>On Monday, I join <xhtml:a href="http://sebastian-bergmann.de/">Sebastian Bergmann</xhtml:a> and <xhtml:a href="http://naberezny.com/">Mike Naberezny</xhtml:a> in a full-day tutorial
session on PHP Development Best Practices and Unit Testing. This
expands on what Mike and I did last year, and will more heavily
emphasize the role of testing in the development process --
arguably the most important best practice you can adopt.</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>On Tuesday monrning, I'll present a Zend Framework MVC Quick
Start. This talk is based on a <xhtml:a href="http://weierophinney.net/matthew/archives/144-Zend-Framework-MVC-Webinar-posted.html">
webinar</xhtml:a> I recently gave for Zend, and covers the various pieces
of the MVC layer in Zend Framework.</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>Tuesday evening, I'll present an <xhtml:a href="http://zendcon.com/wiki/index.php?title=Uncon">Unconference</xhtml:a>
session on Ajax-enabling your Zend Framework controllers. I don't
know yet if I'll need the whole hour, but I can probably fill it up
with some examples of decorating your apps with AJAX.</xhtml:li>
</xhtml:ul>
<xhtml:p>Looking forward to seeing you all there!</xhtml:p>
</xhtml:div>
    </content>
  </entry>
</feed>
