<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/">
  <channel>
    <title>Tag: dojo :: phly, boy, phly</title>
    <description>Tag: dojo :: phly, boy, phly</description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2009 13:17:00 +0000</pubDate>
    <generator>Zend_Feed_Writer 2.0.0beta5 (http://framework.zend.com)</generator>
    <link>http://mwop.net/blog/tag/dojo.html</link>
    <atom:link rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" href="http://mwop.net/blog/tag/dojo-rss.xml"/>
    <item>
      <title>Recursively Destroying Dojo ContentPanes</title>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2009 13:17:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/208-Recursively-Destroying-Dojo-ContentPanes.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/208-Recursively-Destroying-Dojo-ContentPanes.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    I ran into an issue recently with Dojo's ContentPanes. I was using them with
    a TabContainer, and had made them closable; however, user actions might
    re-open tabs that pull from the same source. This led to conflicts with
    dijit IDs that I had to resolve.
</p>

<p>
    Most Dijits have a <code>destroyRecursive()</code> method which should,
    theoretically, destroy any dijits contained within them. However, for many
    Dijits, this functionality simply does not work due to how they are
    implemented; many do not actually have any knowledge of the dijits beneath
    them.
</p>

<p>
    ContentPanes fall into this latter category. fortunately, it's relatively
    easy to accomplish, due to Dojo's heavily object oriented nature.
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Using JSLint</title>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2009 13:11:41 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/207-Using-JSLint.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/207-Using-JSLint.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    I've been doing a fair bit of programming in 
    <a href="http://dojotoolkit.org/">Dojo</a> lately, and have on occasion run
    into either inconsistent interfaces, or interfaces that simply fail to load
    in Internet Explorer. Several people have pointed out to me some
    optimizations to make, but, being a lazy programmer, I often forget to do
    so.
</p>

<p>
    Fortunately, there's a tool for lazy developers like myself: 
    <a href="http://jslint.com">JSLint</a>. Linters are commonly used in static
    development languages so that developers can verify that their programs are
    syntactically correct prior to compilation; they basically ensure that
    you're not accidentally attempting to compile something that will never
    compile in the first place. Many dynamic languages also have them; I've had
    a key bound in vim to run the current file through PHP's linter for many
    years now. JSLint provides linting capabilities for JavaScript, as well as
    some code analysis to point you towards some best practices -- mainly geared
    for cross-browser compatability.
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2008: The year in review</title>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2009 07:00:49 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/203-2008-The-year-in-review.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/203-2008-The-year-in-review.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    That time of year again -- wrap-up time. Each year, it seems like it's the
    busiest ever, and I often wonder if it will ever slow down. As usual, I'm
    restricting myself to primarily professional activities out of respect for
    the privacy of my family.
</p>

<p>
    The short, executive summary:
</p>

<ul>
    <li>One trip to Israel</li>
    <li>One trip to The Netherlands</li>
    <li>One trip to California's Bay Area</li>
    <li>One trip to Atlanta, GA</li>
    <li>Three minor releases of Zend Framework</li>
    <li>Seven webinars, six for zend.com and one for Adobe</li>
    <li>Three conferences attended as a speaker, including:<ul>
         <li>One six-hour workshop</li>
         <li>One three-hour tutorial (as a co-presenter)</li>
         <li>Four regular sessions</li>
         <li>Two panel sessions (one scheduled, one for an uncon)</li>
         <li>Two uncon sessions (one as a co-presenter)</li>
         <li>One foul-mouthed Pecha Kucha talk</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>Ten Burlington, VT PHP User's Group meetings attended; I spoke at
        many</li>
    <li>One Bug Hunt week organized</li>
    <li>Two books reviewed as a technical editor</li>
    <li>Six articles for <a href="http://devzone.zend.com/">DevZone</a></li>
    <li>50 blog entries (including this one)</li>
</ul>

<p>
    Read on for the gruesome, month-by-month breakdown.
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Simple PHP Publish-Subscribe System</title>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Dec 2008 12:05:35 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/199-A-Simple-PHP-Publish-Subscribe-System.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/199-A-Simple-PHP-Publish-Subscribe-System.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    I've been playing a lot with <a href="http://dojotoolkit.org/">Dojo</a>
    lately, and have been very impressed by its elegant publish-subscribe
    system. Basically, any object can publish an event, and any other object can
    subscribe to it. This creates an incredibly flexible notification
    architecture that's completely opt-in.
</p>

<p>
    The system has elements of Aspect Oriented Programming (AOP), as well as the
    Observer pattern. Its power, however, is in the fact that an individual
    object does not need to implement any specific interface in order to act as
    either a Subject or an Observer; the system is globally available.
</p>

<p>
    Being a developer who recognizes good ideas when he sees them, of course I
    decided to port the idea to PHP. You can see the results <a href="http://github.com/weierophinney/phly/tree/master/Phly_PubSub">on github</a>.
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Autocompletion with Zend Framework and Dojo</title>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2008 11:49:51 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/198-Autocompletion-with-Zend-Framework-and-Dojo.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/198-Autocompletion-with-Zend-Framework-and-Dojo.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    I've fielded several questions about setting up an autocompleter with
    <a href="http://framework.zend.com/">Zend Framework</a> and
    <a href="http://dojotoolkit.org/">Dojo</a>, and decided it was time to
    create a HOWTO on the subject, particularly as there are some nuances you
    need to pay attention to.
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tidings of the Season</title>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Dec 2008 23:48:16 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/196-Tidings-of-the-Season.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/196-Tidings-of-the-Season.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    Just about every day, I have an idea for a blog post, and most days, by the
    end of the day, I just don't have the time or energy to actually write
    anything up. The inner writer in me screams, "no excuses!" while the aging
    adult in me whispers, "time for bed, dear."
</p>

<p>
    So, to keep my hand in the game, here are a few things running through my
    head, or that I'm working on, or that I'll be doing soon.
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pastebin app updates</title>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Oct 2008 09:39:15 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/193-Pastebin-app-updates.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/193-Pastebin-app-updates.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    I've been getting a lot of interest in my 
    <a href="http://weierophinney.net/matthew/archives/189-Pastebin-app-and-conference-updates.html">Pastebin</a>
    demo app -- partly by those wanting to play with Dojo+ZF, partly by those
    just interested in the application.
</p>

<p>
    I'm constantly trying to improve the application. I've done one webinar and
    one UnCon session showcasing it, and will be presenting it at 
    <a href="http://dojotoolkit.org/2008/07/10/dojo-developer-day-boston">Dojo Develper Day in Boston</a> 
    this Monday as well as at 
    <a href="http://phpworks.mtacon.com/c/index">php|works</a> later this fall,
    and want to keep the materials up-to-date and freely available. To this end,
    I've created a <a href="http://github.com">Github</a> repository so you can
    track the latest developments, as well as pull custom tarballs:
</p>

<ul>
    <li><a href="http://github.com/weierophinney/pastebin/tree/master">Pastebin
    on Github</a></li>
</ul>

<p>
    All patches and feedback are welcome!
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ZendCon08 Wrapup</title>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Sep 2008 16:06:11 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/192-ZendCon08-Wrapup.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/192-ZendCon08-Wrapup.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    I'm a bit late on my <a href="http://www.zendcon.com/">ZendCon'08</a>
    wrapup; the conference left me both exhausted and with a backlog of email
    and work that has consumed me since it ended. However, this, too, is good,
    as it has given me time to reflect... and to finally get my slides up on
    SlideShare.
</p>

<p>
    ZendCon was alternately exhausting, rewarding, educational, fruitful,
    infurating, and ultimately wonderful. I've been to every single ZendCon so
    far -- I started at Zend a scant month before the inaugural event -- and
    have spoken at each. My first time speaking was a fluke; 
    <a href="http://www.sklar.com/">David Sklar</a> had just started at 
    <a href="http://www.ning.com/">Ning</a> and had to back out of his
    "Configuring PHP" tutorial session. 
    <a href="http://mikenaberezny.com/">Mike Naberezny</a> and I were drafted to
    take it over, and we had N+1 attendees, where N was the number of speakers.
    Since that inauspicious beginning, I've gradually taken on more sessions and
    stuck around to participate in the conference more. I can honestly say that
    this was the biggest, busiest, and most community focussed ZendCon I can
    remember.
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pastebin app and conference updates</title>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2008 05:15:30 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/189-Pastebin-app-and-conference-updates.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/189-Pastebin-app-and-conference-updates.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    I have a number of updates and followups, and decided to post them in a
    single entry.
</p>

<p>
    First off, you may now <a
        href="http://www.zend.com/en/webinar/Framework-Dojo/Webinar-Rec-Framework-Dev-EN-ZFDojo-20080903.flv">view
        my Dojo Webinar online</a> (requires login and registration at
    zend.com). Attendance was phenomenal, and I've had some really good
    feedback. If you want to see it live, I'm giving the talk (with revisions!)
    at the <a href="http://www.zendcon.com/">ZendCon</a> UnConference, at 
    <a href="http://dojotoolkit.org/2008/07/10/dojo-developer-day-boston">Dojo Developer Day Boston</a> 
    later this month, and at 
        <a href="http://phpworks.mtacon.com/c/schedule/talk/d1s5/1">php|works</a>
    in November. I hope to be able to show new functionality at each
    presentation.
</p>

<p>
    Second, I've completed what I'm calling version 1.0.0 of the pastebin
    application I demo'd in the webinar. The PHP code is fully unit tested
    (though I haven't yet delved into using DOH! to test the JS), and
    incorporates a number of best practices and tips that Pete Higgins from Dojo
    was kind enough to provide to me. When using a custom build (and I provide a
    profile for building one), it simply flies.
</p>

<ul>
    <li><a href="/uploads/pastebin-1.0.0.tar.gz">Download the pastebin
        application</a></li>
</ul>

<p>
    The pastebin application showcases a number of features besides Dojo:
    <code>Zend_Test_PHPUnit</code> was used to test the application,
    and <code>Zend_Wildfire</code>'s FireBug logger and DB profiler are used to
    provide profiling and debug information.
</p>

<p>
    Finally, <a href="http://www.zendcon.com/">ZendCon</a> is next week! I'll be
    around, but already have a packed schedule (1 tutorial, 2 regular sessions,
    an UnCon session, a meet-the-developers session... and that's just what I
    know about!). I look forward to meeting ZF users and developers, though, so
    feel free to grab me and introduce yourself.
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Proper Layer files when using Dojo with Zend Framework</title>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2008 13:17:34 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/188-Proper-Layer-files-when-using-Dojo-with-Zend-Framework.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/188-Proper-Layer-files-when-using-Dojo-with-Zend-Framework.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    During my <a href="http://www.zend.com/en/resources/webinars/framework">Dojo
        and ZF webinar</a> on Wednesday, 
    <a href="http://higginsforpresident.net/">Pete Higgins</a> of 
    <a href="http://dojotoolkit.org/">Dojo</a> fame noted that I could do
    something different and better on one of my slides.
</p>

<p>
    This particular item had to do with how I was consuming custom Dojo build
    layers within my code. I contacted him afterwards to find out what he
    suggested, and did a little playing of my own, and discovered some more Dojo
    and javascript beauty in the process.
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
