<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title type="text">Tag: dpc08 :: phly, boy, phly</title>
  <updated>2008-06-21T08:34:31+0000</updated>
  <generator uri="http://framework.zend.com" version="2.1.1dev">Zend_Feed_Writer</generator>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mwop.net/blog/tag/dpc08.html"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://mwop.net/blog/tag/dpc08-atom.xml"/>
  <id>http://mwop.net/blog/tag/dpc08.html</id>
  <entry xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[phpwomen at DPC08]]></title>
    <published>2008-06-20T17:30:01+0000</published>
    <updated>2008-06-21T08:34:31+0000</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mwop.net/blog/180-phpwomen-at-DPC08.html"/>
    <id>http://mwop.net/blog/180-phpwomen-at-DPC08.html</id>
    <author>
      <name>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</name>
      <email>me@mwop.net</email>
      <uri>http://mwop.net</uri>
    </author>
    <content xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" type="xhtml">
      <xhtml:div xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><xhtml:p>So, one thing I forgot to mention in my <xhtml:a href="http://weierophinney.net/matthew/archives/179-DPC08-Wrapup.html">DPC08
wrapup</xhtml:a> was my involvement with the <xhtml:a href="http://www.phpwomen.org/">phpwomen booth</xhtml:a>. <xhtml:a href="http://www.khankennels.com/blog/">Lig</xhtml:a> emailed me some months
in advance asking if I'd be an official "booth babe" while at the
conference -- basically wearing a T-shirt to show my support of the
movement, and answering any questions that others might have
regarding it. While I haven't been particularly active with
phpwomen, I of course agreed.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>As <xhtml:a href="http://www.lornajane.net/">Lorna Jane</xhtml:a> noted,
there were <xhtml:em>very</xhtml:em> few women at the conference. I'd say
estimating them at 2% of total attendees would very much be a
stretch. Also very strange was how little interest the phpwomen
booth attracted -- during those times I was at the booth, we'd get
a few people coming forward, but not many... and very few males.
This is very much in contrast to my observations at ZendCon last
year, when there were almost constantly folks at the booth, and
dozens of males were wearing the phpwomen t-shirts throughout the
conference.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>That said, one very funny picture came out of my participation,
snapped by <xhtml:a href="http://www.leftontheweb.com/">Stefan</xhtml:a>:</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:div style="text-align: center"><xhtml:img src="http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3114/2583600706_fa10962945.jpg?v=0" alt="Feeling lucky with the booth babe" height="500" width="375"/></xhtml:div>
<xhtml:p>I think it speaks for itself, no? :-)</xhtml:p>
</xhtml:div>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[DPC08 Wrapup]]></title>
    <published>2008-06-20T11:33:45+0000</published>
    <updated>2008-06-20T15:56:28+0000</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mwop.net/blog/179-DPC08-Wrapup.html"/>
    <id>http://mwop.net/blog/179-DPC08-Wrapup.html</id>
    <author>
      <name>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</name>
      <email>me@mwop.net</email>
      <uri>http://mwop.net</uri>
    </author>
    <content xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" type="xhtml">
      <xhtml:div xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><xhtml:p>Last Friday and Saturday I spent at <xhtml:a href="http://phpconference.nl/">the Dutch PHP Conference</xhtml:a>, hosted by
<xhtml:a href="http://ibuildings.nl/">Ibuildings</xhtml:a>. Unfortunately, I
had very little time to blog while there. I'd prepared my outlines
and basic slides before heading to the conference, but had a large
number of screenshots and images to prepare that kept me up until
the wee hours of the morning each day. In addition, the conference
was extremely well organized -- which meant that any time not spent
speaking was spent interacting with attendees or other speakers --
never a bad thing!</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>First off, the big impression I had when the conference finished
is that either PHP developers in Holland are incredibly
professional, or that the best practices advocated by various
community leaders are finally taking hold. My last talk was one
addressing development best practices, and I was constantly amazed
at how many people were <xhtml:em>already</xhtml:em> using most if not all the
best practices I touched on in my talk. This is really fantastic
news, as far as I'm concerned; hopefully all those PHP detractors
out there are going to start taking notice that PHP development has
matured, and, in fact become very quality oriented. Here's that
presentation:</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:div style="width:425px;text-align:left" id="__ss_472388">
<xhtml:object style="margin:0px" width="425" height="355"><xhtml:param name="movie" value="http://static.slideshare.net/swf/ssplayer2.swf?doc=20080614bestpractices-1213726335523088-9"/>
<xhtml:param name="allowFullScreen" value="true"/>
<xhtml:param name="allowScriptAccess" value="always"/>
<xhtml:embed src="http://static.slideshare.net/swf/ssplayer2.swf?doc=20080614bestpractices-1213726335523088-9" type="application/x-shockwave-flash" allowscriptaccess="always" allowfullscreen="true" width="425" height="355"/></xhtml:object>
<xhtml:div style="font-size:11px;font-family:tahoma,arial;height:26px;padding-top:2px;">
<xhtml:a href="http://www.slideshare.net/?src=embed"><xhtml:img src="http://static.slideshare.net/swf/logo_embd.png" style="border:0px none;margin-bottom:-5px" alt="SlideShare"/></xhtml:a> |
<xhtml:a href="http://www.slideshare.net/weierophinney/everyday-best-practices-of-php-development?src=embed" title="View Everyday Best Practices of PHP Development on SlideShare">View</xhtml:a>
| <xhtml:a href="http://www.slideshare.net/upload?src=embed">Upload your
own</xhtml:a></xhtml:div>
</xhtml:div>
<xhtml:p>The big event for me, of course, was the full day Zend Framework
workshop. My two regrets: a) not having a better script for the
final hour, when I covered a simple demo bugapp used for developing
the workshop, and b) running opposite <xhtml:a href="http://sebastian-bergmann.de">Sebastian Bergmann</xhtml:a> -- as I
wanted to see what he's been working on recently with <xhtml:a href="http://phpunit.de/">PHPUnit</xhtml:a>. That said, I feel the workshop
went over very well; I was able to finish each section early enough
that we had time for 5 - 15 minutes of questions over the material
just covered, and there were excellent questions from those
attending. The funny part was that with two of the questions, I
simply fired up my browser to the tutorials I wrote on <xhtml:a href="http://devzone.zend.com/">DevZone</xhtml:a>, and used the examples and
materials from them to answer the questions.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:div style="width:425px;text-align:left" id="__ss_472382">
<xhtml:object style="margin:0px" width="425" height="355"><xhtml:param name="movie" value="http://static.slideshare.net/swf/ssplayer2.swf?doc=20080613zendframeworkworkshop-1213725963433006-9"/>
<xhtml:param name="allowFullScreen" value="true"/>
<xhtml:param name="allowScriptAccess" value="always"/>
<xhtml:embed src="http://static.slideshare.net/swf/ssplayer2.swf?doc=20080613zendframeworkworkshop-1213725963433006-9" type="application/x-shockwave-flash" allowscriptaccess="always" allowfullscreen="true" width="425" height="355"/></xhtml:object>
<xhtml:div style="font-size:11px;font-family:tahoma,arial;height:26px;padding-top:2px;">
<xhtml:a href="http://www.slideshare.net/?src=embed"><xhtml:img src="http://static.slideshare.net/swf/logo_embd.png" style="border:0px none;margin-bottom:-5px" alt="SlideShare"/></xhtml:a> |
<xhtml:a href="http://www.slideshare.net/weierophinney/zend-framework-workshop?src=embed" title="View Zend Framework Workshop on SlideShare">View</xhtml:a> |
<xhtml:a href="http://www.slideshare.net/upload?src=embed">Upload your
own</xhtml:a></xhtml:div>
</xhtml:div>
<xhtml:p>As promised, I've <xhtml:a href="/uploads/bugapp.tar.gz">uploaded the
bug application</xhtml:a> I worked up to create the session. Be aware
that it's incomplete; the main thing was to see how each of the
various pieces could interact so I'd know what to cover and when in
the workshop.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Following the night of the workshops, Ibuildings had a dinner
for their employees, and I was invited to tag along. I had some
great conversations with <xhtml:a href="http://www.lornajane.net">Lorna
Jane</xhtml:a> and one of her colleagues, Bill, discussing topics ranging
from family to training, from travel to PHP, and more. Dinner was
timed to end as the big match between Holland and France began, and
all I have to say about that is: if you've never witnessed the fans
of a big football match in Holland when Oranje is winning, you
haven't lived. 'Nuff said. :-)</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>I had a number of good conversations with a variety of people,
really -- <xhtml:a href="http://inside.e-novative.de/">Stefan
Priebsch</xhtml:a>, <xhtml:a href="http://sebastian-bergmann.de/">Sebastian</xhtml:a>, <xhtml:a href="http://suraski.net/blog/">Zeev</xhtml:a>, <xhtml:a href="http://mtabini.blogspot.com">Marco Tabini</xhtml:a>, Lorna Jane, Stefan
Koopfmanschap, <xhtml:a href="http://www.aide-de-camp.org/">Fabien
Potencier</xhtml:a>, and more. (Believe it or not, you <xhtml:em>can</xhtml:em> get
more than one framework lead in the same room and have things stay
civil; Fabien and I swapped some information regarding plans for
our next major releases, what issues we've seen, and what features
we're excited about.) <xhtml:a href="http://felix.phpbelgium.be/blog/">Felix De Vliegher</xhtml:a> and
<xhtml:a href="http://www.dragonbe.com/">Michelangelo Van Damme</xhtml:a> were
also there, representing PHP Belgium, and it was great to hear how
their region's PHP community is starting to come together.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>I also got a chance to meet a few people from the Zend Framework
lists and IRC in person: Andries Seutens, Jurrien Stutterheim, and
Bart McLeod -- and a few others whose names I most regrettably
forget. I wish I could have had more time to talk with each of you,
and discuss your projects more.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Now, while the conference was fantastic, probably the best part
for me personally was the day prior. My good friend <xhtml:a href="http://www.wolerized.com/">Remi</xhtml:a>, with whom I've worked on some
projects at Zend a number of times over the past year, came up from
Gouda to hang with me for the day. We walked all over the city --
through the Vondelpark, up by the Rijksmuseum and Van Gogh museums,
along and over countless canals, near (but not through) the red
light district, by the RAI (where the conference was held) and all
the way up to Grand Centraal. I complained about sore feet and legs
all weekend, but it was the best tour I could have imagined of the
city, and one I shan't forget any time soon. And the reason we went
to Grand Centraal was to meet up with <xhtml:a href="http://www.leftontheweb.com/">Stefan Koopmanschap</xhtml:a>, with whom
we would then have dinner and drinks that night. I feel very
fortunate to have had the chance to spend some uninterrupted time
with each of these fantastic developers and individuals.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>So, the short summary: excellent conference, excellent friends,
excellent city. Looking forward to DPC '09!</xhtml:p>
</xhtml:div>
    </content>
  </entry>
</feed>
