<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title type="text">Tag: dpc10 :: phly, boy, phly</title>
  <updated>2010-04-20T13:35:46+0000</updated>
  <generator uri="http://framework.zend.com" version="2.0.2">Zend_Feed_Writer</generator>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mwop.net/blog/tag/dpc10.html"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://mwop.net/blog/tag/dpc10-atom.xml"/>
  <id>http://mwop.net/blog/tag/dpc10.html</id>
  <entry xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[PHP Invades Amsterdam; or, the Dutch PHP Conference]]></title>
    <published>2010-04-20T03:58:37+0000</published>
    <updated>2010-04-20T13:35:46+0000</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mwop.net/blog/239-PHP-Invades-Amsterdam;-or,-the-Dutch-PHP-Conference.html"/>
    <id>http://mwop.net/blog/239-PHP-Invades-Amsterdam;-or,-the-Dutch-PHP-Conference.html</id>
    <author>
      <name>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</name>
      <email>me@mwop.net</email>
      <uri>http://mwop.net</uri>
    </author>
    <content xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" type="xhtml">
      <xhtml:div xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><xhtml:p>For the third year running, I'm pleased to be speaking at the
<xhtml:a href="http://phpconference.nl/">Dutch PHP Conference</xhtml:a>, held
again in Amsterdam this coming 10-12 of June.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p style="text-align:center"><xhtml:a href="http://phpconference.nl/" title="2010 Dutch PHP Conference"><xhtml:img src="/uploads/dpc10_speaker.jpg"/></xhtml:a></xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Once again, I'll be doing another <xhtml:a href="http://framework.zend.com/">Zend Framework</xhtml:a> workshop, but this
year I'll be teaming up with <xhtml:a href="http://akrabat.com/">Rob
Allen</xhtml:a>. Our focus this year will be on oft-used application
patterns found in the ZF ecosystem, and how you can weave them
together to create complex and robust applications.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>I'm also presenting two regular sessions. The first is a session
on writing RESTful web services with Zend Framework. My goal is to
show you a handful of techniques that should get you up and
running, building RESTful applications that can respond to normal
HTML requests as well as XML and JSON payloads with a minimum of
effort.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>My second session will be a continuation of my "Models" talk,
but this time looking at domain models from the perspective of
NoSQL databases. "NoSQL" means "Not Only SQL", and refers to the
new proliferation of data stores that focus on key/value storage
and document storage. They offer some new paradigms to how we store
and retrieve data, and also introduce some potentially more
flexible, lightweight ways to map your domain objects to the data
store.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>There will be a ton of great speakers at DPC again this year --
from stalwart PHP veterans such as Chris Shiflett and Sebastian
Bergmann to core PHP developers like Scott MacVicar, Ilia
Alshanetsky and Melanie Rhianna Lewis, and many, many more. It's
not one to miss!</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Hoping to meet <xhtml:em>you</xhtml:em> in Amsterdam this June!</xhtml:p>
</xhtml:div>
    </content>
  </entry>
</feed>
