<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/">
  <channel>
    <title>Tag: family :: phly, boy, phly</title>
    <description>Tag: family :: phly, boy, phly</description>
    <pubDate>Sat, 10 Dec 2005 22:00:15 +0000</pubDate>
    <generator>Zend_Feed_Writer 2.1.1dev (http://framework.zend.com)</generator>
    <link>http://mwop.net/blog/tag/family.html</link>
    <atom:link rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" href="http://mwop.net/blog/tag/family-rss.xml"/>
    <item>
      <title>Name recognition</title>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Dec 2005 22:00:15 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/102-Name-recognition.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/102-Name-recognition.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    Don't know if this is actually possible, but it appears Liam is already
    starting to associate names with people!
</p>
<p>
    Just now, Jen was holding Liam, and turned him to face Maeve and I, who were
    sitting on the couch. He wasn't looking anywhere in particular. Then, Jen
    said, "Hi, Papa!" and his eyes moved to focus on me. A moment later, she
    said, "Hi, big sister!" and he moved is eyes to focus on Maeve.
</p>
<p>
    As I type this, Jen just tried the experiment again with Maeve, and again he
    moved his eyes and head to look at her!
</p>
<p>
    How cool and amazing it is to witness child development!
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Safari</title>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Jul 2005 03:16:59 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/87-On-Safari.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/87-On-Safari.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    This past year, Maeve had a month-long unit on Safaris and jungle animals at
    daycare. One day, she came home singing:
</p>
<blockquote><i>
        On Safari, on Safari,<br />
        In a jeep, in a jeep,<br />
        I can see a lion, I will take a picture,<br />
        Click, click, click. Click, click, click.<br />
        <br />
        On Safari, on Safari,<br />
        In a jeep, in a jeep,<br />
        I can see a tiger, I will take a picture,<br />
        Click, click, click. Click, click, click.
</i></blockquote>
<p>
    And so on.
</p>
<p>
    There's a place just over the Quebec border called <a
    href="http://www.parcsafari.com">Parc Safari</a> that we've been hearing
    about, and today we went up there on a family outing -- one of the last that
    we'll have with just the three of us (before little Liam is born).
</p><blockquote><i>
        On Safari, on Safari,<br />
        In our Matrix, in our Matrix,<br />
        I can see a zebra, I will take a picture,<br />
        Click, click, click. Click, click, click.<br />
</i></blockquote>
<p>
    Needless to say, the excursion was a hit for the whole family. The park has
    a drive-through safari adventure where you drive your car through a small
    preserve, looking at animals and even getting a chance to feed some of them.
    We saw zebras, elephants, rhinos, ostriches, water buffalo, ibexes, camels,
    giraffes, emu, oryx, reindeer, caribou, elk, bison, yaks, wildebeests... and
    many more that I'm either forgetting or didn't know the names of. 
</p>
<p>
    The highlight of the safari was probably towards the end, when we each of us
    got chances to feed bison from the car -- try <em>that</em> in Yellowstone!
    The bison were surprisingly gentle, and typically tried to take the food
    nuggets from your hand with their lips, but the greedier ones used their
    tongues and tended to exude tremendous amounts of slobber in the process.
</p>
<p>
    (My personal favorite, though, was getting the chance to stroke a camel's
    whiskers. I don't know why, but it was just one of those great moments.)
</p>
<p>
    Parc Safari also has a small amusement park, with very cheap prices ($2
    Canadian per person for all day access to all rides), so Maeve got a chance
    to ride to her hearts delight. She and I went on the Ferris wheel together,
    and had an excellent time waving at Jen, who awaited us below.
</p>
<p>
    If we had any doubts about Maeve enjoying it, they were allayed when,
    shortly after crossing the US border, we looked back in time to see Maeve
    pass out from sheer exhaustion. What a sweet kid... the chocolate from the
    ice cream was still smudged on her cheek, and her hand was gripping her
    memento rock.
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>&amp;quot;I'm so right&amp;quot;</title>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jul 2005 20:23:56 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/86-Im-so-right.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/86-Im-so-right.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    Not long ago, as Maeve and I were en route to Jen's work one evening, Maeve
    was being very insistent that certain things were a certain way, and was
    very adamant even as I used a placating tone with her. I asked her,
    jokingly, "Why are you so contrary today?" Her reply?
</p>
<p>
    "Because I'm so smart, and because I'm so right."
</p>
<p>
    I almost wrecked the car as I guffawed. Kids. They're so dang cute. And so
    right!
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Every little girl has to give up the bink...</title>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jul 2005 03:31:54 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/82-Every-little-girl-has-to-give-up-the-bink....html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/82-Every-little-girl-has-to-give-up-the-bink....html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
So, last night, Maeve fell asleep in the early evening, on the couch, clutching
her sippy cup and sucking on her bink while watching Scooby Doo. She woke up an
hour later, and after she'd been up for a while and was less groggy, she
announced to Jen and me that, "I'm not going to use my bink ANY MORE. Every
little girl has to give up the bink some time, when they're four, so I'm not
going to use the bink EVER AGAIN." (Imagine dramatic pauses between the all-caps
words there...)
</p>

<p>
This coming from the girl who has a fit every time her bink isn't within
eyesight and reach. Needless to say, we didn't quite believe her, but we were
willing to support her. We told her that if she wants to stop using the bink,
that's okay; it's also okay if she decides to use it again. (Fully expecting
she'd want it within minutes of going to bed.)
</p>

<p>
Well... Maeve slept all night without it, and didn't want it this morning, nor
in the car. She's adamant, our little warrior queen! (Which is what the Gaelic
Maeve translates to in English, in case you were wondering.)
</p>

<p>
I might be jumping the gun here, but I get the feeling our little girl has taken
another step in growing up... and I'm bewildered and a little sad. Much as I've
hated the bink the past year, I also associate it with my little girl... and
she's getting so she's not so little any more!
</p>
<p>
<b>UPDATE:</b> I jumped the gun. She <em>did</em> go a full 24 hours, but the
following night decided she wanted the bink again. But there <em>is</em> hope
for a bink-less future... 
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
