<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/">
  <channel>
    <title>Tag: linux :: phly, boy, phly</title>
    <description>Tag: linux :: phly, boy, phly</description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 25 Mar 2010 10:57:03 +0000</pubDate>
    <generator>Zend_Feed_Writer 2.0.0beta5 (http://framework.zend.com)</generator>
    <link>http://mwop.net/blog/tag/linux.html</link>
    <atom:link rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" href="http://mwop.net/blog/tag/linux-rss.xml"/>
    <item>
      <title>GPG-signing Git Commits</title>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Mar 2010 10:57:03 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/236-GPG-signing-Git-Commits.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/236-GPG-signing-Git-Commits.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    We're working on migrating <a href="http://framework.zend.com/">Zend
        Framework</a> to <a href="http://git-scm.org/">Git</a>. One issue we're
    trying to deal with is enforcing that commits come from <acronym
        title="Contributor License Agreement">CLA</acronym> signees.
</p>

<p>
    One possibility presented to us was the possibility of utilizing
    <acronym title="GNU Privacy Guard">GPG</acronym> signing of commit messages.
    Unfortunately, I was able to find little to no information on the 'net about
    how this might be done, so I started to experiment with some solutions.
</p>

<p>
    The approach I chose utilizes <a
        href="http://www.kernel.org/pub/software/scm/git/docs/githooks.html">git
        hooks</a>, specifically the <code>commit-msg</code> hook client-side,
    and the <code>pre-receive</code> hook server-side.
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enabling VPN split tunnel with NetworkManager</title>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Aug 2009 19:34:37 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/223-Enabling-VPN-split-tunnel-with-NetworkManager.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/223-Enabling-VPN-split-tunnel-with-NetworkManager.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    I've been using <a
        href="http://projects.gnome.org/NetworkManager/">NetworkManager</a> for
    some time now, and appreciate how easy it makes both connecting to wifi as
    well as VPNs. That said, I've had an issue with it that I only resolved
    today.
</p>

<p>
    When working from home, I prefer to use a VPN split tunnel setup -- I'm
    behind a firewall all the time, and it's useful to be able to run virtual
    machines while still connected to my VPN (e.g., when doing training or
    webinar sessions). However, I noticed some months ago that this wasn't
    working. I assumed at first it was a change in our network setup, but others
    reported that the split tunnel was working fine. It's been particularly
    problematic when on IRC -- if the VPN drops, I lose my IRC connection,
    meaning I have to re-connect and re-claim my nick.
</p>

<p>
    So, I did some searching, and found an interesting setting. In
    NetworkManager, "Configure..." then "Edit" your VPN connection,
    and navigate to the "IPv4 Settings" tab. Once there, click the button that
    says "Routes..." and select the checkbox next to "Use this connection only
    for resources on its network". Press Ok to close the dialog, then "Apply" to
    exit out of the VPN configuration. Re-connect to the VPN, and you should be
    all set.
</p>

<p>
    <em>Note: this will only work if your VPN server is configured to allow
    split tunnels. Additionally, only do so if you are behind a firewall.
    Practice safe networking.</em>
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VirtualBox Networking</title>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2009 15:43:40 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/205-VirtualBox-Networking.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/205-VirtualBox-Networking.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    I use Linux on the desktop (currently <a href="http://www.ubuntu.com/">Ubuntu</a>), 
    but occasionally need to use Windows for things like webinars, OS-specific
    testing, etc. I started using <a href="http://virtualbox.org/">VirtualBox</a> 
    for virtualization around six months ago, and have been reasonably
    satisfied; Windows boots quickly, and everything "just works." That is,
    until yesterday.
</p>

<p>
    I was given a linux VM image running a web server and some applications I
    needed to review. On top of that, I needed to do so over WebEx, so that I
    could share my screen with somebody else. This meant I needed the following
    to work:
</p>

<ol>
    <li>Internet access for my Windows VM</li>
    <li>Access to my linux VM from my Windows VM</li>
    <li>Ideally, access to both guest VMs from my linux host</li>
    <li>Ideally, internet access for my linux host</li>
</ol>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Server Upgrades... lost entries...</title>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2008 18:35:27 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/171-Server-Upgrades...-lost-entries....html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/171-Server-Upgrades...-lost-entries....html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    My good friend, Rob, hosts my site for me, in return for helping with server
    maintenance. After being on Gentoo for the past three years, though, we
    decided it was time to switch to something a little easier to maintain, so
    last night we wiped the system partitions and installed Ubuntu server.
</p>

<p>
    I'll say this: the setup is much faster! However, we had a few gotchas that
    surprised us -- it didn't setup our RAID array out-of-the-box, which led to
    a good hour of frustration as we tried to verify that the install wouldn't
    wipe it, and then to verify that we could re-assemble it.  (We succeeded.)
    Additionally, we second-guessed a few things we shouldn't have, which led to
    needing to back out and reconfigure. But what was over a 12 hour install
    with Gentoo we accomplished in a matter of a few hours with Ubuntu server --
    so it was a huge success that way.
</p>

<p>
    Unfortunately, our mysqldump of all databases... wasn't, a fact we
    discovered only after importing it into the new system. I ended up losing my
    blog database and PEAR channel database. Fortunately, the PEAR channel
    has not changed at all in the past year, so we had an old backup that
    worked, and I had a snapshot of my blog database from three weeks ago I was
    able to use. As a result, there are a few missing entries, but for the most
    part, all works. If you commented on one of those missing entries, my
    apologies.
</p>

<p>
    Now that the install is done, I'm also finalizing some design changes to my
    blog -- it's time to leave the black and white for more colorful grounds.
    Look for a revamp in the coming weeks!
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Apache HOSTNAME on Clusters</title>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Jan 2008 13:22:44 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/156-Apache-HOSTNAME-on-Clusters.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/156-Apache-HOSTNAME-on-Clusters.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    In an effort to debug issues on a cluster, I was trying to determine which
    machine on the cluster was causing the issue. My idea was that I could
    insert a header token identifying the server.
</p>

<p>
    My first idea was to add the directive 'Header add X-Server-Ip
    "%{SERVER_ADDR}e" in my httpd.conf. However, due to the nature of our load
    balancer, Apache was somehow resolving this to the load balancer IP address
    on all machines of the cluster -- which was really, really not useful.
</p>

<p>
    I finally stumbled on a good solution, however: you can set environment
    variables in apachectl, and then pass them into the Apache environment using
    the PassEnv directive from mod_env; once that's done, you can use the
    environment variable anywhere.
</p>

<p>
    In my apachectl, I added the line "export HOSTNAME=`hostname`". Then, in my
    httpd.conf, I added first the line "PassEnv HOSTNAME", followed by the
    directive 'Header add X-Server-Name "%{HOSTNAME}e"'. Voila! I now had the
    hostname in the header, which gave me the information I needed for
    debugging.
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gutsy Gibbon review</title>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Oct 2007 20:38:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/147-Gutsy-Gibbon-review.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/147-Gutsy-Gibbon-review.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    Early in the week, I decided to avoid the release rush and go ahead and
    update my laptop to <a href="http://www.ubuntu.com">Ubuntu's</a> Gutsy 
    Gibbon release. Overall, it's quite good, with one caveat I'll elaborate on
    later. 
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Back on Linux Again</title>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 May 2007 15:03:06 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/136-Back-on-Linux-Again.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/136-Back-on-Linux-Again.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    A little over a year ago, <a href="http://weierophinney.net/matthew/archives/101-Using-Windows-XP.html">I stopped using Linux as my primary desktop</a> 
    due to the fact that a number of programs we were using were Windows
    dependent. Despite 
    <a href="http://weierophinney.net/matthew/archives/103-XP-+-Cygwin-+-coLinux-Productivity.html">getting coLinux running</a>,
    I've never been completely satisfied with the setup. I missed being able to
    paste with my middle-mouse button, and I was constantly having character
    encoding issues pasting back and forth between PuTTY and windows apps,
    couldn't access mail easily between my coLinux and Windows partitions, and
    overall felt that I was losing out on some productivity by not having a
    native linux environment as my primary OS.
</p>
<p>
    Last week, we had an infrastructure change at work, and I basically realized
    that my Windows + coLinux setup was going to get in the way of productivity
    -- and that, at this point, there were now Windows applications tying me to
    that OS. So, I decided it was time to go back to Linux.
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>coLinux Recovery</title>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Sep 2006 21:27:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/124-coLinux-Recovery.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/124-coLinux-Recovery.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    As <a href="http://weierophinney.net/matthew/archives/103-XP-+-Cygwin-+-coLinux-Productivity.html">I've written previously,</a>
    I use <a href="http://www.colinux.org">coLinux</a> in order to have a
    Linux virtual machine running on my Windows XP install. It runs Debian
    unstable (SID), which gives me all apt-geet love I could want.
</p>
<p>
    Except when an apt-get based install goes bad, that is, like it did Saturday
    evening. This is the tale of how I got it back up and running.
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>XP + Cygwin + coLinux == Productivity</title>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jan 2006 19:58:23 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/103-XP-+-Cygwin-+-coLinux-Productivity.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/103-XP-+-Cygwin-+-coLinux-Productivity.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    I wrote earlier of my experiences <a href="http://weierophinney.net/matthew/archives/101-Using-Windows-XP.html">using Windows XP</a>,
    a move I've considered somewhat unfortunate but necessary. I've added a
    couple more tools to my toolbox since that have made the environment even
    better.
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>File_SMBPasswd woes</title>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Sep 2005 13:50:23 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/93-File_SMBPasswd-woes.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/93-File_SMBPasswd-woes.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    I've been cobbling together a system at work for the last couple months to
    allow a single place for changing all network passwords. This includes a
    variety of database sources, as well as <i>passwd</i> files and
    <i>smbpasswd</i> files.
    I've been making use of PEAR's <a href="http://pear.php.net/package/File_Passwd">File_Passwd</a> and <a href="http://pear.php.net/package/File_SMBPasswd">File_SMBPasswd</a>, and they've
    greatly simplified the task of updating passwords for those types of
    systems. However, I've encountered some issues that I never would have
    expected.
</p>
<p>
    I have the web user in a group called 'samba', and I have the
    <i>smbpasswd</i> file owned by root:samba. I then set the <i>smbpasswd</i>
    file to be group +rw. Simple, right? The web user should then be able to
    update the <i>smbpasswd</i> file without a problem, right? Wrong.
</p>
<p>
    I kept getting errors, and on investigation continually found that the
    <i>smbpasswd</i> file permissions had reverted to 0600 -- i.e., only the
    root user could access it. I tried using 'chattr -i' on the off-chance that
    the file had been made immutable (which didn't make sense, as I was able to
    see the permissions change). No luck.
</p>
<p>
    Based on observations of when the permissions reverted, it appears that the
    various SMB processes will reset the permissions! An example is when
    someone attempts to mount a resource from the server; this accesses the
    smbpasswd file to perform authentication -- and at this point the file
    permissions change.  I can find no documentation to support this; these are
    simply my observations.
</p>
<p>
    So, to get around the behaviour, I created a script that will set the file
    permissions to what I want them, and then gave <i>sudo</i> privileges to the
    samba group for that script. This script is then called via <i>system()</i>
    in the update script just before processing.
</p>
<p>
    It's a hack, and could be made more secure, but it works.
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
