<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/">
  <channel>
    <title>Tag: perl :: phly, boy, phly</title>
    <description>Tag: perl :: phly, boy, phly</description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jun 2012 02:50:00 +0000</pubDate>
    <generator>Zend_Feed_Writer 2 (http://framework.zend.com)</generator>
    <link>http://mwop.net/blog/tag/perl.html</link>
    <atom:link rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" href="http://mwop.net/blog/tag/perl-rss.xml"/>
    <item>
      <title>Automatic deployment with git and gitolite</title>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jun 2012 02:50:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/2012-06-24-git-deploy.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/2012-06-24-git-deploy.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    I read a <a 
    href="http://seancoates.com/blogs/deploy-on-push-from-github" 
    target="_blank">post recently by Sean Coates about deploy on 
    push</a>. The concept is nothing new: you set up a hook that 
    listens for commits on specific branches or tags, and it then
    deploys your site from that revision.
</p>

<p>
    Except I'd not done it myself. This is how I got there.
</p><p>
    Sean's approach uses <a href="https://help.github.com/articles/post-receive-hooks" target="_blank">Github webhooks</a>,
    which are a fantastic concept. Basically, once your commit completes, Github
    will send a JSON-encoded payload to a specific URI. Sean uses this to 
    trigger an API call to a specific page in his website, which will then
    trigger a deployment activity.
</p>

<p>
    Awesome, this should be easy; I already have a deploy script written
    that I trigger manually.
</p>

<p>
    One small problem: my site, while in Git, is not on Github. I maintain
    it on my own <a href="https://github.com/sitaramc/gitolite" target="_blank">Gitolite</a>
    repository. Which means I needed to write my own hooks.
</p>

<p>
    I originally went down the route of using a post-receive hook. However,
    I had problems determining what branch the given commit was on, despite
    a variety of advice I found on the subject on 
    <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/" target="_blank">StackOverflow</a> and git mailing
    lists. I ended up finding a great example using post-update, which
    was actually perfect for my needs.
</p>

<p>
    In order to keep the post-update script non-blocking when I commit, I made 
    it do very little: It simply determines what branch the commit was on, and if
    it was the master branch, it touches a specific file on the filesystem and
    finishes. The entire hook looks like this:
</p>

<div class="example"><pre>
#!/bin/bash
branch=$(git rev-parse --symbolic --abbrev-ref $1)
echo "Commit was for branch $branch"
if [[ "$branch" == "master" ]];then
    echo "Preparing to deploy"
    echo "1" > /var/local/mwop.net.update
fi
</pre></div>

<p>
    Now I needed something to detect such a push, and act on it.
</p>

<p>
    I considered using cron for this; it'd be relatively easy to have it fire
    up once a minute, and simply act on it. But I decided instead to write a 
    simple little daemon using perl. Perl daemons are trivially easy to write,
    and if you use module such as <code>Proc::Daemon</code> and follow a few
    trivial defensive coding practices, you can keep memory leaks contained (or
    at least minimal). Besides, it gave me a chance to dust off my perl chops.
</p>

<p>
    I decided I'd have it check for the file in 30 second intervals, simply
    sleeping if no changes were detected. If the file was found, however, it
    should attempt to deploy. Additionally, I wanted it to quit if it was
    unable to remove the file (as this could lead to multiple deploy attempts),
    and log success and failure status of the deploy. The full script looks like
    this:
</p>

<div class="example"><pre>
#!/usr/bin/perl
use strict;
use warnings;
use Proc::Daemon;

Proc::Daemon::Init;

my $continue = 1;
$SIG{TERM} = sub { $continue = 0 };

my $updateFile   = "/var/local/mwop.net.update";
my $updateScript = "/home/matthew/bin/deploy-mwop";
my $logFile      = "/var/local/mwop.net-deploy.log";
while ($continue) {
    # 30s intervals between iterations
    sleep 30;

    # Check for update file, and restart loop if not found
    unless (-e $updateFile) {
        next;
    }

    # Remove update file
    if (!unlink($updateFile)) {
        # If unable to unlink, we need to quit
        system('echo "' . time() . ': Failed to REMOVE ' . $updateFile . '" >> ' . $logFile);
        $continue = 0;
        next;
    }

    # Deploy
    system($updateScript);
    if ( $? == -1 ) {
        system('echo "' . time() . ': FAILED to deploy: ' . $! . '" >> ' .  $logFile);
    } else {
        system('echo "' . time() . ': Successfully DEPLOYED" >> ' . $logFile);
    }
}
</pre></div>

<p>
    The <code>system()</code> calls for logging could have been done using 
    Perl, but I didn't want to deal with additional error handling and file
    pointers; simply proxying to the system seemed reasonable and expedient.
</p>

<p>
    When all was ready, I started the above listener, which automatically
    daemonizes itself. I then installed the post-update hook into my bare
    repository, and tested it out. And it runs! When I push to master, my
    site is automatically deployed, typically within 15-20 seconds from
    completion.
</p>

<h4>Caveats</h4>

<p>
    This solution, of course, relies on a daemonized process. If that process
    were to terminate, I'd have no idea until I discovered my site didn't
    refresh after the most recent push. Clearly, some sort of monitor checking
    for the status of the daemon should be in place.
</p>

<p>
    Also, note that I'm having this update on changes to the master branch;
    you may need to adapt it for your own needs, depending on your branching
    strategy.
</p>

<p>
    Finally, this approach does not address issues that might require a 
    roll-back. Ideally, the script should probably log what revision was 
    current prior to the deployment, allowing roll-back to the previous
    state. Alternately, the deployment script should create a new clone
    of the site and swap symlinks to allow quick roll-back when required.
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why Conventions Matter</title>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jan 2012 03:58:28 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/why-conventions-matter.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/why-conventions-matter.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    When I started teaching myself scripting languages, I started with Perl. One
    Perl motto is <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/TMTOWTDI">"TMTOWTDI"</a>
    -- "There's More Than One Way To Do It," and pronounced "tim-toady." The
    idea is that there's likely multiple ways to accomplish the very same thing,
    and the culture of the language encourages finding novel ways to do things.
</p>

<p>
    I've seen this principle used everywhere and in just about every programming
    situation possible, applied to logical operations, naming conventions,
    formatting, and even project structure.  Everyone has an opinion on these
    topics, and given free rein to implement as they see fit, it's rare that two
    developers will come up with the same conventions.
</p>

<p>
    TMTOWTDI is an incredibly freeing and egalitarian principle.
</p>

<p>
    Over the years, however, my love for TMTOWTDI has diminished some.  Freeing
    as it is, is also a driving force behind having coding standards and
    conventions -- because when everyone does it their own way, projects become
    quickly hard to maintain. Each person finds themselves reformatting code to
    their own standards, simply so they can read it and follow its flow.
</p>

<p>
    Additionally, TMTOWTDI can actually be a foe of simple, elegant solutions.
</p>

<p>
    Why do I claim this?
</p><p>
    Recently, discussing module structure in Zend Framework 2, some folks were
    arguing that our recommended directory structure invokes the <a
        href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/YAGNI">YAGNI</a> principle: You Ain't
    Gonna Need It.  Our recommendation is this:
</p>

<div class="example"><pre>
ModuleName/
    autoload_classmap.php
    Module.php
    config/
        module.config.php
        (other config files)
    public/
        css/
        images/
        js/
    src/
        ModuleName/
            (source files)
    test/
    view/
</pre></div>

<p>
    The argument is that since most modules implement a single namespace, and
    because we recommend following <a
        href="https://github.com/php-fig/fig-standards/blob/master/accepted/PSR-0.md">PSR-0</a>
    for autoloaders, it makes sense to simply have the source files directly
    under the module directory.
</p>

<div class="example"><pre>
ModuleName/
    autoload_classmap.php
    Module.php
    (other source files)
    config/
        module.config.php
        (other config files)
    public/
    test/
    view/
</pre></div>

<p>
    The argument myself and others made was that it makes sense to group the
    files by responsibility. However, the module system ultimately <em>doesn't
        care</em> how you organize the module -- we've embraced TMTOWTDI, and
    our only requirement is that for your module to be consumed, you must define
    a <code>ModuleName\Module</code> class, and notify the module manager how to
    find it. Anything goes.
</p>

<p>
    How does that bolster my argument about the importance of conventions? It
    doesn't. What does is what following the recommended structure enabled me to
    do.
</p>

<p>
    One common concern identified with having a re-usable module system is that
    you should be able to expose public assets easily: things like
    module-specific CSS or JavaScript, or even images. The first question that
    arises when you consider this is: where do I put them in my module? That's
    why the recommendation includes a <code>public</code> directory. In fact,
    the recommendation goes a step further, and suggests <code>css</code>,
    <code>images</code>, and <code>js</code> directories as well.
</p>

<p>
    Now, your modules are typically <em>outside</em> the document root. This is
    a rudimentary and fundamental security measure, and also simplifies
    deployment to a degree -- you don't need to worry about telling the web
    server about what it <em>shouldn't</em> serve. But if the modules are
    outside the document root, how can I expose their public assets?
</p>

<p>
    There are a two possibilities that immediately jump to mind:
</p>

<ul>
    <li>Install scripts for modules, which copy the files into the document root.</li>
    <li>Symlink the files into the document root.</li>
</ul>

<p>
    Both are valid, and easy to accomplish. Both raise the same question: where,
    exactly? What if multiple modules have public assets named the same? how do
    I refer to my assets withing things like view scripts?
</p>

<p>
    This is where having a convention starts to make sense: having a convention
    should answer these questions unambiguously.
</p>

<p>
    My answer: public access should be at
    <code>/css/ModuleName/stylesheetname</code>, or
    <code>/js/ModuleName/scriptname</code> or
    <code>/images/Modulename/imagename</code>. It's a dirt-simple rule that
    fulfills the use cases.
</p>

<p>
    However, I'm now stuck with having to develop either install scripts or
    remembering to create symlinks -- ugh. And that's where having conventions
    led me to a simple, elegant solution.
</p>

<p>
    I added one line to my Apache vhost definition:
</p>

<div class="example"><pre>
AliasMatch /(css|js|images)/([^/]+)/(.*) /path/to/module/$2/public/$1/$3
</pre></div>

<p>
    The translation:
</p>

<blockquote>
    When I come across a path to CSS, JS, or image files that are in a
    subdirectory, alias it to the corresponding public asset of the matched
    module directory.
</blockquote>

<p>
    I dropped this into my vhost, restarted Apache, and now not only were the
    assets I'd created already served, but any new ones I create are immediately
    available as well. Having a convention actually simplified my choices and my
    solutions.
</p>

<p>
    Rapid application development at its finest.
</p>

<p>
    My point is this: there will always be more than one way to do things when
    you're programming, and you may not always agree with the decisions your
    team has made, or the component library or framework you're using has made.
    However, if you poke around a little and play within those confines, you may
    find that those decisions make other decisions easier, or disappear
    altogether.
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Seven Things - Tagged by Keith Casey</title>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Jan 2009 21:31:52 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/204-Seven-Things-Tagged-by-Keith-Casey.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/204-Seven-Things-Tagged-by-Keith-Casey.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    I'm really not sure I understand these "seven things" or "tagged" memes, but
    I'm going to give it a shot, after 
    <a href="http://caseysoftware.com/blog/seven-things-tagged-by-tony-bibbs">Keith Casey</a> did a drive-by
    tagging of me on New Year's Eve.
</p>

<p>
    So, without further ado, seven things you may not know about me...
</p><ul>
    <li>
        <em>My actual college degree is in comparative religion.</em> I ended up
        in the Religion department at the 
        <a href="http://www.ups.edu/">University of Puget Sound</a> (yes, the
        initials are UPS, which can easily cause confusion with brown,
        parcel-bearing trucks), due to a line of questioning that occurred
        during an Artificial Intelligence course I was taking. The instructor
        was asking if there would be any ethical barrier to unplugging an AI --
        i.e., since it would be capable of thought, would this be equivalent to
        "killing" it? My initial response was, "No," because humans consist of
        more than thought... and then I started wondering a bit about that. My
        emphasis in religion was in Eastern religions. I have a minor in
        Mathematics (CS at UPS was actually CS/Mathematics).
    </li>

    <li>
        <em>I have an FCC Commercial Radio Operator's License.</em> My parents
        were volunteer DJs at <a href="http://www.kglt.net/">KGLT</a> while I
        was growing up, and I did my first radio announcing at... get this...
        the ripe age of 11. I finally got my license before starting college so
        that I could be a DJ at the university station... and ended up as the
        General Manager of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/KUPS">KUPS</a>
        my last two years.
    </li>

    <li>
        <em>I had long hair -- down to my butt at times -- for around ten
            years.</em> Which likely comes as a huge shock to those of you who
        have met me at conferences.  Ironically, I cut it off just prior to
        moving to Vermont as part of an effort to increase the success of my job
        hunt.
    </li>

    <li>
        <em>Before I started my programming career, I was a graphics
        technician.</em> The job immediately prior to my first programming
        position was with a small book publisher that specialized in bird
        hunting and flyfishing guidebooks, for which I created maps, scanned and
        processed images for books, and did book and catalog layout.
    </li>

    <li>
        <em>My first Object Oriented Programming was in Perl.</em> If you've
        ever done OOP in Perl, you'll likely agree with the following statement:
        OOP in any other language is easy by comparison. I mean, come on, a
        syntax where the very definition of an object requires that you "bless"
        a "thingy"? Truly; this is from the "bless" documentation:

        <blockquote>
            bless REF: This function tells the thingy referenced by REF that it
            is now an object in the CLASSNAME package. If CLASSNAME is omitted,
            the current package is used. Because a bless is often the last thing
            in a constructor, it returns the reference for convenience. Always
            use the two-argument version if a derived class might inherit the
            function doing the blessing. See perltoot and perlobj for more about
            the blessing (and blessings) of objects.
        </blockquote>

        This made OOP in PHP look easy.
    </li>

    <li>
        <em>I hold the degree of shodan in Aikido,</em> though I haven't trained
        in several years, due to time and travel constraints. I love the
        movement and flow of Aikido, and always found it very meditative. I also
        liked working with weapons, especially the bokken (wooden sword). This
        is why when I say, "don't make me get my clue bat out," you should take
        heed; I know from experience that white oak leaves a mark.
    </li>

    <li>
        <em>I could have been <a href="http://calevans.com/">Cal</a>.</em> When
        <a href="http://www.zend.com/">Zend</a> first interviewed me, it was for
        the position of Editor-in-Chief of 
        <a href="http://devzone.zend.com/">DevZone</a>. After my in-house
        interview, I had reservations -- I didn't feel experienced or connected
        enough, and was worried I'd botch it. Fortunately for me, and probably
        the PHP community in general, they decided to hire me as a PHP developer
        instead.
    </li>
</ul>

<p>
    So, that's seven things (and quite a bit more, really) about me. And now
    it's time to tag some others:
</p>

<ul>
    <li><a href="http://calevans.com/">Cal Evans</a> is an obvious choice for
    me. Besides having worked together for some years, he's a great friend.</li>

    <li><a href="http://www.leftontheweb.com/">Stefan Koopmanschap</a>, who
    took a train to Amsterdam just to have dinner and a beer with me.</li>
    <li><a href="http://seancoates.com/">Sean Coates</a>, whom I met in an
    airport on the way back from ZendCon two years ago, who lives less than two
    hours away, and whom I haven't seen since that ZendCon.</li>
    <li><a href="http://www.lornajane.net/">Lorna Jane Mitchell</a>, with whom
    I'll be doing a tutorial session on Subversion at php|tek, and who will be
    clearly flustered by being tagged.</li>
    <li><a href="http://jansch.nl/">Ivo Jansch</a>, whom I met almost two years
    ago, and somebody I admire and respect greatly.</li>
    <li><a href="http://www.khankennnels.com/blog/">Ligaya Turmelle</a>, one of
    my co-authors for "The PHP Anthology," the woman who got me to volunteer as
    a phpwomen Booth Babe, and now MySQL guru.</li>
    <li><a href="http://akrabat.com/">Rob Allen</a>, who has made my job easier
    by publishing tutorials and now a book on Zend Framework, and who in
    real-life is a mild-mannered Clark Kent I'd gladly raise a pint with any
    day.</li>
</ul>

<p>
    And here are the rules I'm supposed to pass on to the above bloggers:
</p>

<ul>
    <li>Link your original tagger(s), and list these rules on your blog.</li>
    <li>Share seven facts about yourself in the post - some random, some wierd.</li>
    <li>Tag seven people at the end of your post by leaving their names and the
    links to their blogs.</li>
    <li>Let them know they've been tagged by leaving a comment on their blogs
    and/or Twitter.</li>
</ul>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mumbles irssi integration</title>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2008 20:19:50 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/197-Mumbles-irssi-integration.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/197-Mumbles-irssi-integration.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    I've been using IRC regularly for the past six to nine months, in large part
    due to the growing ZF community on the 
    <a href="http://freenode.net/">Freenode</a> #zftalk channel (unfortunately,
    I simply don't have time to be in that particular channel any more, but you
    can generally find me in #zftalk.dev), but also to keep in contact with
    other peers, friends, and colleagues. 
</p>

<p>
    One difficulty, however, is keeping productivity high while staying on IRC.
    To me, the ultimate client would provide me notifications when somebody
    mentions my name or a watch word - allowing me to read the channel at my
    leisure, yet still respond to people in a timely fashion.
</p><p>
    I've tried a variety of IRC clients over the months, starting with Pidgin
    (poor interface for IRC), mirc (huge difficulties figuring out the UI),
    xchat (not bad, but seemed a bit heavy), Chatzilla (I liked the interface,
    but once you got many tabs going, it was unwieldy switching around between
    them; I also hated that Firefox dying or restarting caused Chatzilla to do
    likewise), and now <a href="http://irssi.org/">irssi</a>. 
</p>

<p>
    So far, irssi is the best I've tried -- I can run it in screen,
    allowing me to keep it open as long as my machine is running. The interface
    is reasonable, and cleanly keeps channels separate from private messages.
    Opening, closing, and manipulating windows is easy. And it's highly
    scriptable... including in a language I actually use! The perl bindings are
    top notch, though sometimes cryptic. What's important, however, is that
    there are plenty of examples out there if you want to try doing something.
    So, I figured I'd write up a quick plugin to trigger notifications.
</p>

<p>
    I've been using a number of different notification servers for linux, and
    personally like both <a href="http://gnotify.sourceforge.net">gnotify</a>
    and <a href="http://www.mumbles-project.org/">mumbles</a>. Both are very
    lightweight and offer network protocols for triggering notifications.
</p>

<p>
    I first tried using gnotify. It has a very, very simple TCP protocol, and
    I've had success creating messages from the shell, PHP, and perl.
    Unfortunately, for some reason, using it in irssi displayed some odd
    behavior: I'd lose the cursor and the ability to enter input from the time a
    notification triggered until it completed (i.e., the notification
    disappeared). Forking the process did not appear to help.
</p>

<p>
    So, I decided to try out mumbles. Mumbles is written in python, and has
    themeable notifications -- already a plus. It runs via dbus by default, but
    can also optionally spawn a server that implements the 
    <a href="http://growl.info/">Growl protocol</a> -- making it accessible for
    any process to send notifications. Additionally, it has a command-line
    utility for triggering notifications -- by default over dbus, but optionally
    by contacting the growl server, if running.
</p>

<p>
    Growl's protocol is a bit involved, and I didn't want to spend too much time
    on this. So, I did a quick, dirty hack: I used backticks to trigger the CLI
    utility. And it works <em>fantastically</em> -- no delays whatsoever. Here's
    the code:
</p>

<div class="example"><pre><code lang="perl">
# $HOME/.irssi/scripts/mumbles.pl
use strict;
use Irssi;
use Irssi::Irc;
use vars qw($VERSION %IRSSI);

$VERSION = '0.1.0';
%IRSSI = (
    authors     =&gt; \&quot;Matthew Weier O'Phinney\&quot;,
    contact     =&gt; 'matthew@weierophinney.net',
    name        =&gt; 'Mumbles notifications for irssi',
    description =&gt; 'This script enables mumbles notifications for irssi',
    license     =&gt; 'New BSD',
	changed     =&gt; \&quot;2008-12-10\&quot;
);


sub mumbles_sig_printtext {
  my ($dest, $text, $stripped) = @_;

  if (($dest-&gt;{level} &amp; (MSGLEVEL_HILIGHT|MSGLEVEL_MSGS)) &amp;&amp; ($dest-&gt;{level} &amp; MSGLEVEL_NOHILIGHT) == 0)
  {
    if ($dest-&gt;{level} &amp; MSGLEVEL_PUBLIC)
    {
      mumbles($dest-&gt;{target} . \&quot; : \&quot; . $text);
    }
  }
}

sub mumbles {
    my $message = shift;
    my $response;

    $message =~ s/[^!-~\s]//g;

    `/usr/bin/mumbles-send -g 127.0.0.1 -s \&quot;IRC\&quot; \&quot;$message\&quot;`;
}

Irssi::command_bind 'mumbles' =&gt; sub {
    my ($message) = @_;
    mumbles($message);
};

Irssi::signal_add({
  'print text'    =&gt; \&amp;mumbles_sig_printtext
});
</code></pre></div>

<p>
    This triggers a notification for any "highlight" event -- basically, anytime
    anybody "says" my name in a channel, or mentions a keyword I've marked for
    highlighting. Additionally, I created a "mumbles" command so that I can send
    test messages (usage: "/mumbles "this is the message..."). You could
    certainly bind to other events, such as topic changes, joins, parts, etc --
    I'm only interested in highlight events.
</p>

<p>
    You may note the regexp in there. One thing I discovered was that most
    messages contained control and non-ascii characters that often resulted in
    unreadable notifications, as well as some nasty messages reported by irssi.
    The regexp removes anything not in the ascii character set or the set of
    whitespace definitions prior to emitting the notification.
</p>

<p>
    Something else I needed to do was configure compiz to ensure that the
    notifications actually popped <em>above</em> my windows. I did this by going
    into the compiz configuration manager, selecting "General Options",
    selecting the "Focus &amp; Raise Behaviour" tab, and modifying the "Focus
    Prevention Windows" to read as follows:
</p>

<code><pre>
(any) &amp; !(class=Mumbles)
</pre></code>

<p>
    To test it, I placed the script in $HOME/.irssi/scripts/mumbles.pl, and then, 
    in irssi, executed "/load mumbles.pl".

<p>
    Once I had it to my liking, I symlinked it into my $HOME/.irssi/scripts/autorun/
    directory, allowing it to run as soon as irssi loads. I can now have irssi 
    running in a screen session, or minimize the terminal, and get notifications 
    -- keeping me productive and informed at the same time.
</p>

<p>
    <b>UPDATED 2008-12-12:</b> Added information on how to load the script, as 
    well as fixed the location to the autorun directory. Thanks, @sidhighwind!
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vimgrep and Vim Project</title>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2008 01:55:03 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/194-Vimgrep-and-Vim-Project.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/194-Vimgrep-and-Vim-Project.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    Chris Hartjes today was <a href="http://www.littlehart.net/atthekeyboard/2008/10/20/vim-programming-bounty-fuzzyfind-inside-files/">on a quest for a "find in project" feature for Vim</a>.
    "Find in Project" was a feature of Textmate that he'd grown accustomed to
    and was having trouble finding an equivalent for.
</p>

<p>
    The funny thing is that Textmate is a newcomer, and, of course, vim has had
    such a feature for years. The thing to remember with vim, of course, is its
    unix roots; typically if you know the unix command for doing something, you
    can find what you need in vim. In this case, the key is the vimgrep plugin,
    which ships in the standard vim distribution.
</p><p>
    There are a variety of resources on vimgrep. The vim documentation includes
    a chapter on it, and a quick <a href="http://www.google.com/search?q=vimgrep">google search</a>
    on the subject turns up some nice tutorials immediately. If you've ever used
    grep, the syntax is very straightforward:
</p>

<code><pre>
vimgrep /{pattern}/[g][j] {file} ...
</pre></code>

<p>
    The "g" option indicates that all matches for a search will be returned
    instead of just one per line, and the "j" option tells vim <em>not</em> to
    jump to the first match automatically. What does the "g" flag really mean,
    though, and how are searches returned?
</p>

<p>
    Vimgrep returns search results in what's known as a "quickfix" window, and
    this is where the vimgrep documentation falls apart... it doesn't explain
    what this is, or link to it (which would be a nice indication that it
    actually has a separate topic for this).
</p>

<p>
    The Quickfix window is a pane that shows a search result per line. Each line
    shows the file that matches, the line number, and the contents of that line:
</p>

<code><pre>
/home/matthew/git/bugapp/application/controllers/helpers/GetForm.php|10| * @var Zend_Loader_PluginLoader
</pre></code>

<p>
    You can't do much from this window; it simply serves as a visual indicator
    of what file you're currently looking at from the list. However, in the main
    window, you can start iterating through the results one at a time, using a
    subset of the Quickfix commands. As a quick summary:
</p>

<ul>
    <li><b>:cc</b> will move to the next match in the list</li>
    <li><b>:cn</b> will move to the next match in the list</li>
    <li><b>:cp</b> will move to the previous match in the list</li>
    <li><b>:cr</b> will rewind to the first match in the list</li>
    <li><b>:cla</b> will fast forward to the last match in the list</li>
</ul>

<p>
    When done, you can simply close the Quickfix window/pane, and continue
    working.
</p>

<p>
    I should note that vimgrep <em>is</em> cross-platform. On *nix-based
    systems, it defaults to using the native grep command, but it also contains
    an internal (slower) implementation for use on operating systems that do not
    provide grep by default. You may also map the command to alternate
    implementations if desired.
</p>

<p>
    I personally use this feature most with the <a href="http://www.vim.org/scripts/script.php?script_id=69">project plugin</a>.
    Project maps vimgrep to two different commands: &lt;Leader&gt;g and
    &lt;Leader&gt;G. The first will grep all files in the current project at the
    current level; the second does the same, but also recurses into subprojects.
    This is an incredibly easy way to refactor code, particularly for name
    changes.
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vim 7 code completion</title>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Sep 2006 13:21:27 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/123-Vim-7-code-completion.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/123-Vim-7-code-completion.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    I may work at <a href="http://www.zend.com/">Zend</a>, but I've never been a
    fan of IDEs. They simply don't suit my programming style. I can usually keep
    track of file locations in my head pretty easily, and what I really need is
    a blank slate on which I can write, and one that doesn't consume resource
    that can better be used running web servers and other programs. Syntax
    highlighting, good indentation -- these are important, but you can get these
    from good, minimal text editors very easily. 
    <a href="http://www.vim.org">Vim is my editor of choice</a>.
</p>
<p>
    I will admit, though, that one area where I have had IDE-envy is the area of
    code completion. I often find myself doing quick lookups to php.net or
    perldoc to determine the order of arguments to a function or method call,
    or checking for the expected return value. Most of the time, this doesn't
    take much time, however, so I just live with it.
</p>
<p>
    Today, however, cruising through the blogosphere, I came across 
    <a href="http://linuxhelp.blogspot.com/2006/09/visual-walk-through-of-couple-of-new.html">an article showcasing some new features of Vim 7.0</a>, 
    and discovered Vim 7's code completion.
</p>
<p>
    Basically, while in insert mode, you can type &lt;C-x&gt; &lt;C-o&gt; to
    have vim attempt to autocomplete the current keyword. If more than one
    possibility exists, it shows a dropdown, and you can use your arrow keys to
    highlight the keyword that you wish to use.
</p>
<p>
    But it gets better! Not only does it do this kind of autocompletion, but it
    also opens a small 'scratch preview' pane showing the function/method
    signature -- i.e., the expected arguments and return value!
</p>
<p>
    I thought I had little need for IDEs before... now I have even less! Bram
    and the rest of the Vim team, my hat's off to you for more fine work!
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Telcos are Attacking the Internet</title>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Apr 2006 17:47:28 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/107-Telcos-are-Attacking-the-Internet.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/107-Telcos-are-Attacking-the-Internet.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    I generally try to stay out of politics on this blog, but this time
    something has to be said, as it affects anyone who uses the internet, at
    least in the US.
</p>
<p>
    Basically, a number of telcos and cable providers are talking about charging
    internet content providers -- the places you browse to on the internet,
    places like Google, Yahoo!, Amazon, etc. -- fees to ensure bandwidth to
    their sites. Their argument is that these content providers are getting a
    'free ride' on their lines, and generating a lot of traffic themselves, and
    should thus be paying for the cost of bandwidth.
</p>
<p>
    This is patently ridiculous. Content providers already have to pay for their
    bandwidth -- they, too, have ISPs or agreements with telcos in place, either
    explicitly or via their hosting providers. Sure, some of them, particularly
    search engines, send out robots in order to index or find content, but,
    again, they're paying for the bandwidth those robots generate.
    Additionally, people using the internet are typically paying for bandwidth
    as well, through their relationship with their ISP. What this amounts to is
    the telcos getting paid not just by each person to whom they provide
    internet access, but every end point on the internet, at least those within
    the US.
</p>
<p>
    What this is really about is telcos wanting more money, and wanting to push
    their own content. As an example, let's say your ISP is AOL. AOL is part of
    Time Warner, and thus has ties to those media sources. Now, those media
    sources may put pressure on AOL to reduce bandwidth to sites operated by
    ABC, CBS, NBC, FOX, Disney, PBS, etc. This might mean that your kid can no
    longer visit the Sesame Street website reliably, because AOL has reduced the
    amount of bandwidth allowed to that service -- but any media site in the TWC
    would get optimal access, so they could get to Cartoon Network. Not to slam
    Cartoon Network (I love it), but would you rather have your kid visiting
    cartoonnetwork.com or pbskids.org?  Basically, content providers would not
    need to compete based on the value of their content, but on who they can get
    to subscribe to their service.
</p>
<p>
    Here's another idea: your ISP is MSN. You want to use Google... but MSN has
    limited the bandwidth to Google because it's a competitor, and won't accept
    any amount of money to increase that bandwidth. They do the same with Yahoo!
    So, now you're limited to MSN search, because that's the only one that
    responds reliably -- regardless of whether or not you like their search
    results. By doing so, they've just artificially inflated the value of their
    search engine -- without needing to compete based on merit. 
</p>
<p>
    Additionally, let's say Barnes and Noble has paid MSN to ensure good
    bandwidth, but part of that agreement is a non-compete clause.  Now you find
    your connections to Amazon timing out, meaning that you can't even see which
    book provider has the better price on the book you want; you're stuck
    looking and buying from B&amp;N.
</p>
<p>
    Now, let's look at something a little more close to home for those of us
    developing web applications. There have been a number of success stories the
    last few years: MySpace, Digg, and Flickr all come to mind. Would these
    endeavors have been as successful had they needed to pay multiple times for
    bandwidth, once to their ISP and once each to each telco charging for
    content providers? Indeed, some of these are still free services -- how
    would they ever have been able to pay the extra amounts to the telcos in the
    first place?
</p>
<p>
    So, basically, the only winners here are the telcos.
</p>
<p>
    Considering how ludicrous this scheme is, one must be thinking, isn't the US
    Government going to step in and regulate against such behaviour? <a href="http://www.businessweek.com/technology/content/apr2006/tc20060426_553893.htm?chan=technology_technology+index+page_more+of+today">The answer, sadly, is no.</a>
    The GOP doesn't like regulation, and so they want market forces to decide.
    Sadly, what this will likely do is force a number of content providers to
    offshore their internet operations -- which is likely to have some pretty
    negative effects on the economy.
</p>
<p>
    The decision isn't final -- efforts can still be made to prevent it (the
    above link references a Senate committee meeting; there's been no vote on
    it). Call your representatives today and give them an earful. Tell them it's
    not just about regulation of the industry, but about fair competition in the
    market. Allowing the telcos to extort money from content providers will only
    reduce the US' economic chances in the world, and stifle innovation and
    choice.
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PHP error reporting for Perl users</title>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Mar 2006 14:19:35 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/105-PHP-error-reporting-for-Perl-users.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/105-PHP-error-reporting-for-Perl-users.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    On <a href="http://www.perlmonks.org">perlmonks</a> today, a user was
    needing to maintain a PHP app, and wanted to know what the PHP equivalent of
    "perl -wc script.pl" was -- specifically, they wanted to know how to run a
    PHP script from the commandline and have it display any warnings (ala perl's
    strict and warnings pragmas).
</p>
<p>
    Unfortunately, there's not as simple a way to do this in PHP as in perl.
    Basically, you need to do the following:
</p>
<ul>
    <li><strong>To display errors:</strong><ul>
        <li>In you php.ini file, set "display_errors = On", <b>or</b></li>
        <li>In your script, add the line "ini_set('display_errors', true);"</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li><strong>To show notices, warnings, errors, deprecation
        notices:</strong><ul>
        <li>In you php.ini file, set "error_reporting = E_ALL | E_STRICT", <b>or</b></li>
        <li>In your script, add the line "error_reporting(E_ALL | E_STRICT);"</li>
    </ul></li>
</ul>
<p>
    Alternatively, you can create a file with the lines:
</p>
<pre>
&lt;?php
    error_reporting(E_ALL | E_STRICT);
    ini_set('display_errors', true);
</pre>
<p>
    and then set the php.ini setting 'auto_prepend_file' to the path to that
    file.
</p>
<p>
    <strong>NOTE: do not do any of the above on a production system!</strong>
    PHP's error messages often reveal a lot about your applications, including
    file layout and potential vectors of attack. Turn display_errors off on
    production machines, set your error_reporting somewhat lower, and log_errors
    to a file so you can keep track of what's going on on your production
    system.
</p>
<p>
    The second part of the question was how to run a PHP script on the command
    line. This is incredibly simple: php myscript.php. No different than any
    other scripting language.
</p>
<p>
    You can get some good information by using some of the switches, though.
    <strong>'-l'</strong> turns the PHP interpreter into a linter, and can let
    you know if your code is well-formed (which doesn't necessarily preclude
    runtime or parse errors). <strong>'-f'</strong> will run the script through
    the parser, which can give you even more information. I typically bind these
    actions to keys in vim so I can check my work as I go.
</p>
<p>
    If you plan on running your code <em>solely</em> on the commandline, add a
    shebang to the first line of your script: #!/path/to/php. Then make the
    script executable, and you're good to go. This is handy for cronjobs, or
    batch processing scripts.
</p>
<p>
    All of this information is readily available in <a
        href="http://www.php.net/manual">the PHP manual</a>, and the commandline
    options are always available by passing the --help switch to the PHP
    executable. So, start testing your scripts already!
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sign of a Geek</title>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Nov 2004 21:05:42 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/51-Sign-of-a-Geek.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/51-Sign-of-a-Geek.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    It's now been confirmed: I'm a geek. 
</p>
<p>
    Okay, so that probably comes as no shocker to those of you who know me, but
    it's the little things that make me realize it myself.
</p>
<p>
    I've been frequenting <a href="http://www.perlmonks.org">Perl Monks</a> for
    a couple of years now, mainly to garner ideas and code to help me with my
    personal or work projects. I rarely post comments, and I've only once
    submitted a question to the site. However, I <strong>do</strong> frequent
    the site regularly, and the few comments I've put in -- generally regarding
    usage of <a href="http::/search.cpan.org/search?query=CGI%3A%3AApplication">CGI::Application</a>
    -- have been typically well-moderated.
</p>
<p>
    Well, yesterday I <a href="http://www.perlmonks.org/?node_id=408255">made a comment</a> to a user <a href="http://www.perlmonks.org/?node_id=408231">asking about editors to
        use with perl</a>. I was incensed by a remark he made about <a href="http://www.vim.org">VIM</a> not having the features he needed.
    Now, as I said in my comment, I've used VIM on a daily basis for over two
    years, and I'm <em>still</em> discovering new features -- and I've used all
    of the features he was looking for.
</p>
<p>
    This is where I discovered I'm a geek: my comment made it into the <a href="http://www.perlmonks.org/?node=Best%20Nodes">Daily
    Best</a> for today, peaking around number 5. The fact that that made my day
    indicates to me that I <em>must</em> be a geek.
</p>
<p>
    Oh -- and VIM rules!
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PHP_SELF versus SCRIPT_NAME</title>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Oct 2004 01:35:03 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/45-PHP_SELF-versus-SCRIPT_NAME.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/45-PHP_SELF-versus-SCRIPT_NAME.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    I've standardized my PHP programming to use the environment variable
    <b>SCRIPT_NAME</b> when I want my script to refer to itself in links and
    form actions. I've known that <b>PHP_SELF</b> has the same information, but
    I was more familiar with the name 'SCRIPT_NAME' from using it in perl, and
    liked the feel of it more as it seems to describe the resource better
    ('PHP_SELF' could stand for the path to the PHP executable if I were to go
    by the name only).
</p>
<p>
    However, I just noticed a post on the php.general newsgroup where somebody
    asked what the difference was between them. Semantically, there isn't any;
    they should contain the same information. However, historically and
    technically speaking, there is. <b>SCRIPT_NAME</b> is defined in the CGI 1.1
    specification, and is thus a standard. <em>However</em>, not all web servers
    actually implement it, and thus it isn't necessarily <em>portable</em>.
    <b>PHP_SELF</b>, on the other hand, is implemented directly by PHP, and as
    long as you're programming in PHP, will always be present.
</p>
<p>
    Guess I have some grep and sed in my future as I change a bunch of
    scripts...
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
