<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/">
  <channel>
    <title>Tag: perl :: phly, boy, phly</title>
    <description>Tag: perl :: phly, boy, phly</description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jun 2012 02:50:00 +0000</pubDate>
    <generator>Zend_Feed_Writer 2.0.0beta5 (http://framework.zend.com)</generator>
    <link>http://mwop.net/blog/tag/perl.html</link>
    <atom:link rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" href="http://mwop.net/blog/tag/perl-rss.xml"/>
    <item>
      <title>Automatic deployment with git and gitolite</title>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jun 2012 02:50:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/2012-06-24-git-deploy.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/2012-06-24-git-deploy.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    I read a <a 
    href="http://seancoates.com/blogs/deploy-on-push-from-github" 
    target="_blank">post recently by Sean Coates about deploy on 
    push</a>. The concept is nothing new: you set up a hook that 
    listens for commits on specific branches or tags, and it then
    deploys your site from that revision.
</p>

<p>
    Except I'd not done it myself. This is how I got there.
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why Conventions Matter</title>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jan 2012 03:58:28 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/why-conventions-matter.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/why-conventions-matter.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    When I started teaching myself scripting languages, I started with Perl. One
    Perl motto is <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/TMTOWTDI">"TMTOWTDI"</a>
    -- "There's More Than One Way To Do It," and pronounced "tim-toady." The
    idea is that there's likely multiple ways to accomplish the very same thing,
    and the culture of the language encourages finding novel ways to do things.
</p>

<p>
    I've seen this principle used everywhere and in just about every programming
    situation possible, applied to logical operations, naming conventions,
    formatting, and even project structure.  Everyone has an opinion on these
    topics, and given free rein to implement as they see fit, it's rare that two
    developers will come up with the same conventions.
</p>

<p>
    TMTOWTDI is an incredibly freeing and egalitarian principle.
</p>

<p>
    Over the years, however, my love for TMTOWTDI has diminished some.  Freeing
    as it is, is also a driving force behind having coding standards and
    conventions -- because when everyone does it their own way, projects become
    quickly hard to maintain. Each person finds themselves reformatting code to
    their own standards, simply so they can read it and follow its flow.
</p>

<p>
    Additionally, TMTOWTDI can actually be a foe of simple, elegant solutions.
</p>

<p>
    Why do I claim this?
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Seven Things - Tagged by Keith Casey</title>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Jan 2009 21:31:52 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/204-Seven-Things-Tagged-by-Keith-Casey.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/204-Seven-Things-Tagged-by-Keith-Casey.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    I'm really not sure I understand these "seven things" or "tagged" memes, but
    I'm going to give it a shot, after 
    <a href="http://caseysoftware.com/blog/seven-things-tagged-by-tony-bibbs">Keith Casey</a> did a drive-by
    tagging of me on New Year's Eve.
</p>

<p>
    So, without further ado, seven things you may not know about me...
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mumbles irssi integration</title>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2008 20:19:50 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/197-Mumbles-irssi-integration.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/197-Mumbles-irssi-integration.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    I've been using IRC regularly for the past six to nine months, in large part
    due to the growing ZF community on the 
    <a href="http://freenode.net/">Freenode</a> #zftalk channel (unfortunately,
    I simply don't have time to be in that particular channel any more, but you
    can generally find me in #zftalk.dev), but also to keep in contact with
    other peers, friends, and colleagues. 
</p>

<p>
    One difficulty, however, is keeping productivity high while staying on IRC.
    To me, the ultimate client would provide me notifications when somebody
    mentions my name or a watch word - allowing me to read the channel at my
    leisure, yet still respond to people in a timely fashion.
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vimgrep and Vim Project</title>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2008 01:55:03 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/194-Vimgrep-and-Vim-Project.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/194-Vimgrep-and-Vim-Project.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    Chris Hartjes today was <a href="http://www.littlehart.net/atthekeyboard/2008/10/20/vim-programming-bounty-fuzzyfind-inside-files/">on a quest for a "find in project" feature for Vim</a>.
    "Find in Project" was a feature of Textmate that he'd grown accustomed to
    and was having trouble finding an equivalent for.
</p>

<p>
    The funny thing is that Textmate is a newcomer, and, of course, vim has had
    such a feature for years. The thing to remember with vim, of course, is its
    unix roots; typically if you know the unix command for doing something, you
    can find what you need in vim. In this case, the key is the vimgrep plugin,
    which ships in the standard vim distribution.
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vim 7 code completion</title>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Sep 2006 13:21:27 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/123-Vim-7-code-completion.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/123-Vim-7-code-completion.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    I may work at <a href="http://www.zend.com/">Zend</a>, but I've never been a
    fan of IDEs. They simply don't suit my programming style. I can usually keep
    track of file locations in my head pretty easily, and what I really need is
    a blank slate on which I can write, and one that doesn't consume resource
    that can better be used running web servers and other programs. Syntax
    highlighting, good indentation -- these are important, but you can get these
    from good, minimal text editors very easily. 
    <a href="http://www.vim.org">Vim is my editor of choice</a>.
</p>
<p>
    I will admit, though, that one area where I have had IDE-envy is the area of
    code completion. I often find myself doing quick lookups to php.net or
    perldoc to determine the order of arguments to a function or method call,
    or checking for the expected return value. Most of the time, this doesn't
    take much time, however, so I just live with it.
</p>
<p>
    Today, however, cruising through the blogosphere, I came across 
    <a href="http://linuxhelp.blogspot.com/2006/09/visual-walk-through-of-couple-of-new.html">an article showcasing some new features of Vim 7.0</a>, 
    and discovered Vim 7's code completion.
</p>
<p>
    Basically, while in insert mode, you can type &lt;C-x&gt; &lt;C-o&gt; to
    have vim attempt to autocomplete the current keyword. If more than one
    possibility exists, it shows a dropdown, and you can use your arrow keys to
    highlight the keyword that you wish to use.
</p>
<p>
    But it gets better! Not only does it do this kind of autocompletion, but it
    also opens a small 'scratch preview' pane showing the function/method
    signature -- i.e., the expected arguments and return value!
</p>
<p>
    I thought I had little need for IDEs before... now I have even less! Bram
    and the rest of the Vim team, my hat's off to you for more fine work!
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Telcos are Attacking the Internet</title>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Apr 2006 17:47:28 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/107-Telcos-are-Attacking-the-Internet.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/107-Telcos-are-Attacking-the-Internet.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    I generally try to stay out of politics on this blog, but this time
    something has to be said, as it affects anyone who uses the internet, at
    least in the US.
</p>
<p>
    Basically, a number of telcos and cable providers are talking about charging
    internet content providers -- the places you browse to on the internet,
    places like Google, Yahoo!, Amazon, etc. -- fees to ensure bandwidth to
    their sites. Their argument is that these content providers are getting a
    'free ride' on their lines, and generating a lot of traffic themselves, and
    should thus be paying for the cost of bandwidth.
</p>
<p>
    This is patently ridiculous. Content providers already have to pay for their
    bandwidth -- they, too, have ISPs or agreements with telcos in place, either
    explicitly or via their hosting providers. Sure, some of them, particularly
    search engines, send out robots in order to index or find content, but,
    again, they're paying for the bandwidth those robots generate.
    Additionally, people using the internet are typically paying for bandwidth
    as well, through their relationship with their ISP. What this amounts to is
    the telcos getting paid not just by each person to whom they provide
    internet access, but every end point on the internet, at least those within
    the US.
</p>
<p>
    What this is really about is telcos wanting more money, and wanting to push
    their own content. As an example, let's say your ISP is AOL. AOL is part of
    Time Warner, and thus has ties to those media sources. Now, those media
    sources may put pressure on AOL to reduce bandwidth to sites operated by
    ABC, CBS, NBC, FOX, Disney, PBS, etc. This might mean that your kid can no
    longer visit the Sesame Street website reliably, because AOL has reduced the
    amount of bandwidth allowed to that service -- but any media site in the TWC
    would get optimal access, so they could get to Cartoon Network. Not to slam
    Cartoon Network (I love it), but would you rather have your kid visiting
    cartoonnetwork.com or pbskids.org?  Basically, content providers would not
    need to compete based on the value of their content, but on who they can get
    to subscribe to their service.
</p>
<p>
    Here's another idea: your ISP is MSN. You want to use Google... but MSN has
    limited the bandwidth to Google because it's a competitor, and won't accept
    any amount of money to increase that bandwidth. They do the same with Yahoo!
    So, now you're limited to MSN search, because that's the only one that
    responds reliably -- regardless of whether or not you like their search
    results. By doing so, they've just artificially inflated the value of their
    search engine -- without needing to compete based on merit. 
</p>
<p>
    Additionally, let's say Barnes and Noble has paid MSN to ensure good
    bandwidth, but part of that agreement is a non-compete clause.  Now you find
    your connections to Amazon timing out, meaning that you can't even see which
    book provider has the better price on the book you want; you're stuck
    looking and buying from B&amp;N.
</p>
<p>
    Now, let's look at something a little more close to home for those of us
    developing web applications. There have been a number of success stories the
    last few years: MySpace, Digg, and Flickr all come to mind. Would these
    endeavors have been as successful had they needed to pay multiple times for
    bandwidth, once to their ISP and once each to each telco charging for
    content providers? Indeed, some of these are still free services -- how
    would they ever have been able to pay the extra amounts to the telcos in the
    first place?
</p>
<p>
    So, basically, the only winners here are the telcos.
</p>
<p>
    Considering how ludicrous this scheme is, one must be thinking, isn't the US
    Government going to step in and regulate against such behaviour? <a href="http://www.businessweek.com/technology/content/apr2006/tc20060426_553893.htm?chan=technology_technology+index+page_more+of+today">The answer, sadly, is no.</a>
    The GOP doesn't like regulation, and so they want market forces to decide.
    Sadly, what this will likely do is force a number of content providers to
    offshore their internet operations -- which is likely to have some pretty
    negative effects on the economy.
</p>
<p>
    The decision isn't final -- efforts can still be made to prevent it (the
    above link references a Senate committee meeting; there's been no vote on
    it). Call your representatives today and give them an earful. Tell them it's
    not just about regulation of the industry, but about fair competition in the
    market. Allowing the telcos to extort money from content providers will only
    reduce the US' economic chances in the world, and stifle innovation and
    choice.
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PHP error reporting for Perl users</title>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Mar 2006 14:19:35 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/105-PHP-error-reporting-for-Perl-users.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/105-PHP-error-reporting-for-Perl-users.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    On <a href="http://www.perlmonks.org">perlmonks</a> today, a user was
    needing to maintain a PHP app, and wanted to know what the PHP equivalent of
    "perl -wc script.pl" was -- specifically, they wanted to know how to run a
    PHP script from the commandline and have it display any warnings (ala perl's
    strict and warnings pragmas).
</p>
<p>
    Unfortunately, there's not as simple a way to do this in PHP as in perl.
    Basically, you need to do the following:
</p>
<ul>
    <li><strong>To display errors:</strong><ul>
        <li>In you php.ini file, set "display_errors = On", <b>or</b></li>
        <li>In your script, add the line "ini_set('display_errors', true);"</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li><strong>To show notices, warnings, errors, deprecation
        notices:</strong><ul>
        <li>In you php.ini file, set "error_reporting = E_ALL | E_STRICT", <b>or</b></li>
        <li>In your script, add the line "error_reporting(E_ALL | E_STRICT);"</li>
    </ul></li>
</ul>
<p>
    Alternatively, you can create a file with the lines:
</p>
<pre>
&lt;?php
    error_reporting(E_ALL | E_STRICT);
    ini_set('display_errors', true);
</pre>
<p>
    and then set the php.ini setting 'auto_prepend_file' to the path to that
    file.
</p>
<p>
    <strong>NOTE: do not do any of the above on a production system!</strong>
    PHP's error messages often reveal a lot about your applications, including
    file layout and potential vectors of attack. Turn display_errors off on
    production machines, set your error_reporting somewhat lower, and log_errors
    to a file so you can keep track of what's going on on your production
    system.
</p>
<p>
    The second part of the question was how to run a PHP script on the command
    line. This is incredibly simple: php myscript.php. No different than any
    other scripting language.
</p>
<p>
    You can get some good information by using some of the switches, though.
    <strong>'-l'</strong> turns the PHP interpreter into a linter, and can let
    you know if your code is well-formed (which doesn't necessarily preclude
    runtime or parse errors). <strong>'-f'</strong> will run the script through
    the parser, which can give you even more information. I typically bind these
    actions to keys in vim so I can check my work as I go.
</p>
<p>
    If you plan on running your code <em>solely</em> on the commandline, add a
    shebang to the first line of your script: #!/path/to/php. Then make the
    script executable, and you're good to go. This is handy for cronjobs, or
    batch processing scripts.
</p>
<p>
    All of this information is readily available in <a
        href="http://www.php.net/manual">the PHP manual</a>, and the commandline
    options are always available by passing the --help switch to the PHP
    executable. So, start testing your scripts already!
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sign of a Geek</title>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Nov 2004 21:05:42 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/51-Sign-of-a-Geek.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/51-Sign-of-a-Geek.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    It's now been confirmed: I'm a geek. 
</p>
<p>
    Okay, so that probably comes as no shocker to those of you who know me, but
    it's the little things that make me realize it myself.
</p>
<p>
    I've been frequenting <a href="http://www.perlmonks.org">Perl Monks</a> for
    a couple of years now, mainly to garner ideas and code to help me with my
    personal or work projects. I rarely post comments, and I've only once
    submitted a question to the site. However, I <strong>do</strong> frequent
    the site regularly, and the few comments I've put in -- generally regarding
    usage of <a href="http::/search.cpan.org/search?query=CGI%3A%3AApplication">CGI::Application</a>
    -- have been typically well-moderated.
</p>
<p>
    Well, yesterday I <a href="http://www.perlmonks.org/?node_id=408255">made a comment</a> to a user <a href="http://www.perlmonks.org/?node_id=408231">asking about editors to
        use with perl</a>. I was incensed by a remark he made about <a href="http://www.vim.org">VIM</a> not having the features he needed.
    Now, as I said in my comment, I've used VIM on a daily basis for over two
    years, and I'm <em>still</em> discovering new features -- and I've used all
    of the features he was looking for.
</p>
<p>
    This is where I discovered I'm a geek: my comment made it into the <a href="http://www.perlmonks.org/?node=Best%20Nodes">Daily
    Best</a> for today, peaking around number 5. The fact that that made my day
    indicates to me that I <em>must</em> be a geek.
</p>
<p>
    Oh -- and VIM rules!
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PHP_SELF versus SCRIPT_NAME</title>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Oct 2004 01:35:03 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/45-PHP_SELF-versus-SCRIPT_NAME.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/45-PHP_SELF-versus-SCRIPT_NAME.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    I've standardized my PHP programming to use the environment variable
    <b>SCRIPT_NAME</b> when I want my script to refer to itself in links and
    form actions. I've known that <b>PHP_SELF</b> has the same information, but
    I was more familiar with the name 'SCRIPT_NAME' from using it in perl, and
    liked the feel of it more as it seems to describe the resource better
    ('PHP_SELF' could stand for the path to the PHP executable if I were to go
    by the name only).
</p>
<p>
    However, I just noticed a post on the php.general newsgroup where somebody
    asked what the difference was between them. Semantically, there isn't any;
    they should contain the same information. However, historically and
    technically speaking, there is. <b>SCRIPT_NAME</b> is defined in the CGI 1.1
    specification, and is thus a standard. <em>However</em>, not all web servers
    actually implement it, and thus it isn't necessarily <em>portable</em>.
    <b>PHP_SELF</b>, on the other hand, is implemented directly by PHP, and as
    long as you're programming in PHP, will always be present.
</p>
<p>
    Guess I have some grep and sed in my future as I change a bunch of
    scripts...
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
