<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title type="text">Tag: personal :: phly, boy, phly</title>
  <updated>2009-01-04T15:31:52-06:00</updated>
  <generator uri="http://framework.zend.com" version="2.0.0beta4">Zend_Feed_Writer</generator>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mwop.net/blog/tag/personal.html"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://mwop.net/blog/tag/personal-atom.xml"/>
  <id>http://mwop.net/blog/tag/personal.html</id>
  <entry xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Seven Things - Tagged by Keith Casey]]></title>
    <published>2009-01-02T09:44:54-06:00</published>
    <updated>2009-01-04T15:31:52-06:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mwop.net/blog/204-Seven-Things-Tagged-by-Keith-Casey.html"/>
    <id>http://mwop.net/blog/204-Seven-Things-Tagged-by-Keith-Casey.html</id>
    <author>
      <name>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</name>
      <email>me@mwop.net</email>
      <uri>http://mwop.net</uri>
    </author>
    <content xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" type="xhtml">
      <xhtml:div xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><xhtml:p>I'm really not sure I understand these "seven things" or
"tagged" memes, but I'm going to give it a shot, after <xhtml:a href="http://caseysoftware.com/blog/seven-things-tagged-by-tony-bibbs">Keith
Casey</xhtml:a> did a drive-by tagging of me on New Year's Eve.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>So, without further ado, seven things you may not know about
me...</xhtml:p>
</xhtml:div>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2007 Retrospective]]></title>
    <published>2008-01-01T15:49:26-06:00</published>
    <updated>2008-01-03T05:22:35-06:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mwop.net/blog/154-2007-Retrospective.html"/>
    <id>http://mwop.net/blog/154-2007-Retrospective.html</id>
    <author>
      <name>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</name>
      <email>me@mwop.net</email>
      <uri>http://mwop.net</uri>
    </author>
    <content xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" type="xhtml">
      <xhtml:div xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><xhtml:p>2007 was a busy year, both personally and professionally. I
won't go into the personal too much, because, well, it's personal,
and some of the details are simply inappropriate for blogging
material.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Here's the short version:</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:ul>
<xhtml:li>One trip to Belgium and The Netherlands.</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>Two trips to Israel.</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>Two trips to Atlanta, GA (not counting the return trip from
Europe, when I was stranded for a day due to storms in the
Northeast).</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>Three different user groups attended, with three
presentations.</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>One major Zend Framework release</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>One PEAR release.</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>One podcast.</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>One webinar.</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>One book published.</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>One conference attended.</xhtml:li>
</xhtml:ul>
<xhtml:p>What follows is my month-by-month breakdown:</xhtml:p>
</xhtml:div>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[I is a published author!]]></title>
    <published>2007-11-06T11:37:33-06:00</published>
    <updated>2007-11-06T11:41:02-06:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mwop.net/blog/149-I-is-a-published-author!.html"/>
    <id>http://mwop.net/blog/149-I-is-a-published-author!.html</id>
    <author>
      <name>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</name>
      <email>me@mwop.net</email>
      <uri>http://mwop.net</uri>
    </author>
    <content xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" type="xhtml">
      <xhtml:div xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><xhtml:p>So, in addition to it being my daughter's birthday, which is
exciting enough in itself, I received a package from my publisher,
<xhtml:a href="http://www.sitepoint.com">SitePoint</xhtml:a>, with my author
copies of <xhtml:a href="http://www.sitepoint.com/books/phpant2/">The PHP
Anthology</xhtml:a>. Very exciting to see stuff I've written
published!</xhtml:p>
</xhtml:div>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Transitions]]></title>
    <published>2005-09-20T23:58:32-05:00</published>
    <updated>2005-09-21T14:08:39-05:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mwop.net/blog/94-Transitions.html"/>
    <id>http://mwop.net/blog/94-Transitions.html</id>
    <author>
      <name>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</name>
      <email>me@mwop.net</email>
      <uri>http://mwop.net</uri>
    </author>
    <content xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" type="xhtml">
      <xhtml:div xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><xhtml:p>Life is in transition for me now. Two weeks ago, we got to bring
our handsome baby boy home, and I haven't been sleeping much since
(though more than Jen). On top of the sleep deprivation, however,
comes more exciting news: I've been hired as a PHP Developer by
<xhtml:a href="http://www.zend.com/">Zend Technologies</xhtml:a>!</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>I was approached by Daniel Kushner in late July regarding
another position at Zend, and was flown out at the beginning of
August. While I felt the interview went well, I harbored some
doubts; work got fairly busy shortly thereafter, and then, of
course, Liam was born, and the interview went completely out of my
head. Until about three days after Liam's birthday, when Daniel
contacted me again about the PHP Developer position.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Work started yesterday, and I was flown to Zend's offices in
Cupertino, CA, for orientation and to sit down with both Daniel and
others to prepare for the projects on which I will be working.
Thankfully, the job will not require that I move, and I will be
working out of the 'home office' in Vermont when I return later
this week.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>The decision to leave <xhtml:a href="http://assoc.garden.org/about">NGA</xhtml:a> was difficult, but the
opportunity to work with Zend is just too good to miss. I am
honored to be selected by them, and hope this is the beginning of
many good things to come.</xhtml:p>
</xhtml:div>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ZCE - Results are in!]]></title>
    <published>2005-06-28T10:33:00-05:00</published>
    <updated>2005-06-29T04:48:06-05:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mwop.net/blog/80-ZCE-Results-are-in!.html"/>
    <id>http://mwop.net/blog/80-ZCE-Results-are-in!.html</id>
    <author>
      <name>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</name>
      <email>me@mwop.net</email>
      <uri>http://mwop.net</uri>
    </author>
    <content xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" type="xhtml">
      <xhtml:div xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><xhtml:p>Got the official notification: I passed the <xhtml:a href="http://www.zend.com/store/education/certification/zend-php-certification.php">
Zend PHP Certification Exam</xhtml:a>, and can now report I'm a Zend
Certified Engineer (ZCE)!</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p style="text-align: center;"><xhtml:a href="http://zend.com/zce.php?c=ZEND901102&amp;r=0502029"><xhtml:img src="/matthew/img/zce_logo.gif" alt="Zend Certified Engineer" height="47" width="73"/></xhtml:a></xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Thanks go to my bosses at <xhtml:a href="http://assoc.garden.org/">NGA</xhtml:a> for giving me the opportunity to
attend <xhtml:a href="http://www.phparch.com/tropics">php|Tropics</xhtml:a>, to
<xhtml:a href="http://www.phparch.com/">Marco Tabini</xhtml:a> for offering the
ZCE exam as part of the php|Tropics conference fee, and to my wife,
Jen, and daughter, Maeve, for putting up with me while I studied...
and being good sports about having to stay home while I went to
Cancun. Hopefully next time I can take you along!</xhtml:p>
</xhtml:div>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Moving into City Living]]></title>
    <published>2005-06-05T12:00:00-05:00</published>
    <updated>2005-06-05T12:01:03-05:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mwop.net/blog/77-Moving-into-City-Living.html"/>
    <id>http://mwop.net/blog/77-Moving-into-City-Living.html</id>
    <author>
      <name>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</name>
      <email>me@mwop.net</email>
      <uri>http://mwop.net</uri>
    </author>
    <content xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" type="xhtml">
      <xhtml:div xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><xhtml:p>We did it... we moved, again.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>However, unlike our previous two moves, which were interstate,
this time we stayed in the same state. The same county, even. What
made (makes; we're still finishing up as I write this) this one so
jarring is the fact that we're going from the rural mountainside to
the fourth floor of a new apartment/condo building adjoining an
interstate spur.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Why would we do this?</xhtml:p>
</xhtml:div>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[We're having a baby!]]></title>
    <published>2005-04-23T17:01:52-05:00</published>
    <updated>2005-04-23T17:12:20-05:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mwop.net/blog/67-Were-having-a-baby!.html"/>
    <id>http://mwop.net/blog/67-Were-having-a-baby!.html</id>
    <author>
      <name>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</name>
      <email>me@mwop.net</email>
      <uri>http://mwop.net</uri>
    </author>
    <content xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" type="xhtml">
      <xhtml:div xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><xhtml:p>I can't believe I haven't announced this to the world yet, but
Jen and I are expecting another baby! The due date is
mid-September. And.... we decided at the ultrasound this past week
we would go ahead and find out the gender... and....</xhtml:p>
</xhtml:div>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Enter the Matrix]]></title>
    <published>2005-03-20T22:33:41-06:00</published>
    <updated>2005-03-20T22:36:19-06:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mwop.net/blog/59-Enter-the-Matrix.html"/>
    <id>http://mwop.net/blog/59-Enter-the-Matrix.html</id>
    <author>
      <name>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</name>
      <email>me@mwop.net</email>
      <uri>http://mwop.net</uri>
    </author>
    <content xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" type="xhtml">
      <xhtml:div xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><xhtml:p>I couldn't resist... the car model demands it...</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>For those not familiar with where I live, my family and I live
in West Bolton, VT -- about 20 miles from Burlington, and at the
base of Bolton Mountain. Our daily commute is 4 miles on a dirt
road, another 3 to 4 miles on some twisty two-laners at 35mph to
the interstate, and around 10 miles on the interstate into
Burlington. Then there's all the miles in town getting Maeve to
day-care, Jen or myself dropped off, and whomever has the car to
work. And we only have one car.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>So, you can imagine the crisis when, almost a month ago, our
Toyota Rav4 died on the way in to work.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>We started it up that day, and it had this funny knocking sound.
I remembered a similar sound in my old pickup back in Montana...
the one that died. I determined to get it into a shop that day to
get it diagnosed. The noise came and went while we were on the
backroads, and because it wasn't constant, I figured it couldn't be
too serious.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>And then we tried to get to highway speeds.... a few miles on
the interstate, and it was evident we were in trouble. The Rav was
having trouble maintaining 60mph on the way up French Hill -- when
it normally was able to accelerate past 70mph. And the knocking
sound was getting worse and louder.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>We resolved to pull off at the first exit, at Tafts Corners in
Williston. I pulled into the first gas station there, and as we
tried to find a place to park the vehicle, a mechanic was flagging
at us to stop the car. He came over to where we parked and said,
"Sounds like you've blown your engine."</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>These, of course, were the absolute last words I wanted to
hear.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>To make a long story short, apparently a bearing was thrown when
we started the engine that day, and because we decided to drive it,
we basically destroyed the engine. The cost to replace it: around
$6,000.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Now, we're not exactly what you'd call "financially secure".
We've had a lot of transitions in the past five years, and except
for the past year and a few months, haven't typically both been
working at the same time. We've been in a perpetual cycle of having
enough to pay the bills... but having to pay consistently late. And
we haven't been able to do much, if anything, about our educational
debt. In short, our credit sucks. Which means that $6,000 is a big
deal.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Did I mention that, at the time of the incident, we still had 17
months left on our car payments?</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>And, on top of it, I've been in the middle of a <xhtml:em>huge</xhtml:em>
project for work that's required a fair bit of overtime -- and very
little wiggle room for personal time?</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>The timing could not have been worse, either professionally or
financially.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>We've been very fortunate, however. Jen's parents very
graciously offerred to pay off our existing car loan -- which
helped tremendously. It bought us both the time to figure things
out, as well as eliminated one factor that may have barred our
ability to borrow towards repairs or a new car. Additionally, a
friend of Jen's turns out to be absolutely ruthless when it comes
to dealing with car salespeople, and went to bat for us in working
out a deal. If it hadn't been for her efforts -- and those of the
salesperson, who also went to bat for us -- we would not have
gotten more than a thousand or so for the vehicle; we ended up
getting over $3,000 for it, as is. Finally, the finance guy at the
dealership advocated for us tremendously so we could get a loan on
a new vehicle, with the Rav as our trade in.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>So, to conclude: We're now proud owners of a 2005 Toyota Matrix!
(And now the mystery of the title is revealed... to all you Matrix
fans out there...)</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>I'll try to get a photo of the car up soon... about the time we
update the year-old photos on our site... :-)</xhtml:p>
</xhtml:div>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[php|Tropics]]></title>
    <published>2005-03-20T22:13:46-06:00</published>
    <updated>2005-03-20T22:13:59-06:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mwop.net/blog/58-phpTropics.html"/>
    <id>http://mwop.net/blog/58-phpTropics.html</id>
    <author>
      <name>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</name>
      <email>me@mwop.net</email>
      <uri>http://mwop.net</uri>
    </author>
    <content xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" type="xhtml">
      <xhtml:div xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><xhtml:p>Well, it's official: My IT Manager convinced those in the upper
echelons (well, considering it's a non-profit with only around 20
employees, that meant the president and the CFO) that (1) he and I
need to attend a PHP conference, (2) due to the amount of work
we've been putting in to bring money into the organization, cost
shouldn't be <xhtml:em>too</xhtml:em> much of a deciding factor, and (3)
<xhtml:a href="http://www.phparch.com/tropics" target="_blank">php|Tropics</xhtml:a> isn't <xhtml:em>too</xhtml:em> expensive, especially
considering the sessions involved cover some of the very issues
we've been struggling with the past few months (PHP/MySQL/Apache
and clusters, PHP5 OOP, PHP Security, test-driven development,
Smarty, and more).</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>So, we're going to Cancun in May!</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>This is incredibly exciting! I've never been to Mexico, nor even
a resort, so I'll finally get to find out what my wife and friends
have been talking about all these years. Plus, the conference is
top-notch -- many of the presenters are well-known in the PHP
community, and have blogs I've been following for the past year. (I
only wish that Chris Shiflett's PHP Security series wasn't running
head-to-head with the PHP5 OOP Extensions and PHP 5 Patterns
sessions; I suspect Rob and I will have to do a divide-and-conquer
that day.)</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Drop me a line if you'll be attending -- I'm looking forward to
meeting other PHP junkies!</xhtml:p>
</xhtml:div>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[New Cgiapp Site]]></title>
    <published>2005-02-19T13:38:08-06:00</published>
    <updated>2005-03-25T21:51:18-06:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mwop.net/blog/57-New-Cgiapp-Site.html"/>
    <id>http://mwop.net/blog/57-New-Cgiapp-Site.html</id>
    <author>
      <name>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</name>
      <email>me@mwop.net</email>
      <uri>http://mwop.net</uri>
    </author>
    <content xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" type="xhtml">
      <xhtml:div xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><xhtml:p>I've been extremely busy at work, and will continue to be
through the end of March. I realized this past week that I'd set a
goal of having a <xhtml:a href="http://sourceforge.net" target="_blank">SourceForge</xhtml:a> website up and running for Cgiapp by the
end of January -- and it's now mid-February. Originally, I was
going to backport some of my libraries from PHP5 to PHP4 so I could
do so... and I think that was beginning to daunt me a little.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Fortunately, I ran across a quick-and-dirty content management
solution yesterday called <xhtml:a href="http://gunther.sourceforge.net/" target="_blank">Gunther</xhtml:a>. It does templating in Smarty, and uses
a wiki-esque syntax for markup -- though page editing is limited to
admin users only (something I was looking for). I decided to try it
out, and within an hour or so had a working site ready to
upload.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Cgiapp's new site can be found at <xhtml:a href="http://cgiapp.sourceforge.net/">cgiapp.sourceforge.net</xhtml:a>.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:h4>UPDATE</xhtml:h4>
<xhtml:p>Shortly after I wrote this original post, I figured out what the
strength of Gunther was -- and why I no longer needed it. Gunther
was basically taking content entered from a form and then inserting
that content (after some processing for wiki-like syntax) into a
Smarty template. Which meant that I could do the same thing with
Cgiapp and <xhtml:a href="http://pear.php.net/text_wiki">Text_Wiki</xhtml:a>.
Within an hour, I wrote an application module in Cgiapp that did
just that, and am proud to say that the Cgiapp website is 100%
Cgiapp.</xhtml:p>
</xhtml:div>
    </content>
  </entry>
</feed>
