<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/">
  <channel>
    <title>Tag: personal :: phly, boy, phly</title>
    <description>Tag: personal :: phly, boy, phly</description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 04 Jan 2009 15:31:52 -0600</pubDate>
    <generator>Zend_Feed_Writer 2.0.0beta3 (http://framework.zend.com)</generator>
    <link>http://mwop.net/blog/tag/personal.html</link>
    <atom:link rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" href="http://mwop.net/blog/tag/personal-rss.xml"/>
    <item>
      <title>Seven Things - Tagged by Keith Casey</title>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Jan 2009 15:31:52 -0600</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/204-Seven-Things-Tagged-by-Keith-Casey.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/204-Seven-Things-Tagged-by-Keith-Casey.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    I'm really not sure I understand these "seven things" or "tagged" memes, but
    I'm going to give it a shot, after 
    <a href="http://caseysoftware.com/blog/seven-things-tagged-by-tony-bibbs">Keith Casey</a> did a drive-by
    tagging of me on New Year's Eve.
</p>

<p>
    So, without further ado, seven things you may not know about me...
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2007 Retrospective</title>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jan 2008 05:22:35 -0600</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/154-2007-Retrospective.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/154-2007-Retrospective.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    2007 was a busy year, both personally and professionally. I won't go into
    the personal too much, because, well, it's personal, and some of the details
    are simply inappropriate for blogging material.
</p>

<p>
    Here's the short version:
</p>

<ul>
    <li>One trip to Belgium and The Netherlands.</li>
    <li>Two trips to Israel.</li>
    <li>Two trips to Atlanta, GA (not counting the return trip from Europe, when
    I was stranded for a day due to storms in the Northeast).</li>
    <li>Three different user groups attended, with three presentations.</li>
    <li>One major Zend Framework release</li>
    <li>One PEAR release.</li>
    <li>One podcast.</li>
    <li>One webinar.</li>
    <li>One book published.</li>
    <li>One conference attended.</li>
</ul>

<p>
    What follows is my month-by-month breakdown:
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>I is a published author!</title>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2007 11:41:02 -0600</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/149-I-is-a-published-author!.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/149-I-is-a-published-author!.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    So, in addition to it being my daughter's birthday, which is exciting enough
    in itself, I received a package from my publisher, 
    <a href="http://www.sitepoint.com">SitePoint</a>, with my author copies of 
    <a href="http://www.sitepoint.com/books/phpant2/">The PHP Anthology</a>.
    Very exciting to see stuff I've written published!
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transitions</title>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2005 14:08:39 -0500</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/94-Transitions.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/94-Transitions.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    Life is in transition for me now. Two weeks ago, we got to bring our
    handsome baby boy home, and I haven't been sleeping much since (though more
    than Jen). On top of the sleep deprivation, however, comes more exciting
    news: I've been hired as a PHP Developer by <a
        href="http://www.zend.com/">Zend Technologies</a>!
</p>
<p>
    I was approached by Daniel Kushner in late July regarding another position
    at Zend, and was flown out at the beginning of August. While I felt the
    interview went well, I harbored some doubts; work got fairly busy shortly
    thereafter, and then, of course, Liam was born, and the interview went
    completely out of my head. Until about three days after Liam's birthday,
    when Daniel contacted me again about the PHP Developer position.
</p>
<p>
    Work started yesterday, and I was flown to Zend's offices in Cupertino, CA,
    for orientation and to sit down with both Daniel and others to prepare for
    the projects on which I will be working. Thankfully, the job will not
    require that I move, and I will be working out of the 'home office' in
    Vermont when I return later this week.
</p>
<p>
    The decision to leave <a href="http://assoc.garden.org/about">NGA</a> was
    difficult, but the opportunity to work with Zend is just too good to miss. I
    am honored to be selected by them, and hope this is the beginning of many
    good things to come.
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ZCE - Results are in!</title>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jun 2005 04:48:06 -0500</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/80-ZCE-Results-are-in!.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/80-ZCE-Results-are-in!.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    Got the official notification: I passed the <a
        href="http://www.zend.com/store/education/certification/zend-php-certification.php">Zend
        PHP Certification Exam</a>, and can now report I'm a Zend Certified
    Engineer (ZCE)!
</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">
    <a href="http://zend.com/zce.php?c=ZEND901102&r=0502029"><img
        src="/matthew/img/zce_logo.gif" alt="Zend Certified Engineer" height="47"
        width="73" /></a>
</p>
<p>
    Thanks go to my bosses at <a href="http://assoc.garden.org/">NGA</a> for
    giving me the opportunity to attend <a
        href="http://www.phparch.com/tropics">php|Tropics</a>, to <a
        href="http://www.phparch.com/">Marco Tabini</a> for offering the ZCE
    exam as part of the php|Tropics conference fee, and to my wife, Jen, and
    daughter, Maeve, for putting up with me while I studied... and being good
    sports about having to stay home while I went to Cancun. Hopefully next time I can take you along!
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Moving into City Living</title>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jun 2005 12:01:03 -0500</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/77-Moving-into-City-Living.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/77-Moving-into-City-Living.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    We did it... we moved, again.
</p>
<p>
    However, unlike our previous two moves, which were interstate, this time we
    stayed in the same state. The same county, even. What made (makes; we're
    still finishing up as I write this) this one so jarring is the fact that
    we're going from the rural mountainside to the fourth floor of a new
    apartment/condo building adjoining an interstate spur.
</p>
<p>
    Why would we do this?
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>We're having a baby!</title>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Apr 2005 17:12:20 -0500</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/67-Were-having-a-baby!.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/67-Were-having-a-baby!.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    I can't believe I haven't announced this to the world yet, but Jen and I are
    expecting another baby! The due date is mid-September. And.... we decided at
    the ultrasound this past week we would go ahead and find out the gender...
    and....
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enter the Matrix</title>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Mar 2005 22:36:19 -0600</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/59-Enter-the-Matrix.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/59-Enter-the-Matrix.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    I couldn't resist... the car model demands it...
</p>
<p>
     For those not familiar with where I live, my family and I live in West
     Bolton, VT -- about 20 miles from Burlington, and at the base of Bolton
     Mountain. Our daily commute is 4 miles on a dirt road, another 3 to 4 miles
     on some twisty two-laners at 35mph to the interstate, and around 10 miles
     on the interstate into Burlington. Then there's all the miles in town
     getting Maeve to day-care, Jen or myself dropped off, and whomever has the
     car to work. And we only have one car.
</p>
<p>
    So, you can imagine the crisis when, almost a month ago, our Toyota Rav4
    died on the way in to work.
</p>
<p>
    We started it up that day, and it had this funny knocking sound. I
    remembered a similar sound in my old pickup back in Montana... the one that
    died. I determined to get it into a shop that day to get it diagnosed. The
    noise came and went while we were on the backroads, and because it wasn't
    constant, I figured it couldn't be too serious.
</p>
<p>
    And then we tried to get to highway speeds.... a few miles on the
    interstate, and it was evident we were in trouble. The Rav was having
    trouble maintaining 60mph on the way up French Hill -- when it normally was
    able to accelerate past 70mph. And the knocking sound was getting worse and
    louder.
</p>
<p>
    We resolved to pull off at the first exit, at Tafts Corners in Williston. I
    pulled into the first gas station there, and as we tried to find a place to
    park the vehicle, a mechanic was flagging at us to stop the car. He came
    over to where we parked and said, "Sounds like you've blown your engine."
</p>
<p>
    These, of course, were the absolute last words I wanted to hear.
</p>
<p>
    To make a long story short, apparently a bearing was thrown when we started
    the engine that day, and because we decided to drive it, we basically
    destroyed the engine. The cost to replace it: around $6,000.
</p>
<p>
    Now, we're not exactly what you'd call "financially secure". We've had a lot
    of transitions in the past five years, and except for the past year and a
    few months, haven't typically both been working at the same time. We've been
    in a perpetual cycle of having enough to pay the bills... but having to pay
    consistently late. And we haven't been able to do much, if anything, about our
    educational debt. In short, our credit sucks. Which means that $6,000 is a
    big deal.
</p>
<p>
    Did I mention that, at the time of the incident, we still had 17 months left
    on our car payments?
</p>
<p>
    And, on top of it, I've been in the middle of a <em>huge</em> project for
    work that's required a fair bit of overtime -- and very little wiggle room
    for personal time?
</p>
<p>
    The timing could not have been worse, either professionally or financially.
</p>
<p>
    We've been very fortunate, however. Jen's parents very graciously offerred
    to pay off our existing car loan -- which helped tremendously. It bought us
    both the time to figure things out, as well as eliminated one factor that
    may have barred our ability to borrow towards repairs or a new car.
    Additionally, a friend of Jen's turns out to be absolutely ruthless when it
    comes to dealing with car salespeople, and went to bat for us in working out
    a deal. If it hadn't been for her efforts -- and those of the salesperson,
    who also went to bat for us -- we would not have gotten more than a thousand
    or so for the vehicle; we ended up getting over $3,000 for it, as is.
    Finally, the finance guy at the dealership advocated for us tremendously so
    we could get a loan on a new vehicle, with the Rav as our trade in.
</p>
<p>
    So, to conclude: We're now proud owners of a 2005 Toyota Matrix! (And now
    the mystery of the title is revealed... to all you Matrix fans out there...)
</p>
<p>
    I'll try to get a photo of the car up soon... about the time we update the
    year-old photos on our site... :-)
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>php|Tropics</title>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Mar 2005 22:13:59 -0600</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/58-phpTropics.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/58-phpTropics.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    Well, it's official: My IT Manager convinced those in the upper echelons
    (well, considering it's a non-profit with only around 20 employees, that
    meant the president and the CFO) that (1) he and I need to attend a PHP
    conference, (2) due to the amount of work we've been putting in to bring
    money into the organization, cost shouldn't be <em>too</em> much of a
    deciding factor, and (3) <a href="http://www.phparch.com/tropics"
        target="_blank">php|Tropics</a> isn't <em>too</em> expensive, especially
    considering the sessions involved cover some of the very issues we've been
    struggling with the past few months (PHP/MySQL/Apache and clusters, PHP5
    OOP, PHP Security, test-driven development, Smarty, and more). 
</p>
<p>
    So, we're going to Cancun in May!
</p>
<p>
    This is incredibly exciting! I've never been to Mexico, nor even a resort,
    so I'll finally get to find out what my wife and friends have been talking
    about all these years. Plus, the conference is top-notch -- many of the
    presenters are well-known in the PHP community, and have blogs I've been
    following for the past year. (I only wish that Chris Shiflett's PHP Security
    series wasn't running head-to-head with the PHP5 OOP Extensions and PHP 5
    Patterns sessions; I suspect Rob and I will have to do a divide-and-conquer
    that day.)
</p>
<p>
    Drop me a line if you'll be attending -- I'm looking forward to meeting
    other PHP junkies!
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New Cgiapp Site</title>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Mar 2005 21:51:18 -0600</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/57-New-Cgiapp-Site.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/57-New-Cgiapp-Site.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    I've been extremely busy at work, and will continue to be through the end of
    March. I realized this past week that I'd set a goal of having a <a
        href="http://sourceforge.net" target="_blank">SourceForge</a> website up
    and running for Cgiapp by the end of January -- and it's now mid-February.
    Originally, I was going to backport some of my libraries from PHP5 to PHP4
    so I could do so... and I think that was beginning to daunt me a little. 
</p>
<p>
    Fortunately, I ran across a quick-and-dirty content management solution
    yesterday called <a href="http://gunther.sourceforge.net/"
        target="_blank">Gunther</a>. It does templating in Smarty, and uses a
    wiki-esque syntax for markup -- though page editing is limited to admin
    users only (something I was looking for). I decided to try it out, and
    within an hour or so had a working site ready to upload.
</p>
<p>
    Cgiapp's new site can be found at <a
        href="http://cgiapp.sourceforge.net/">cgiapp.sourceforge.net</a>.
</p>

<h4>UPDATE</h4>
<p>
    Shortly after I wrote this original post, I figured out what the strength of
    Gunther was -- and why I no longer needed it. Gunther was basically taking
    content entered from a form and then inserting that content (after some
    processing for wiki-like syntax) into a Smarty template. Which meant that I
    could do the same thing with Cgiapp and <a
        href="http://pear.php.net/text_wiki">Text_Wiki</a>. Within an hour, I
    wrote an application module in Cgiapp that did just that, and am proud to
    say that the Cgiapp website is 100% Cgiapp.
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
