<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/">
  <channel>
    <title>Tag: personal :: phly, boy, phly</title>
    <description>Tag: personal :: phly, boy, phly</description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 27 Feb 2013 18:41:00 +0000</pubDate>
    <generator>Zend_Feed_Writer 2.1.4dev (http://framework.zend.com)</generator>
    <link>http://mwop.net/blog/tag/personal.html</link>
    <atom:link rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" href="http://mwop.net/blog/tag/personal-rss.xml"/>
    <item>
      <title>On PHP-FIG</title>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Feb 2013 18:41:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/2013-02-27-resigned-from-php-fig.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/2013-02-27-resigned-from-php-fig.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday, I left the PHP-FIG group.</p>

<p>As in: left the github organization I created, and removed myself from the
mailing list I created.</p>

<p>I have contacted members of my development team and the Zend Framework community
review team to see if anybody is willing to represent ZF in the group. I no
longer am.</p>

<p>I was going to leave quietly, but as a favor to Paul M. Jones -- a good friend
and sometimes collaborator -- I'm writing now.</p><p>I had high hopes for the group. It was the culmination of something I've been
ruminating on for almost a decade (<a href="http://www.mwop.net/blog/12-PHP-standards-ruminations.html">see post number 12 on my blog, dated to
January 2004, for
proof</a>). My thoughts
have mainly been around coding standards and best practices, helping educate
developers around their benefits, and how to leverage both in order to
create maintainable code.</p>

<p>First, a few thoughts:</p>

<ul>
<li>I personally feel that interfaces are a bad fit for the organization;
<a href="http://www.mwop.net/blog/2012-12-20-on-shared-interfaces.html">I have outlined my thoughts on interface standardization
elsewhere</a>.</li>
<li>Multiple coding standards are okay. A standard for every project,
organization, or developer is not. The ideal is a handful or so for any given
language, as more than that means there are no standards; it's just a
free-for-all.</li>
<li>No individual coding standard will satisfy all developers. In fact, in my
experience, there will always be choices in <em>any</em> standard that even the
authors of the standard are unhappy with. The point of a coding standard is
not to make everyone happy. It's to have a document that details the structure
of code so that developers focus on the intent of code, not the way it's
formatted.</li>
<li>Coding standards are useless if they do not contain hard rules, as automated
tooling to sniff for CS issues cannot be written. "COULD", "SHOULD", and "CAN"
are all problematic, and any use of "EITHER" is going to make automation
ridiculously complex.</li>
<li>In the end, no matter what the technical arguments are for any given detail,
all coding standards are ultimately subjective. The only objective standard is
what is parseable in the given language.</li>
<li>What matters is that you <em>adopt</em> an <em>existing</em> standard, and <em>use</em> it. When
you do, you can automate some code review, prevent developer commit skirmishes
arising from differences in formatting aesthetics, and focus on the problem
you're trying to solve in your code.</li>
</ul><p>With those thoughts as background, then, I can better explain my departure.</p>

<p>The point of PHP-FIG was to create consensus around practices shared by its
member groups, no more, no less.</p>

<p>When PSR-0 was created, we had around a half-dozen member groups. You have to
start somewhere.</p>

<p>Each proposal since then has had an increasing number of members both
discussing and voting on proposals. That means the early proposals may not be
representative of the later membership. That's a simple fact.</p>

<p>That does not mean the standards should <em>change</em>. Once published, a standard is
done. The only thing that can happen is that a <em>new</em> standard may be created
that can <em>supersede</em> an existing standard, or be used <em>instead</em> <em>of</em> an existing
standard. As examples from existing standards bodies, consider RFC 822, which
codified the format of internet text messages (email); it superseded at least
one other RFC, and has itself been superseded twice (in RFC 2822 and RFC 5322).</p>

<p>PHP-FIG adopted the same workflow. If new practices emerge, or the makeup of the
organization significantly changes, and existing recommendations are found to be
obsolete or outdated, a <em>new</em> recommendation may be proposed to supersede or be
adopted in parallel to them. </p>

<p>Parallel standards from the same body, however, should be considered <em>very</em>
carefully, as they lead to splintering and fragmentation of the standards body
and member organizations. If consensus cannot be achieved, why bother?</p>

<p>What I see happening in the PHP-FIG github organization (in pull request comment
threads) and google group, however, is the exact opposite of the goals that
originally led to the group being formed. Instead of people trying to achieve
consensus, I see a lot of polarizing, all-or-nothing arguments occurring, often
over very subjective things. Developers are defending their opinions and
viewpoints with little to no real analysis of what others present.  I see a lot
of "you're wrong" types of remarks. These are coming largely from non-voting
members, but it means the signal-to-noise ratio within these forums is skewed;
it's hard to find reasonable discussion occurring due to thsi behavior.</p>

<p>The "old guard" is guilty of this at times, too -- but not as often as many
might insist. The insistence of folks like Paul M Jones, Paul Dragoonis, and
Lukas Kahwe Smith that discussion should happen on-list, and that PRs are not
considered for existing, accepted standards is actually reasonable -- for the
reasons I outlined above. A standard is written once; if it needs revision, a
<em>new</em> standard should be written superseding it.</p>

<p>What is most irritating, however, is it doesn't matter how many times such
statements are made; people insist on debating their pet peeves on existing
standards without following the guidelines and established process -- nor
listening when others point out that the debate has occurred before, will occur
again, and needs to stop for now so that we can focus on constructive tasks.
I see a lot of name calling, a lot of accusations of a "dictatorship" (they're
<em>recommendations</em> people; they're not <em>requirements</em>), and overall egotistical
behavior.</p>

<p>I'm tired of it. I have better things to do with my time, things I want to
create, software I want to support, hobbies and interests I want to pursue.
Debating brace placement, tabs vs spaces (for the umpteenth time), or whether or
not annotations have a place in programming in a dynamic language? Not so much.</p>

<p>I hope PHP-FIG can achieve the goals it started with. It will have to do so
without my participation, though.</p>

<h4>Note</h4>

<p>
    I've disabled comments on this post.
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Seven Things - Tagged by Keith Casey</title>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Jan 2009 21:31:52 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/204-Seven-Things-Tagged-by-Keith-Casey.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/204-Seven-Things-Tagged-by-Keith-Casey.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    I'm really not sure I understand these "seven things" or "tagged" memes, but
    I'm going to give it a shot, after 
    <a href="http://caseysoftware.com/blog/seven-things-tagged-by-tony-bibbs">Keith Casey</a> did a drive-by
    tagging of me on New Year's Eve.
</p>

<p>
    So, without further ado, seven things you may not know about me...
</p><ul>
    <li>
        <em>My actual college degree is in comparative religion.</em> I ended up
        in the Religion department at the 
        <a href="http://www.ups.edu/">University of Puget Sound</a> (yes, the
        initials are UPS, which can easily cause confusion with brown,
        parcel-bearing trucks), due to a line of questioning that occurred
        during an Artificial Intelligence course I was taking. The instructor
        was asking if there would be any ethical barrier to unplugging an AI --
        i.e., since it would be capable of thought, would this be equivalent to
        "killing" it? My initial response was, "No," because humans consist of
        more than thought... and then I started wondering a bit about that. My
        emphasis in religion was in Eastern religions. I have a minor in
        Mathematics (CS at UPS was actually CS/Mathematics).
    </li>

    <li>
        <em>I have an FCC Commercial Radio Operator's License.</em> My parents
        were volunteer DJs at <a href="http://www.kglt.net/">KGLT</a> while I
        was growing up, and I did my first radio announcing at... get this...
        the ripe age of 11. I finally got my license before starting college so
        that I could be a DJ at the university station... and ended up as the
        General Manager of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/KUPS">KUPS</a>
        my last two years.
    </li>

    <li>
        <em>I had long hair -- down to my butt at times -- for around ten
            years.</em> Which likely comes as a huge shock to those of you who
        have met me at conferences.  Ironically, I cut it off just prior to
        moving to Vermont as part of an effort to increase the success of my job
        hunt.
    </li>

    <li>
        <em>Before I started my programming career, I was a graphics
        technician.</em> The job immediately prior to my first programming
        position was with a small book publisher that specialized in bird
        hunting and flyfishing guidebooks, for which I created maps, scanned and
        processed images for books, and did book and catalog layout.
    </li>

    <li>
        <em>My first Object Oriented Programming was in Perl.</em> If you've
        ever done OOP in Perl, you'll likely agree with the following statement:
        OOP in any other language is easy by comparison. I mean, come on, a
        syntax where the very definition of an object requires that you "bless"
        a "thingy"? Truly; this is from the "bless" documentation:

        <blockquote>
            bless REF: This function tells the thingy referenced by REF that it
            is now an object in the CLASSNAME package. If CLASSNAME is omitted,
            the current package is used. Because a bless is often the last thing
            in a constructor, it returns the reference for convenience. Always
            use the two-argument version if a derived class might inherit the
            function doing the blessing. See perltoot and perlobj for more about
            the blessing (and blessings) of objects.
        </blockquote>

        This made OOP in PHP look easy.
    </li>

    <li>
        <em>I hold the degree of shodan in Aikido,</em> though I haven't trained
        in several years, due to time and travel constraints. I love the
        movement and flow of Aikido, and always found it very meditative. I also
        liked working with weapons, especially the bokken (wooden sword). This
        is why when I say, "don't make me get my clue bat out," you should take
        heed; I know from experience that white oak leaves a mark.
    </li>

    <li>
        <em>I could have been <a href="http://calevans.com/">Cal</a>.</em> When
        <a href="http://www.zend.com/">Zend</a> first interviewed me, it was for
        the position of Editor-in-Chief of 
        <a href="http://devzone.zend.com/">DevZone</a>. After my in-house
        interview, I had reservations -- I didn't feel experienced or connected
        enough, and was worried I'd botch it. Fortunately for me, and probably
        the PHP community in general, they decided to hire me as a PHP developer
        instead.
    </li>
</ul>

<p>
    So, that's seven things (and quite a bit more, really) about me. And now
    it's time to tag some others:
</p>

<ul>
    <li><a href="http://calevans.com/">Cal Evans</a> is an obvious choice for
    me. Besides having worked together for some years, he's a great friend.</li>

    <li><a href="http://www.leftontheweb.com/">Stefan Koopmanschap</a>, who
    took a train to Amsterdam just to have dinner and a beer with me.</li>
    <li><a href="http://seancoates.com/">Sean Coates</a>, whom I met in an
    airport on the way back from ZendCon two years ago, who lives less than two
    hours away, and whom I haven't seen since that ZendCon.</li>
    <li><a href="http://www.lornajane.net/">Lorna Jane Mitchell</a>, with whom
    I'll be doing a tutorial session on Subversion at php|tek, and who will be
    clearly flustered by being tagged.</li>
    <li><a href="http://jansch.nl/">Ivo Jansch</a>, whom I met almost two years
    ago, and somebody I admire and respect greatly.</li>
    <li><a href="http://www.khankennnels.com/blog/">Ligaya Turmelle</a>, one of
    my co-authors for "The PHP Anthology," the woman who got me to volunteer as
    a phpwomen Booth Babe, and now MySQL guru.</li>
    <li><a href="http://akrabat.com/">Rob Allen</a>, who has made my job easier
    by publishing tutorials and now a book on Zend Framework, and who in
    real-life is a mild-mannered Clark Kent I'd gladly raise a pint with any
    day.</li>
</ul>

<p>
    And here are the rules I'm supposed to pass on to the above bloggers:
</p>

<ul>
    <li>Link your original tagger(s), and list these rules on your blog.</li>
    <li>Share seven facts about yourself in the post - some random, some wierd.</li>
    <li>Tag seven people at the end of your post by leaving their names and the
    links to their blogs.</li>
    <li>Let them know they've been tagged by leaving a comment on their blogs
    and/or Twitter.</li>
</ul>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2007 Retrospective</title>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jan 2008 11:22:35 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/154-2007-Retrospective.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/154-2007-Retrospective.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    2007 was a busy year, both personally and professionally. I won't go into
    the personal too much, because, well, it's personal, and some of the details
    are simply inappropriate for blogging material.
</p>

<p>
    Here's the short version:
</p>

<ul>
    <li>One trip to Belgium and The Netherlands.</li>
    <li>Two trips to Israel.</li>
    <li>Two trips to Atlanta, GA (not counting the return trip from Europe, when
    I was stranded for a day due to storms in the Northeast).</li>
    <li>Three different user groups attended, with three presentations.</li>
    <li>One major Zend Framework release</li>
    <li>One PEAR release.</li>
    <li>One podcast.</li>
    <li>One webinar.</li>
    <li>One book published.</li>
    <li>One conference attended.</li>
</ul>

<p>
    What follows is my month-by-month breakdown:
</p><h3>January</h3>
<p>
    I finished up the last of my three chapters for 
    <a href="http://sitepoint.com/books/phpant2/">The PHP Anthology, 2nd Edition</a>, 
    and promptly used my advance to buy the family a Wii. 
</p>

<p>
    I was also introduced to <a href="http://jansch.nl/">Ivo Jansch</a> through
    work, and had him wow me with one of the 
    <a href="http://ibuildings.nl">ibuildings</a> products.
</p>

<h3>February</h3>
<p>
    Mid-month, my boss at <a href="http://www.zend.com/">Zend</a>, Boaz, got the
    go-ahead to use the ibuildings WDE platform to build our new website CMS;
    part of the plan would include training at the ibuildings home office in
    Vlissingen, NL... which meant I had to get my passport pronto.
</p>

<p>
    Towards the end of the month, I was invited to 
    <a href="http://bostonphp.org">BostonPHP</a> to present 
    building a simple <a href="http://framework.zend.com/">Zend Framework</a>
    CRUD application, along with <a href="http://hagunbu.ch/">Chuck Hagenbuch</a> 
    of the <a href="http://horde.org/">HORDE project</a>. While there, 
    <a href="http://cake.insertdesignhere.com/">Nate Abele</a> heckled me, and
    then joined Chuck and myself for an impromptu framework panel; a good time
    was had by all.
</p>

<h3>March</h3>
<p>
    I flew to Brussels, Belgium, where I met my supervisor, Boaz, so we could go
    to Vlissingen. We spent the day in Brussels, walking around and visiting
    such sites as the Cathedral of St. Michael, La Grand Place, and the Mannekin
    Pis. 
</p>

<p>
    Our visit to ibuildings was very productive, and I was very impressed by the
    team there; everybody was very knowledgeable and skilled. I presented a Zend
    Framework overview, as well as an abbreviated version of the Best Practices
    talk I'd given with Mike Naberezny at the 2006 ZendCon; the latter ignited a
    ton of questions and enthusiasm.
</p>

<p>
    On returning home, I had a ton of work to do on the zend.com CMS, and this
    continued in spurts through November. The job was made much easier by the
    ibuildings WDE product.
</p>

<p>
    I closed out a ton of MVC issues in the Zend Framework, and we released the
    first beta version late in the month.
</p>

<h3>April</h3>
<p>
    At the beginning of the month, our landlord threw us for a loop and
    announced he was going to sell our apartment... meaning that we either had
    to step up our plans to purchase a home, or start looking for a new rental.
    Ultimately, we ended up looking for a rental, due to time constraints. The
    next two months would be highlighted with the look for a new place as well
    as countless showings of our apartment to potential buyers.
</p>

<p>
    Mid-month, we packed up the family and flew down to Atlanta, GA, to visit my
    wife's family. While there, we were able to go to the Atlanta Zoo and see
    Mei Lan, their baby panda -- way cute!
</p>

<h3>May</h3>
<p>
    Mid-month, we found a new place in Richmond, VT -- a small village about 10
    minutes from Burlington, near where we originally lived when we first moved
    to Vermont. 
</p>

<p>
    During the first RC for Zend Framework, released at the end of the month, I
    introduced the ViewRenderer, a feature for auto-rendering views based on the
    current controller and action name -- a feature common to many frameworks.
    However, it ostensibly broke a ton of existing applications by being enabled
    by default -- not one of my more popular decisions. Since the 1.0.0 release,
    I've heard little grumbling about it, and it's now often cited as an
    ease-of-use feature -- go figure.
</p>

<h3>June</h3>
<p>
    The first week of June, I flew to Tel Aviv, Israel, to start training people
    on the new CMS, as well as to work with our entire ebiz team to finalize the
    work plan for completing the CMS. It was, needless to say, my first time to
    Israel or the Middle East, and I was constantly confronted with culture
    shock. Europe was an easy transition to make, but Israel was completely
    foreign to me -- everything from the way people drove, to the architecture,
    to the food was different. Unfortunately, I arrived a day late due to a
    flight cancellation, and missed the tour of Jerusalem my supervisor had
    planned for all of us. However, he took me to the city of Yafa, an Arabic
    city where the Israeli's originally tried to settle before building Tel Aviv
    to the north. The architecture was amazing, as were the winding, narrow
    streets of the old city.
</p>

<p>
    I was also told during this trip that Andi had requested transferring me
    full-time to the Zend Framework team. I would spend the next week or two
    weighing my options, and ultimately decided to do so.
</p>

<p>
    A week after I returned, we moved into our new rental in Richmond. The kids
    love the new place, which has a bedroom for each of them, a yard, and
    porches on each entrance.
</p>

<p>
    Somehow, I also found time to record my first (and so far only) 
    <a href="http://devzone.zend.com/article/2140-PHP-Abstract-Podcast-Episode-2---Backup-or-Die">PHP Abstract podcast</a>.
</p>

<h3>July</h3>
<p>
    We released <a href="http://framework.zend.com/">Zend Framework</a> 1.0.0 at
    the beginning of the month, marking our first stable release. While many
    still view it as incomplete, the overwhelming feedback has been positive,
    and we've had over 2 million downloads to date.
</p>

<p>
    I accepted the transfer to the Zend Framework team, but the condition was
    made that I would stay part-time on the ebiz team until the new site was
    launched.  This meant that the next 5 months were spent splitting my time
    between the two projects, often working late and on weekends to get work
    done.
</p>

<p>
    Towards the end of the month, we took a long weekend camping in Vermont's
    Northeast Kingdom. The weather was unseasonably wet, but we persevered and
    had a great time. 5 days of offline time was definitely needed!
</p>

<p>
    I also finally released the first stable version of 
    <a href="http://pear.php.net/packages/File_Fortune">File_Fortune</a> on 
    <a href="http://pear.php.net/">PEAR</a>, over a year since I'd first
    proposed it. The package interfaces with mod_fortune files, allowing both
    the ability to read and write such files, with full binary compatability.
</p>

<h3>August</h3>
<p>
    Not much to report in August, except work, work, and more work.
</p>

<h3>September</h3>
<p>
    My ebiz supervisor, Boaz, flew me to Tel Aviv for a second time, this time
    to perform a "brain dump" for the rest of the team before I transitioned
    fully out of the team, and also to help setup our new data center and
    release procedures. This time, Boaz took me to Jerusalem himself during my
    last full day in the country. If you've never been to the city, you should
    definitely put it on your list of things to do before you die. With my
    degree in religion, the place was full of meaning for me, but it would be
    putting it lightly to say that religion is palpable in the air there. We
    visited the Wailing Wall, the Via Dolorosa, the Church of the Holy
    Sepulchre, and listened to the muezzins sing the call to prayer for the
    muslims. The tour was simply amazing.
</p>

<p>
    A few days after I returned, I flew down to New York City for a special
    meeting of <a href="http://nyphp.org/">NYPHP</a>, where 
    <a href="http://blogs.zend.com/author/mark/">Mark de Visser</a> presented on
    various Zend products and initiatives, and I gave a Zend Framework overview.
</p>

<p>
    A week after the NYPHP presentation, I did a
    <a href="http://www.zend.com/webinars">zend.com webinar</a>
    on the Zend Framework MVC layer.
</p>

<h3>October</h3>
<p>
    October was the month of <a href="http://www.zendcon.con/">ZendCon</a>. I
    presented a full-day tutorial on best practices and unit testing with 
    <a href="http://sebastian-bergmann.de/">Sebastian Bergmann</a> and 
    <a href="http://naberezny.com/">Mike Naberezny</a>; despite the length and
    subject matter, we were SRO for most of the day. 
</p>
<p>
    I also did a main-stage presentation on Zend Framework's MVC components,
    directly following <a href="http://terrychay.com/blog/">Terry Chay</a> -- an
    intimidating situation at best. From the feedback I've seen, the
    presentation was well-received, and I had somewhere between 120 and 150
    attendees -- phenomenal! (Even more amazing was how many people were
    familiar with MVC in general!)
</p>

<p>
    One great thing about the conference was the fact that I got to network with
    a number of framework developers, both Zend Framework and otherwise,
    including Nate Abele of CakePHP as well as 
    <a href="http://paul-m-jones.com">Paul M. Jones</a> of 
    <a href="http://solarphp.com">the Solar framework</a>. Many good
    conversations were had.
</p>

<p>
    Late in the month, 
    <a href="http://sitepoint.com/books/phpant2/">The PHP Anthology, 2nd Edition</a>, 
    my first published book as an author, was finally released!
</p>

<h3>November</h3>
<p>
    I spent much of the month working on 
    <a href="http://framework.zend.com/wiki/display/ZFPROP/Zend_Layout">Zend_Layout</a>,
    a much requested component that simplifies and automates Two Step Views in
    Zend Framework. I also started work implementing 
    <a href="http://framework.zend.com/wiki/pages/viewpage.action?pageId=33071">Zend_View Enhanced</a>,
    a set of view helpers for making complex views with Zend_View possible.
</p>

<p>
    I also started playing with <a href="http://twitter.com/">Twitter</a> a bit,
    and came up with a 
    <a href="http://framework.zend.com/wiki/display/ZFPROP/Zend_Service_Twitter">Zend_Service_Twitter</a>
    proposal for interacting with the Twitter API via PHP.
</p>

<p>
    And finally, the Sunday before Thanksgiving, we finally launched the new 
    <a href="http://www.zend.com/">Zend.com</a> site, which was well-received in
    the blogosphere.
</p>

<h3>December</h3>
<p>
    A goal I've had for some time has been to form a PHP user group in the
    Burlington area. A friend of mine pointed out to me sometime this fall that
    there's actually already
    <a href="http://groups.google.com/group/Burlington-VT-PHP">a Google Group</a> 
    formed; he and the original founder started planning a meeting for early
    December. I spoke at this inaugural meeting, presenting Zend Framework's MVC
    layer yet again; a good time was had by all, and a lot of enthusiasm for
    future meetings was generated.
</p>

<p>
    I finished up Zend_Layout and Zend_View Enhanced with the help of Ralph
    Schindler, and got a new proposal up for 
    <a href="http://framework.zend.com/wiki/display/ZFPROP/Zend_Form">Zend_Form</a>,
    just in time for my holidays to begin -- 11 days with family and with little
    to no internet connectivity during a trip to Atlanta, GA for one of only a
    handful of Christmases I've spent without snow.
</p>

<h2>Summary</h2>
<p>
    This year was <em>incredibly</em> busy -- three cross-seas trips, one
    cross-continent trip, a move, and several trips along the Eastern Seaboard;
    three user group presentations, and eight presentations over the course of
    the year; one conference; one move; one PEAR release; one podcast; one
    webinar; one book; and countless hours of programming.
</p>

<p>
    My goals for the coming year? I'm too tired to even think about it ;-).
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>I is a published author!</title>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2007 17:41:02 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/149-I-is-a-published-author!.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/149-I-is-a-published-author!.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    So, in addition to it being my daughter's birthday, which is exciting enough
    in itself, I received a package from my publisher, 
    <a href="http://www.sitepoint.com">SitePoint</a>, with my author copies of 
    <a href="http://www.sitepoint.com/books/phpant2/">The PHP Anthology</a>.
    Very exciting to see stuff I've written published!
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transitions</title>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2005 19:08:39 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/94-Transitions.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/94-Transitions.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    Life is in transition for me now. Two weeks ago, we got to bring our
    handsome baby boy home, and I haven't been sleeping much since (though more
    than Jen). On top of the sleep deprivation, however, comes more exciting
    news: I've been hired as a PHP Developer by <a
        href="http://www.zend.com/">Zend Technologies</a>!
</p>
<p>
    I was approached by Daniel Kushner in late July regarding another position
    at Zend, and was flown out at the beginning of August. While I felt the
    interview went well, I harbored some doubts; work got fairly busy shortly
    thereafter, and then, of course, Liam was born, and the interview went
    completely out of my head. Until about three days after Liam's birthday,
    when Daniel contacted me again about the PHP Developer position.
</p>
<p>
    Work started yesterday, and I was flown to Zend's offices in Cupertino, CA,
    for orientation and to sit down with both Daniel and others to prepare for
    the projects on which I will be working. Thankfully, the job will not
    require that I move, and I will be working out of the 'home office' in
    Vermont when I return later this week.
</p>
<p>
    The decision to leave <a href="http://assoc.garden.org/about">NGA</a> was
    difficult, but the opportunity to work with Zend is just too good to miss. I
    am honored to be selected by them, and hope this is the beginning of many
    good things to come.
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ZCE - Results are in!</title>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jun 2005 09:48:06 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/80-ZCE-Results-are-in!.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/80-ZCE-Results-are-in!.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    Got the official notification: I passed the <a
        href="http://www.zend.com/store/education/certification/zend-php-certification.php">Zend
        PHP Certification Exam</a>, and can now report I'm a Zend Certified
    Engineer (ZCE)!
</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">
    <a href="http://zend.com/zce.php?c=ZEND901102&r=0502029"><img
        src="/matthew/img/zce_logo.gif" alt="Zend Certified Engineer" height="47"
        width="73" /></a>
</p>
<p>
    Thanks go to my bosses at <a href="http://assoc.garden.org/">NGA</a> for
    giving me the opportunity to attend <a
        href="http://www.phparch.com/tropics">php|Tropics</a>, to <a
        href="http://www.phparch.com/">Marco Tabini</a> for offering the ZCE
    exam as part of the php|Tropics conference fee, and to my wife, Jen, and
    daughter, Maeve, for putting up with me while I studied... and being good
    sports about having to stay home while I went to Cancun. Hopefully next time I can take you along!
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Moving into City Living</title>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jun 2005 17:01:03 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/77-Moving-into-City-Living.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/77-Moving-into-City-Living.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    We did it... we moved, again.
</p>
<p>
    However, unlike our previous two moves, which were interstate, this time we
    stayed in the same state. The same county, even. What made (makes; we're
    still finishing up as I write this) this one so jarring is the fact that
    we're going from the rural mountainside to the fourth floor of a new
    apartment/condo building adjoining an interstate spur.
</p>
<p>
    Why would we do this?
</p><p>
    First, some history. In case you haven't been reading the blog, Jen and I
    are having another baby. And our one-and-only car died a few months ago
    (which we've since replaced). And we were living in West Bolton, a good
    half-hour by car to Burlington, where we work and often play -- which means
    that we've been having a long commute each day (50 minutes, minimum, each
    way). And we've been spending far more on our rent and utilities than we'd
    like; we haven't been able to save at all.
</p>
<p>
    We got to thinking that this was not an ideal situation for us. We cannot
    afford another car (either the initial purchase or the ongoing expense of
    one), so we decided it was time to look for something closer to town. And
    then, as we did, we discovered that places were either not close enough to
    change the commute significantly, or we were going to be spending the same
    amount of money (or more) to live closer as we were to live up in the
    mountains -- and sometimes this was with less space.
</p>
<p>
    We finally found several places we liked and which were in the price range
    we were targetting, and it came down to how we felt about our potential
    landlords, and they us. And the one that was cheapest, most convenient to
    our workplaces, and still somewhat reasonably sized... is the <a
        href="http://www.citysedgevt.com/">brand-new apartment on the city's
        edge</a> we're currently occupying.
</p>
<p>
    Our landlord is very nice, and a mortgage broker for a local bank; yet, this
    is actually his first rental property. He and his wife breed some sort of
    dog, and he was quite happy to have Cuervo move in. Additionally, when we
    came to visit the location, Maeve had her tiger, Talula, with her, and he
    liked the name so much that he suggested it to his wife for a puppy name. It
    just felt like a good fit.
</p>
<p>
    Now, as I mentioned above, we've moved from the rural mountainside to the
    city: we've gone from complete quiet (apart from the peepers singing) and
    complete darkness (other than the blanket of stars in the sky) to a constant
    hum of traffic and lights that never shut off. But in the mountains, all we
    could see was the sky above and trees surrounding us; we couldn't even see
    the mountain on which we lived. The new apartment is on the top floor,
    looking west...  which gives us an excellent view of the Adirondacks and a
    portion of Lake Champlain, as well as beautiful sunsets.
</p>
<p>
    The new location poses some challenges. The place is significantly smaller
    than our place in West Bolton, and doesn't have a full basement for storage
    (obviously). Plus, we're <em>adding</em> to our family, yet we're reducing
    the number of rooms by one. And, for pete's sake, we're on the fourth floor
    -- what about when Cuervo needs to pee?
</p>
<p>
    Well, now that we're mostly moved in, I can answer some of these questions.
    The move has been difficult, but a good experience. We've taken it as an
    opportunity to simplify. Which, in a nutshell, means, "throw out unnecessary
    shit." I discovered that I had four file cabinet drawers full of old papers
    that I had absolutely no use for, nor attachment to. We took several boxes
    of books to a local charity, and untold numbers of clothes and toys. We've
    now got just about everything over to the new place, except some stuff from
    the office and some storage from the basement... and I find myself wondering
    why we ever felt we needed all the things we got rid of.
</p>
<p>
    Cuervo's settling in nicely, though she's having a little trouble
    understanding that she can't be as vocal. As it turns out, Cuervo's getting
    old. She's now seven, and in this first week of walks, I've discovered that
    in her little 'explores' up in West Bolton, she was likely walking for up to
    10 minutes, and then sitting on her butt or outright laying down for a while
    before getting up to continue. She doesn't even pull incessantly on the
    leash anymore! She's certainly very healthy and in good shape, but she
    simply doesn't have quite the energy and enthusiasm I remember from walking
    her in years past. So, as it turns out, the move is probably a good thing
    for her, too -- we interact with her more, and also can keep a better eye on
    her general health.
</p>
<p>
    I've also discovered that I like living near more people. Every day, I run
    into people, usually while walking Cuervo. I already know several people by
    name, which is several people more than I met all of last year.
    Additionally, the building was built on the edge of some property that
    contains four other apartment buildings, some of which are Section 8 --
    which means that when Maeve goes down to play at the playground, she's
    meeting kids of many ethnicities and economic backgrounds. (We met a couple
    of girls whose family emigrated from Rwanda, for instance!)
</p>
<p>
    The move has been trying in many ways, though. The sheer amount of stuff to
    do has alternately overwhelmed myself and then Jen, and we have found
    ourselves getting frustrated with each other quite often. However, the
    common experience of our 'simplifying' process has also drawn us together --
    it's a goal we both share, and for which we must both sacrifice.
    Additionally, the new place has a layout that encourages staying connected:
    the kitchen, dining room, and living room all flow into each other, and the
    bedrooms open off this main room, meaning we're always within hearing
    distance -- and often sight -- of each other. 
</p>
<p>
    So, all in all, while difficult, I feel the move has been a very good one
    for the family as a whole. Now if only I could turn off the parking lot
    lights and passing traffic when I go to bed...
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>We're having a baby!</title>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Apr 2005 22:12:20 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/67-Were-having-a-baby!.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/67-Were-having-a-baby!.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    I can't believe I haven't announced this to the world yet, but Jen and I are
    expecting another baby! The due date is mid-September. And.... we decided at
    the ultrasound this past week we would go ahead and find out the gender...
    and....
</p><p style="font-size: 1.5em; font-weight: bold;">
    It's A BOY!!!!
</p>
<p>
    I'm terribly excited, in case you can't tell. I'd had a dream shortly after
    we found out we were pregnant that we were at the doctor's for the
    ultrasound, and I'd seen quite clearly a little penis; I've been convinced
    since then that we would have a boy. It was amazing to have it confirmed --
    so many emotions ran through me -- how will I be a father to a boy, how will
    I teach him to shave, will I need to learn about sports if he takes to them,
    IT'S A BOY!!!
</p>
<p>
    We've been going through baby names since then. Before Maeve was born, we'd
    planned on calling a boy Aidan; a couple years ago, we though maybe Will
    would be a good name (Will is one of the principal characters in Philip
    Pullman's <em>His Dark Materials</em> trilogy). However, one of my
    co-workers, has two boys -- Will and Aidan -- whom Maeve plays with, so
    those names are out.
</p>
<p>
    We've narrowed the names down to four, though: Nolan, Liam, Gavin, and
    Devin. Leave a comment and let us know what you think!
</p>
<p>
    Oh, did I mention -- it's a boy!!!!
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enter the Matrix</title>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Mar 2005 04:36:19 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/59-Enter-the-Matrix.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/59-Enter-the-Matrix.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    I couldn't resist... the car model demands it...
</p>
<p>
     For those not familiar with where I live, my family and I live in West
     Bolton, VT -- about 20 miles from Burlington, and at the base of Bolton
     Mountain. Our daily commute is 4 miles on a dirt road, another 3 to 4 miles
     on some twisty two-laners at 35mph to the interstate, and around 10 miles
     on the interstate into Burlington. Then there's all the miles in town
     getting Maeve to day-care, Jen or myself dropped off, and whomever has the
     car to work. And we only have one car.
</p>
<p>
    So, you can imagine the crisis when, almost a month ago, our Toyota Rav4
    died on the way in to work.
</p>
<p>
    We started it up that day, and it had this funny knocking sound. I
    remembered a similar sound in my old pickup back in Montana... the one that
    died. I determined to get it into a shop that day to get it diagnosed. The
    noise came and went while we were on the backroads, and because it wasn't
    constant, I figured it couldn't be too serious.
</p>
<p>
    And then we tried to get to highway speeds.... a few miles on the
    interstate, and it was evident we were in trouble. The Rav was having
    trouble maintaining 60mph on the way up French Hill -- when it normally was
    able to accelerate past 70mph. And the knocking sound was getting worse and
    louder.
</p>
<p>
    We resolved to pull off at the first exit, at Tafts Corners in Williston. I
    pulled into the first gas station there, and as we tried to find a place to
    park the vehicle, a mechanic was flagging at us to stop the car. He came
    over to where we parked and said, "Sounds like you've blown your engine."
</p>
<p>
    These, of course, were the absolute last words I wanted to hear.
</p>
<p>
    To make a long story short, apparently a bearing was thrown when we started
    the engine that day, and because we decided to drive it, we basically
    destroyed the engine. The cost to replace it: around $6,000.
</p>
<p>
    Now, we're not exactly what you'd call "financially secure". We've had a lot
    of transitions in the past five years, and except for the past year and a
    few months, haven't typically both been working at the same time. We've been
    in a perpetual cycle of having enough to pay the bills... but having to pay
    consistently late. And we haven't been able to do much, if anything, about our
    educational debt. In short, our credit sucks. Which means that $6,000 is a
    big deal.
</p>
<p>
    Did I mention that, at the time of the incident, we still had 17 months left
    on our car payments?
</p>
<p>
    And, on top of it, I've been in the middle of a <em>huge</em> project for
    work that's required a fair bit of overtime -- and very little wiggle room
    for personal time?
</p>
<p>
    The timing could not have been worse, either professionally or financially.
</p>
<p>
    We've been very fortunate, however. Jen's parents very graciously offerred
    to pay off our existing car loan -- which helped tremendously. It bought us
    both the time to figure things out, as well as eliminated one factor that
    may have barred our ability to borrow towards repairs or a new car.
    Additionally, a friend of Jen's turns out to be absolutely ruthless when it
    comes to dealing with car salespeople, and went to bat for us in working out
    a deal. If it hadn't been for her efforts -- and those of the salesperson,
    who also went to bat for us -- we would not have gotten more than a thousand
    or so for the vehicle; we ended up getting over $3,000 for it, as is.
    Finally, the finance guy at the dealership advocated for us tremendously so
    we could get a loan on a new vehicle, with the Rav as our trade in.
</p>
<p>
    So, to conclude: We're now proud owners of a 2005 Toyota Matrix! (And now
    the mystery of the title is revealed... to all you Matrix fans out there...)
</p>
<p>
    I'll try to get a photo of the car up soon... about the time we update the
    year-old photos on our site... :-)
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>php|Tropics</title>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Mar 2005 04:13:59 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/58-phpTropics.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/58-phpTropics.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    Well, it's official: My IT Manager convinced those in the upper echelons
    (well, considering it's a non-profit with only around 20 employees, that
    meant the president and the CFO) that (1) he and I need to attend a PHP
    conference, (2) due to the amount of work we've been putting in to bring
    money into the organization, cost shouldn't be <em>too</em> much of a
    deciding factor, and (3) <a href="http://www.phparch.com/tropics"
        target="_blank">php|Tropics</a> isn't <em>too</em> expensive, especially
    considering the sessions involved cover some of the very issues we've been
    struggling with the past few months (PHP/MySQL/Apache and clusters, PHP5
    OOP, PHP Security, test-driven development, Smarty, and more). 
</p>
<p>
    So, we're going to Cancun in May!
</p>
<p>
    This is incredibly exciting! I've never been to Mexico, nor even a resort,
    so I'll finally get to find out what my wife and friends have been talking
    about all these years. Plus, the conference is top-notch -- many of the
    presenters are well-known in the PHP community, and have blogs I've been
    following for the past year. (I only wish that Chris Shiflett's PHP Security
    series wasn't running head-to-head with the PHP5 OOP Extensions and PHP 5
    Patterns sessions; I suspect Rob and I will have to do a divide-and-conquer
    that day.)
</p>
<p>
    Drop me a line if you'll be attending -- I'm looking forward to meeting
    other PHP junkies!
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
