<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title type="text">Tag: programming :: phly, boy, phly</title>
  <updated>2009-01-05T07:00:49+0000</updated>
  <generator uri="http://framework.zend.com" version="2.1.1dev">Zend_Feed_Writer</generator>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mwop.net/blog/tag/programming.html"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://mwop.net/blog/tag/programming-atom.xml"/>
  <id>http://mwop.net/blog/tag/programming.html</id>
  <entry xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2008: The year in review]]></title>
    <published>2008-12-31T19:17:03+0000</published>
    <updated>2009-01-05T07:00:49+0000</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mwop.net/blog/203-2008-The-year-in-review.html"/>
    <id>http://mwop.net/blog/203-2008-The-year-in-review.html</id>
    <author>
      <name>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</name>
      <email>me@mwop.net</email>
      <uri>http://mwop.net</uri>
    </author>
    <content xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" type="xhtml">
      <xhtml:div xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><xhtml:p>That time of year again -- wrap-up time. Each year, it seems
like it's the busiest ever, and I often wonder if it will ever slow
down. As usual, I'm restricting myself to primarily professional
activities out of respect for the privacy of my family.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>The short, executive summary:</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:ul>
<xhtml:li>One trip to Israel</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>One trip to The Netherlands</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>One trip to California's Bay Area</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>One trip to Atlanta, GA</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>Three minor releases of Zend Framework</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>Seven webinars, six for zend.com and one for Adobe</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>Three conferences attended as a speaker, including:
<xhtml:ul>
<xhtml:li>One six-hour workshop</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>One three-hour tutorial (as a co-presenter)</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>Four regular sessions</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>Two panel sessions (one scheduled, one for an uncon)</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>Two uncon sessions (one as a co-presenter)</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>One foul-mouthed Pecha Kucha talk</xhtml:li>
</xhtml:ul>
</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>Ten Burlington, VT PHP User's Group meetings attended; I spoke
at many</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>One Bug Hunt week organized</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>Two books reviewed as a technical editor</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>Six articles for <xhtml:a href="http://devzone.zend.com/">DevZone</xhtml:a></xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>50 blog entries (including this one)</xhtml:li>
</xhtml:ul>
<xhtml:p>Read on for the gruesome, month-by-month breakdown.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:h2>January and February</xhtml:h2>
<xhtml:p>I started coding <xhtml:code>Zend_Form</xhtml:code> in earnest in January,
and had a preview ready for testing mid-month. The pace continued
into February, as I addressed user feedback and issues, and
continued working feverishly towards what would become Zend
Framework's 1.5.0 release.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>I also answered many questions for and had many discussions with
<xhtml:a href="http://www.calevans.com/">Cal Evans</xhtml:a> relating to his
"Guide to Programming Zend Framework".</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:h2>March</xhtml:h2>
<xhtml:p>I gave my first webinar of the year early in March, on the
subject of <xhtml:code>Zend_Form</xhtml:code>; it was very well attended, but
unfortunately there was an issue recording the sound, so the
recording was never released. After two more failed attempts at
re-recording, we gave up. I apologize to all who have wanted to
view it.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>While working towards the 1.5.0 release, <xhtml:a href="http://ralphschindler.com/">Ralph Schindler</xhtml:a> and I also
finished up final touches on <xhtml:code>Zend_Layout</xhtml:code> and the
various "placeholder" view helper implementations.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>On 17 March 2008, we released Zend Framework 1.5, our first
minor release following 1.0.0.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>I started blogging tips and tricks for 1.5, and also writing
articles for <xhtml:a href="http://devzone.zend.com/">DevZone</xhtml:a> during
March, and had tremendous amounts of feedback. In fact, one blog
post, on "Login and Authentication", is still one of the most
trafficked on my blog after 9 months.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>I also began what I envisioned as a series of Vim posts, but,
alas, it has resulted only in two.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:h2>April</xhtml:h2>
<xhtml:p>Following the 1.5 release, I did weekly posts for a month or so
covering various features of Zend Framework, including Front
Controller plugins, Action Controller helpers, and View helpers.
Towards the end of the month, the entire team participated in a
Q&amp;A webinar to discuss the 1.5 release.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:h2>May</xhtml:h2>
<xhtml:p>At the beginning of the month, I released the last in my series
of 1.5 tutorials on <xhtml:a href="http://devzone.zend.com/">DevZone</xhtml:a>,
covering Form decorators. This has saved me countless hours on IRC
and in the mailing lists explaining how this aspect of forms
work.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>During this month, we also finally announced that Zend Framework
would be partnering with <xhtml:a href="http://dojotoolkit.org/">Dojo</xhtml:a>
to provide an out-of-the-box RIA solution. I began work identifying
the various integration points and creating proposals for
implementation. I also did a Q&amp;A webinar with the Dojo team
outlining the proposed integration.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>At the end of the month, the ZF team reorganized the subversion
repository to allow for an "Extras" repository, and also to ensure
that projects originating in the laboratory or extras and migrating
to the standard library retain all history. Even with the big
notices we put on the ZF site, articles on DevZone, and posts on
various blogs, we still get questions on this seven months later.
Let this be a lesson to you: plan your repositories for any
contingency as early as you can!</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:h2>June</xhtml:h2>
<xhtml:p>I started June with a trip to Israel, to visit the Zend offices.
I met up with <xhtml:a href="http://andigutmans.blogspot.com/">Andi</xhtml:a>
in Newark, and we flew from there to Israel several rows apart in
coach. One of the best meals I've ever had was after we landed and
he invited me to his sister's place for dinner, and we dined on
chicken marinated in home-pressed olive oil and fresh herbs,
hummus, and pitas baked with fresh oregano. The rest of the week
was spent in the office, in endless meetings.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Four days after returning from Israel, I flew to Amsterdam for
the <xhtml:a href="http://www.phpconference.nl">Dutch PHP Conference</xhtml:a>,
to which I'd been invited to speak. My good friend <xhtml:a href="http://wolerized.com/">Remi</xhtml:a> took the train up to Amsterdam to
meet me the day I flew in, and we walked and walked and walked
around the city, until dinnertime. <xhtml:a href="http://www.leftontheweb.com/">Stefan Koopmanschap</xhtml:a> then met us
for a lovely dinner, and I returned to the hotel to finish
screenshots for the six-hour workshop on Zend Framework I was
presenting the next day. The entire conference was wonderful, and I
met many fantastic people, including <xhtml:a href="http://www.priebsch.de/">Stefan Priebsch</xhtml:a>, <xhtml:a href="http://www.lornajane.net/">Lorna Jane Mitchell</xhtml:a>, <xhtml:a href="http://andries.systray.be/">Andries Seutens</xhtml:a>, and many, many
more -- plus many familiar faces, such as Sebastian Bergmann, Derek
Rethans, Mike Van Dam, Felix de Vliegher, and Marco Tabini.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>On my blog, I started raising the question of how we will refer
to Abstract classes and Interfaces in PHP 5.3, but I think my
arguments went largely unheard and/or misunderstood.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>The last half of the month was spent working on both Dojo
integration with Zend Framework (a task that turned out fairly
easy, in large part due to some wonderful guidance from <xhtml:a href="http://higginsforpresident.net/">Pete Higgins</xhtml:a>), and preparing
<xhtml:code>Zend_Test_PHPUnit</xhtml:code> for inclusion in Zend Framework
1.6.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:h2>July</xhtml:h2>
<xhtml:p>I think I'll remember July as the month of the neverending
release cycle.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:h2>August</xhtml:h2>
<xhtml:p>On 8 August 2008, PHP 4 officially died. I thought about
drinking a toast for about 3 seconds, forgot about it, and finished
my beer.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>The following Monday, we released the second release candidate
of Zend Framework 1.6.0.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>August, too, became part of the month of the neverending release
cycle.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:h2>September</xhtml:h2>
<xhtml:p>Finally, on 2 September 2008, we released 1.6.0 into the wild.
My contributions included, as noted earlier, Dojo integration,
PHPUnit integration, and code assistance on our Captcha solution
and file upload support.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>The next day, I gave yet another webinar on Zend Framework and
Dojo integration, but finally actually had some code samples and
working demos to show off, soundly quieting the claims of
vaporware. I also started learning about Dojo release builds, under
the tutelage of Pete Higgins.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Mid-month saw the fourth annual Zend/PHP Conference, this time
in Santa Clara. I was involved in a marathon of seven different
sessions over three days. I've rarely been so exhausted, and it's a
wonder I remember anything following -- but I had a wonderful time
with the PHP <xhtml:em>community</xhtml:em> following, including <xhtml:a href="http://www.bombdiggity.net/">Jon Whitcraft</xhtml:a>, <xhtml:a href="http://akrabat.com/">Rob Allen</xhtml:a>, the <xhtml:a href="http://ibuildings.nl/">ibuildings</xhtml:a> crew, and more.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>I also finally got to meet <xhtml:a href="http://sklar.com/">David
Sklar</xhtml:a>, to whom I owe the fact of my first public speaking
engagement at the first ZendCon.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Following ZendCon, there were announcements that two colleagues
at Zend I respect highly were leaving for new opportunities: Mark
de Visser left to join Sonatype as its CEO, and Cal Evans left to
head ibuildings' new Center for PHP Expertise. I wish them both
luck in their new endeavors.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:h2>October</xhtml:h2>
<xhtml:p>I helped <xhtml:a href="http://wadearnold.com/blog/">Wade Arnold</xhtml:a>
complete testing of <xhtml:code>Zend_Amf</xhtml:code> as we prepared for the
Zend Framework 1.7.0 release, and learned a fair deal about Flex in
the process.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>During this time, I also completed a technical review of
<xhtml:a href="http://zendframeworkinaction.com">Zend Framework in
Action</xhtml:a>. Rob Allen and Nick Lo had contacted me earlier in the
year, but I'd been unable to commit to it. In July, I agreed, only
to get sucked into the neverending release cycle. Fortunately, in
October I had time to complete the review. The book is very well
written and organized, and I can't recommend it highly enough. I
was able to give some constructive feedback and have some dialog
with Rob that, hopefully, helped clarify a few areas of Zend
Framework, and will hopefully help their readers.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>For the 1.7 release of Zend Framework, I worked on performance
benchmarking, profiling, improvements, and a best practices
guide.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Late in the month, I delivered a webinar with Lee Brimelow for
Adobe to showcase the upcoming AMF support in Zend Framework.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:h2>November</xhtml:h2>
<xhtml:p>The last few days of October and first week of November, I
organized a bug hunt week for Zend Framework, culminating in a
<xhtml:a href="http://bughuntday.org/">Bug Hunt Day</xhtml:a> event held and
organized by <xhtml:a href="http://www.phpbelgium.be/">PHP Belgium</xhtml:a>
and <xhtml:a href="http://phpgg.nl/">phpGG</xhtml:a> (The Netherlands). We
closed out close to 150 issues over the course of the week and a
couple dozen during the Bug Hunt Day, and got many contributors
started on the path of professional bug squashing
enlightenment.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>The second week of November, I flew down to Atlanta, GA, to
attend <xhtml:a href="http://phpworks.mtacon.com/">php|works</xhtml:a>.. err,
php|works/pyworks. First off, a huge thank you to <xhtml:a href="http://naramore.net/blog/">Elizabeth Naramore</xhtml:a>, who helped me
fairly last minute to make sure I had a room to stay in. While
there, I presented my Dojo and Zend Framework talk, but with some
updated content. Of course, every presenter's nightmare occurred,
and I had to reboot my laptop mid-stream. I surprised myself, and,
I think, the attendees by actually being able to continue speaking
while we waited for my machine to reboot.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>I also presented a <xhtml:a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pecha_Kucha">Pecha Kucha</xhtml:a> talk --
I re-branded the phrase as "Pikachu" a couple weeks earlier (a
reference to the iconic character in <xhtml:a href="http://www.pokemon.com/">Pokemon</xhtml:a>, a game I play with my
daughter), and that phrase has, for better or for worse, stuck. My
talk was on how to be banned from an open source project, and I
swore entirely too much. It was a nice release, however, as I try
to be politic in public usually, and sometimes just need to
rant.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>I got to see a ton of old and new friends alike while there --
former Zenders <xhtml:a href="http://mikenaberezny.com/">Mike
Naberezny</xhtml:a> and <xhtml:a href="http://paul-m-jones.com/">Paul M.
Jones</xhtml:a>, <xhtml:a href="http://caseysoftware.com/blog/">Keith
Casey</xhtml:a>, <xhtml:a href="http://ishouldbecoding.com/">Matthew
Turland</xhtml:a>, <xhtml:a href="http://jansch.nl/">Ivo</xhtml:a> and a bunch of the
ibuildings crew, Pollita (sorry, I have to stop linking everyone
now...), Sebastian... basically, a ton of the usual suspects. I
also met a lot of new people, many of them introducing themselves
as ZF users; I appreciate all of you introducing yourselves, as
<xhtml:em>you</xhtml:em> are the reason I code.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>The following Monday, 17 November 2008, we released Zend
Framework 1.7.0, timed to coincide with the the Adobe MAX
conference, as AMF support was our major story for the release.
<xhtml:code>Zend_Amf</xhtml:code> has generated tremendous buzz in both the PHP
and Flash/Flex communities, due to the simplicity and robustness of
its design. This release also marked the first release to include
the extras repository -- which now ships with community-contributed
<xhtml:a href="http://jquery.com/">JQuery</xhtml:a> support.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:h2>December</xhtml:h2>
<xhtml:p><xhtml:a href="http://shiflett.org/">Chris Shiflett</xhtml:a> and <xhtml:a href="http://seancoates.com/">Sean Coates</xhtml:a> organized this year's
<xhtml:a href="http://phpadvent.org/2008/">PHP Advent Calendar</xhtml:a>, and
solicited entries from a select group of PHP community members a
week in advance. I didn't volunteer to contribute for the first
week, but managed to get mine in on the first day... only to see it
appear the very next. Hopefuly, my guide to responsible
contributions will help those wondering how to report and/or fix
bugs in open source projects.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>I started blogging more, in part due to more free time in the
evenings (it's nice when the kids go to bed at a reasonable hour!),
and in part due to finally putting a number of ideas into a
blogging "backlog" so that I could pick up and post when I had
time. From this, I added an entry on mumbles/irssi integration,
autocompletion with ZF and Dojo, created a simple pubsub
implementation for PHP, and started a series of posts on how to
architect models (and some concrete tips for doing so). I have more
posts in December than I have in several other months combined.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:h2>Reflection</xhtml:h2>
<xhtml:p>This past year, I became much more involved with both the Zend
Framework and greater PHP communities, and feel I have enriched my
life with many wonderful new friends -- some local, some global. I
feel truly fortunate to be working in a job I love, contributing to
a project that helps others do the jobs they love, and part of such
an accepting and vibrant group of people.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Looking back, I travelled less, though because most of it was in
a five month period, it felt like more. On that note, I vow never
to do back to back trips across the big pond, as it was incredibly
exhausting.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:h2>Looking ahead to 2009</xhtml:h2>
<xhtml:p>I have several things to look forward to already in 2009. I'll
be continuing my series of posts on models. In February, I will
have an article published in a print magazine for the first tiem.
I'll be speaking at PHP Quebec in March, presenting two sessions
and sitting in on a panel. I hope to speak at several other
conferences, and potentially write more articles and tutorials.
Overall, I want to contribute more to the ecosystem of best
practices in PHP, particularly in the areas of testing and
deployment strategies.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>I hope this post finds <xhtml:em>you</xhtml:em> in good health and spirits,
and that you have a fantastic start to the new year!</xhtml:p>
</xhtml:div>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mumbles irssi integration]]></title>
    <published>2008-12-10T20:01:50+0000</published>
    <updated>2008-12-12T20:19:50+0000</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mwop.net/blog/197-Mumbles-irssi-integration.html"/>
    <id>http://mwop.net/blog/197-Mumbles-irssi-integration.html</id>
    <author>
      <name>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</name>
      <email>me@mwop.net</email>
      <uri>http://mwop.net</uri>
    </author>
    <content xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" type="xhtml">
      <xhtml:div xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><xhtml:p>I've been using IRC regularly for the past six to nine months,
in large part due to the growing ZF community on the <xhtml:a href="http://freenode.net/">Freenode</xhtml:a> #zftalk channel (unfortunately,
I simply don't have time to be in that particular channel any more,
but you can generally find me in #zftalk.dev), but also to keep in
contact with other peers, friends, and colleagues.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>One difficulty, however, is keeping productivity high while
staying on IRC. To me, the ultimate client would provide me
notifications when somebody mentions my name or a watch word -
allowing me to read the channel at my leisure, yet still respond to
people in a timely fashion.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>I've tried a variety of IRC clients over the months, starting
with Pidgin (poor interface for IRC), mirc (huge difficulties
figuring out the UI), xchat (not bad, but seemed a bit heavy),
Chatzilla (I liked the interface, but once you got many tabs going,
it was unwieldy switching around between them; I also hated that
Firefox dying or restarting caused Chatzilla to do likewise), and
now <xhtml:a href="http://irssi.org/">irssi</xhtml:a>.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>So far, irssi is the best I've tried -- I can run it in screen,
allowing me to keep it open as long as my machine is running. The
interface is reasonable, and cleanly keeps channels separate from
private messages. Opening, closing, and manipulating windows is
easy. And it's highly scriptable... including in a language I
actually use! The perl bindings are top notch, though sometimes
cryptic. What's important, however, is that there are plenty of
examples out there if you want to try doing something. So, I
figured I'd write up a quick plugin to trigger notifications.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>I've been using a number of different notification servers for
linux, and personally like both <xhtml:a href="http://gnotify.sourceforge.net">gnotify</xhtml:a> and <xhtml:a href="http://www.mumbles-project.org/">mumbles</xhtml:a>. Both are very
lightweight and offer network protocols for triggering
notifications.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>I first tried using gnotify. It has a very, very simple TCP
protocol, and I've had success creating messages from the shell,
PHP, and perl. Unfortunately, for some reason, using it in irssi
displayed some odd behavior: I'd lose the cursor and the ability to
enter input from the time a notification triggered until it
completed (i.e., the notification disappeared). Forking the process
did not appear to help.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>So, I decided to try out mumbles. Mumbles is written in python,
and has themeable notifications -- already a plus. It runs via dbus
by default, but can also optionally spawn a server that implements
the <xhtml:a href="http://growl.info/">Growl protocol</xhtml:a> -- making it
accessible for any process to send notifications. Additionally, it
has a command-line utility for triggering notifications -- by
default over dbus, but optionally by contacting the growl server,
if running.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Growl's protocol is a bit involved, and I didn't want to spend
too much time on this. So, I did a quick, dirty hack: I used
backticks to trigger the CLI utility. And it works
<xhtml:em>fantastically</xhtml:em> -- no delays whatsoever. Here's the
code:</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:div class="example">
<xhtml:pre>
<xhtml:code lang="perl" xml:lang="perl">
# $HOME/.irssi/scripts/mumbles.pl
use strict;
use Irssi;
use Irssi::Irc;
use vars qw($VERSION %IRSSI);

$VERSION = '0.1.0';
%IRSSI = (
    authors     =&gt; \"Matthew Weier O'Phinney\",
    contact     =&gt; 'matthew@weierophinney.net',
    name        =&gt; 'Mumbles notifications for irssi',
    description =&gt; 'This script enables mumbles notifications for irssi',
    license     =&gt; 'New BSD',
        changed     =&gt; \"2008-12-10\"
);


sub mumbles_sig_printtext {
  my ($dest, $text, $stripped) = @_;

  if (($dest-&gt;{level} &amp; (MSGLEVEL_HILIGHT|MSGLEVEL_MSGS)) &amp;&amp; ($dest-&gt;{level} &amp; MSGLEVEL_NOHILIGHT) == 0)
  {
    if ($dest-&gt;{level} &amp; MSGLEVEL_PUBLIC)
    {
      mumbles($dest-&gt;{target} . \" : \" . $text);
    }
  }
}

sub mumbles {
    my $message = shift;
    my $response;

    $message =~ s/[^!-~\s]//g;

    `/usr/bin/mumbles-send -g 127.0.0.1 -s \"IRC\" \"$message\"`;
}

Irssi::command_bind 'mumbles' =&gt; sub {
    my ($message) = @_;
    mumbles($message);
};

Irssi::signal_add({
  'print text'    =&gt; \&amp;mumbles_sig_printtext
});
</xhtml:code>
</xhtml:pre></xhtml:div>
<xhtml:p>This triggers a notification for any "highlight" event --
basically, anytime anybody "says" my name in a channel, or mentions
a keyword I've marked for highlighting. Additionally, I created a
"mumbles" command so that I can send test messages (usage:
"/mumbles "this is the message..."). You could certainly bind to
other events, such as topic changes, joins, parts, etc -- I'm only
interested in highlight events.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>You may note the regexp in there. One thing I discovered was
that most messages contained control and non-ascii characters that
often resulted in unreadable notifications, as well as some nasty
messages reported by irssi. The regexp removes anything not in the
ascii character set or the set of whitespace definitions prior to
emitting the notification.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Something else I needed to do was configure compiz to ensure
that the notifications actually popped <xhtml:em>above</xhtml:em> my windows. I
did this by going into the compiz configuration manager, selecting
"General Options", selecting the "Focus &amp; Raise Behaviour" tab,
and modifying the "Focus Prevention Windows" to read as
follows:</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:pre>
<xhtml:code>(any) &amp; !(class=Mumbles)
</xhtml:code>
</xhtml:pre>
<xhtml:p>To test it, I placed the script in
$HOME/.irssi/scripts/mumbles.pl, and then, in irssi, executed
"/load mumbles.pl".</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Once I had it to my liking, I symlinked it into my
$HOME/.irssi/scripts/autorun/ directory, allowing it to run as soon
as irssi loads. I can now have irssi running in a screen session,
or minimize the terminal, and get notifications -- keeping me
productive and informed at the same time.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p><xhtml:b>UPDATED 2008-12-12:</xhtml:b> Added information on how to load the
script, as well as fixed the location to the autorun directory.
Thanks, @sidhighwind!</xhtml:p>
</xhtml:div>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Vimgrep and Vim Project]]></title>
    <published>2008-10-21T11:36:49+0000</published>
    <updated>2008-10-23T01:55:03+0000</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mwop.net/blog/194-Vimgrep-and-Vim-Project.html"/>
    <id>http://mwop.net/blog/194-Vimgrep-and-Vim-Project.html</id>
    <author>
      <name>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</name>
      <email>me@mwop.net</email>
      <uri>http://mwop.net</uri>
    </author>
    <content xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" type="xhtml">
      <xhtml:div xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><xhtml:p>Chris Hartjes today was <xhtml:a href="http://www.littlehart.net/atthekeyboard/2008/10/20/vim-programming-bounty-fuzzyfind-inside-files/">
on a quest for a "find in project" feature for Vim</xhtml:a>. "Find in
Project" was a feature of Textmate that he'd grown accustomed to
and was having trouble finding an equivalent for.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>The funny thing is that Textmate is a newcomer, and, of course,
vim has had such a feature for years. The thing to remember with
vim, of course, is its unix roots; typically if you know the unix
command for doing something, you can find what you need in vim. In
this case, the key is the vimgrep plugin, which ships in the
standard vim distribution.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>There are a variety of resources on vimgrep. The vim
documentation includes a chapter on it, and a quick <xhtml:a href="http://www.google.com/search?q=vimgrep">google search</xhtml:a> on the
subject turns up some nice tutorials immediately. If you've ever
used grep, the syntax is very straightforward:</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:pre>
<xhtml:code>vimgrep /{pattern}/[g][j] {file} ...
</xhtml:code>
</xhtml:pre>
<xhtml:p>The "g" option indicates that all matches for a search will be
returned instead of just one per line, and the "j" option tells vim
<xhtml:em>not</xhtml:em> to jump to the first match automatically. What does
the "g" flag really mean, though, and how are searches
returned?</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Vimgrep returns search results in what's known as a "quickfix"
window, and this is where the vimgrep documentation falls apart...
it doesn't explain what this is, or link to it (which would be a
nice indication that it actually has a separate topic for
this).</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>The Quickfix window is a pane that shows a search result per
line. Each line shows the file that matches, the line number, and
the contents of that line:</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:pre>
<xhtml:code>/home/matthew/git/bugapp/application/controllers/helpers/GetForm.php|10| * @var Zend_Loader_PluginLoader
</xhtml:code>
</xhtml:pre>
<xhtml:p>You can't do much from this window; it simply serves as a visual
indicator of what file you're currently looking at from the list.
However, in the main window, you can start iterating through the
results one at a time, using a subset of the Quickfix commands. As
a quick summary:</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:ul>
<xhtml:li><xhtml:b>:cc</xhtml:b> will move to the next match in the list</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li><xhtml:b>:cn</xhtml:b> will move to the next match in the list</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li><xhtml:b>:cp</xhtml:b> will move to the previous match in the list</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li><xhtml:b>:cr</xhtml:b> will rewind to the first match in the list</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li><xhtml:b>:cla</xhtml:b> will fast forward to the last match in the
list</xhtml:li>
</xhtml:ul>
<xhtml:p>When done, you can simply close the Quickfix window/pane, and
continue working.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>I should note that vimgrep <xhtml:em>is</xhtml:em> cross-platform. On
*nix-based systems, it defaults to using the native grep command,
but it also contains an internal (slower) implementation for use on
operating systems that do not provide grep by default. You may also
map the command to alternate implementations if desired.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>I personally use this feature most with the <xhtml:a href="http://www.vim.org/scripts/script.php?script_id=69">project
plugin</xhtml:a>. Project maps vimgrep to two different commands:
&lt;Leader&gt;g and &lt;Leader&gt;G. The first will grep all files
in the current project at the current level; the second does the
same, but also recurses into subprojects. This is an incredibly
easy way to refactor code, particularly for name changes.</xhtml:p>
</xhtml:div>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[git-svn Tip: don't use core.autocrlf]]></title>
    <published>2008-09-24T16:16:27+0000</published>
    <updated>2008-09-24T16:16:27+0000</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mwop.net/blog/191-git-svn-Tip-dont-use-core.autocrlf.html"/>
    <id>http://mwop.net/blog/191-git-svn-Tip-dont-use-core.autocrlf.html</id>
    <author>
      <name>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</name>
      <email>me@mwop.net</email>
      <uri>http://mwop.net</uri>
    </author>
    <content xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" type="xhtml">
      <xhtml:div xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><xhtml:p>I've been playing around with <xhtml:a href="http://git.or.cz/">Git</xhtml:a> in the past couple months, and have
been really enjoying it. Paired with subversion, I get the best of
all worlds -- distributed source control when I want it (working on
new features or trying out performance tuning), and non-distributed
source control for my public commits.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p><xhtml:a href="http://github.com/guides/dealing-with-newlines-in-git">Github</xhtml:a>
suggests that when working with remote repositories, you turn on
the autocrlf option, which ensures that changes in line endings do
not get accounted for when pushing to and pulling from the remote
repo. However, when working with git-svn, this actually causes
issues. After turning this option on, I started getting the error
"Delta source ended unexpectedly" from git-svn. After a bunch of
aimless tinkering, I finally asked myself the questions, "When did
this start happening?" and, "Have I changed anything with Git
lately?" Once I'd backed out the config change, all started working
again.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>In summary: don't use "git config --global core.autocrlf true"
when using git-svn.</xhtml:p>
</xhtml:div>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Server Upgrades... lost entries...]]></title>
    <published>2008-05-16T13:05:13+0000</published>
    <updated>2008-05-21T18:35:27+0000</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mwop.net/blog/171-Server-Upgrades...-lost-entries....html"/>
    <id>http://mwop.net/blog/171-Server-Upgrades...-lost-entries....html</id>
    <author>
      <name>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</name>
      <email>me@mwop.net</email>
      <uri>http://mwop.net</uri>
    </author>
    <content xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" type="xhtml">
      <xhtml:div xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><xhtml:p>My good friend, Rob, hosts my site for me, in return for helping
with server maintenance. After being on Gentoo for the past three
years, though, we decided it was time to switch to something a
little easier to maintain, so last night we wiped the system
partitions and installed Ubuntu server.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>I'll say this: the setup is much faster! However, we had a few
gotchas that surprised us -- it didn't setup our RAID array
out-of-the-box, which led to a good hour of frustration as we tried
to verify that the install wouldn't wipe it, and then to verify
that we could re-assemble it. (We succeeded.) Additionally, we
second-guessed a few things we shouldn't have, which led to needing
to back out and reconfigure. But what was over a 12 hour install
with Gentoo we accomplished in a matter of a few hours with Ubuntu
server -- so it was a huge success that way.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Unfortunately, our mysqldump of all databases... wasn't, a fact
we discovered only after importing it into the new system. I ended
up losing my blog database and PEAR channel database. Fortunately,
the PEAR channel has not changed at all in the past year, so we had
an old backup that worked, and I had a snapshot of my blog database
from three weeks ago I was able to use. As a result, there are a
few missing entries, but for the most part, all works. If you
commented on one of those missing entries, my apologies.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Now that the install is done, I'm also finalizing some design
changes to my blog -- it's time to leave the black and white for
more colorful grounds. Look for a revamp in the coming weeks!</xhtml:p>
</xhtml:div>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Submitting Bug Reports]]></title>
    <published>2008-03-08T17:06:13+0000</published>
    <updated>2008-03-09T14:18:36+0000</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mwop.net/blog/161-Submitting-Bug-Reports.html"/>
    <id>http://mwop.net/blog/161-Submitting-Bug-Reports.html</id>
    <author>
      <name>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</name>
      <email>me@mwop.net</email>
      <uri>http://mwop.net</uri>
    </author>
    <content xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" type="xhtml">
      <xhtml:div xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><xhtml:p>Full disclosure: I am employed by <xhtml:a href="http://www.zend.com/">Zend</xhtml:a> to program <xhtml:a href="http://framework.zend.com/">Zend Framework</xhtml:a>. That said, the
following is all my opinion, and is based on my experiences with
Zend Framework, as well as answering questions on a variety of
mailing lists and with other OSS projects (PEAR, Solar, and Cgiapp
in particular).</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>One of my biggest pet peeves in the OSS world is vague bug/issue
reports and feature requests. I cannot count the number of times
I've seen a report similar to the following:</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:blockquote>&lt;Feature X&gt; doesn't work; you need to fix it
<xhtml:b>now!</xhtml:b></xhtml:blockquote>
<xhtml:p>If such a report comes in on an issue tracker, it's invariably
marked critical and high priority.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>What bothers me about it? Simply this: it gives those
responsible for maintaining Feature X absolutely no information to
work on: what result they received, what was expected, or how
exactly they were using the feature. The reviewer now has to go
into one or more cycles with the reporter fishing for that
information -- wasting everyone's time and energy.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Only slightly better are these reports:</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:blockquote>&lt;Feature X&gt; doesn't work -- I keep getting
&lt;Result X&gt; from it, which is incorrect.</xhtml:blockquote>
<xhtml:p>At least this tells the reviewers what they reporter is
receiving... but it doesn't tell them how they got there, or what
they're expecting.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>So, the following should be your mantra when reporting issues or
making feature requests:</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:ul>
<xhtml:li>What is the minimum code necessary to reproduce the issue or
show the desired API?</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>What is the expected result?</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>What is the actual result?</xhtml:li>
</xhtml:ul>
<xhtml:h2>What makes up a good issue report?</xhtml:h2>
<xhtml:p>A good issue report has to contain the above three points, plain
and simple. Without this information, a reviewer simply does not
have the tools with which to properly deal with the issue.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:h3>Reproduce code</xhtml:h3>
<xhtml:p>Quite often, you'll find that an application breaks. It is up to
you to find the root cause of that breakage: what minimal amount of
code do I need to write in order to cause the breakage to occur?
Sometimes this will require a little digging -- you may have a
result that is unexpected, but it may be a symptom of something
breaking earlier.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>For example, in working on Zend_Form in the past couple weeks, I
had a number of issues reported against how the new MultiCheckbox
element was working. One issue noted that populate() was not
properly populating the checkboxes.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>When pressed for reproduce code, the reporter provided the
$_POST array with which they were trying to populate the form:</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:div class="example">
<xhtml:pre>
<xhtml:code lang="php" xml:lang="php">
$_POST = array(
    'foo' =&gt; array(
        0 =&gt; array(0 =&gt; 'bar'),
        1 =&gt; array(0 =&gt; 'baz'),
        2 =&gt; array(0 =&gt; 'bat')
    )
);
</xhtml:code>
</xhtml:pre></xhtml:div>
<xhtml:p>In looking at it, I knew immediately that it was related to
another issue that had been reported. In that issue, the reporter
noted that the input elements rendered by Zend_Form for
MultiCheckbox elements had redundant array notation:</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:div class="example">
<xhtml:pre>
<xhtml:code lang="html" xml:lang="html">
    &lt;input type=\"checkbox\" value=\"foo\" name=\"foo[][]\" value=\"bar\" /&gt;
</xhtml:code>
</xhtml:pre></xhtml:div>
<xhtml:br/>
<xhtml:p>In the former case, we're seeing a symptom of the latter case:
the redundant array notation was causing a form submission that
simply could not populate the element. If the reporter of the
former case had looked at the form used to send the $_POST data
they posted in the tracker, either they likely would have noticed
the similar issue already reported in the tracker -- or I, as the
reviewer, would have been able to quickly mark the bug as a
duplicate.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Regardless, the main point is this: using the value of a POST
request to reproduce an issue is not doing your homework. You need
to look for the <xhtml:em>minimal</xhtml:em> code necessary to reproduce the
issue, and the value provided in $_POST is typically a
<xhtml:em>symptom</xhtml:em> of an issue that has already occurred.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Another rule of thumb with creating reproduce code is to keep
the environment minimal. Try writing up <xhtml:em>fresh</xhtml:em> code in a
scratchpad that you can run over and over again until you get the
result that you're trying to report. This does a few things: it
helps simplify the use case causing the issue, and it often will
help you track down exactly where things begin to break. Sometimes,
and I can attest to this, it helps you find places where you're
doing things wrong in your <xhtml:em>own</xhtml:em> code in the first place,
alleviating the need entirely to submit a report.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>What does the reviewer do with this code? Well, a <xhtml:em>good</xhtml:em>
developer will use it as a test case in the unit test suite --
which is another reason to keep the code down to the minimum
required to reproduce the issue. This code will often end up in the
test suite in order to document the issue report -- as well as to
prove, once a solution is in place, that the issue has been
resolved.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>The above advice is useful even when reporting a feature
request, this information is useful. The reviewer then gets an idea
of the desired API, and they can write a test case against it.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:h3>Expected Results</xhtml:h3>
<xhtml:p>In addition to the reproduce case, you should provide the
expected results. These show clearly your expectations of the code.
The reviewer can use this information in several ways:</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:ul>
<xhtml:li>In the test suite, the reviewer can use the expected results in
assertions to verify the issue (or prove that it is now
corrected)</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>To show where the reporter has flawed assumptions. In some
cases, the expectations of the code are different than the
documented assertions, and the reviewer can then point out where
the differences lie -- which helps to educate the reporter in
proper usage of the code.</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>In the case of a feature request, this will indicate how the
reporter expects the new feature to behave. The reviewer can then
use that expectation as an assertion in the test suite.</xhtml:li>
</xhtml:ul>
<xhtml:h3>Actual Results</xhtml:h3>
<xhtml:p>The actual results are important as they contrast against the
expected results, showing where the breakage is. If the reviewer
cannot recreate these results, then it likely means that the
reproduce code provided is not the actual code needed to reproduce
the issue, or it may mean that environmental differences --
differences in OS or PHP version, for instance -- may be a factor
in recreating the issue.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>In the case of a feature request, you could omit the actual
results, as there won't be any.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:h3>Always search for your issue or feature request</xhtml:h3>
<xhtml:p>Finally, one additional mantra to add to your repertoire: search
the issue tracker and/or mailing lists <xhtml:em>before</xhtml:em> reporting an
issue or requesting a feature. I cannot tell you how many bugs I've
closed as duplicates, or how many times I've had to respond to an
email with the phrase, "this is a known issue." It pays to do your
homework: search and see if others have made the same request. In
many cases, you may actually find a <xhtml:em>solution</xhtml:em> to your issue
posted by others -- either a way to extend a class to get the
behaviour you're expecting, a patch to the software, or even a note
regarding what public release or snapshot contains a fix. There's
no reason to waste people's time by reporting a known issue.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>The best time to search for your issue, believe it or not, is
<xhtml:em>after</xhtml:em> you've done the other steps. Until you know exactly
what code reproduces the issue, and have clearly defined your
expectations and the real results, it can be difficult to identify
when your issue matches another.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:h2>In Conclusion</xhtml:h2>
<xhtml:ul>
<xhtml:li>What is the minimum code necessary to reproduce the issue?</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>What is the expected result?</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>What is the actual result?</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>Have you searched for similar requests in public forums?</xhtml:li>
</xhtml:ul>
<xhtml:p>If you can start answering the above questions <xhtml:em>before</xhtml:em>
posting your issues, you'll start receiving more detailed and
useful responses from those reviewing your issues or feature
requests, and reduce the number of "I don't understand" or "I need
more information" responses. Guaranteed.</xhtml:p>
</xhtml:div>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Backwards Compatibility]]></title>
    <published>2008-02-07T14:56:11+0000</published>
    <updated>2008-02-07T14:56:11+0000</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mwop.net/blog/158-Backwards-Compatibility.html"/>
    <id>http://mwop.net/blog/158-Backwards-Compatibility.html</id>
    <author>
      <name>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</name>
      <email>me@mwop.net</email>
      <uri>http://mwop.net</uri>
    </author>
    <content xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" type="xhtml">
      <xhtml:div xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><xhtml:p><xhtml:a href="http://jansch.nl/">Ivo</xhtml:a> already pointed this out,
but I want to point it out again: Boy Baukema writes <xhtml:a href="http://www.ibuildings.nl/blog/archives/541-Backward-compatibility,-bane-of-the-developer.html">
a very nice entry regarding backwards compatibility</xhtml:a> on the
ibuildings.nl corporate blog.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Backwards compatibility (BC) is a tricky thing to support, even
when you strive hard to, as Boy puts it, "think hard about your
API" prior to release. Somebody will always come along and point
out ways it could have been done better or ways it could be
improved. I've had to wrestle with these issues a ton since joining
the Zend Framework team, and while it often feels like the wrong
thing to do to tell somebody, "too little, too late" when they have
genuinely good feedback for you, its often in the best interest of
the many users already using a component.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>I had the pleasure of meeting Boy last year when visiting the
ibuildings.nl offices, and he's got a good head on his shoulders.
He does a nice job outlining the issues and a number of approaches
to BC; if you develop a project for public consumption, you should
definitely head over and read what he has to say.</xhtml:p>
</xhtml:div>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Apache HOSTNAME on Clusters]]></title>
    <published>2008-01-25T22:38:16+0000</published>
    <updated>2008-01-26T13:22:44+0000</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mwop.net/blog/156-Apache-HOSTNAME-on-Clusters.html"/>
    <id>http://mwop.net/blog/156-Apache-HOSTNAME-on-Clusters.html</id>
    <author>
      <name>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</name>
      <email>me@mwop.net</email>
      <uri>http://mwop.net</uri>
    </author>
    <content xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" type="xhtml">
      <xhtml:div xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><xhtml:p>In an effort to debug issues on a cluster, I was trying to
determine which machine on the cluster was causing the issue. My
idea was that I could insert a header token identifying the
server.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>My first idea was to add the directive 'Header add X-Server-Ip
"%{SERVER_ADDR}e" in my httpd.conf. However, due to the nature of
our load balancer, Apache was somehow resolving this to the load
balancer IP address on all machines of the cluster -- which was
really, really not useful.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>I finally stumbled on a good solution, however: you can set
environment variables in apachectl, and then pass them into the
Apache environment using the PassEnv directive from mod_env; once
that's done, you can use the environment variable anywhere.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>In my apachectl, I added the line "export HOSTNAME=`hostname`".
Then, in my httpd.conf, I added first the line "PassEnv HOSTNAME",
followed by the directive 'Header add X-Server-Name
"%{HOSTNAME}e"'. Voila! I now had the hostname in the header, which
gave me the information I needed for debugging.</xhtml:p>
</xhtml:div>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2007 Retrospective]]></title>
    <published>2008-01-01T21:49:26+0000</published>
    <updated>2008-01-03T11:22:35+0000</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mwop.net/blog/154-2007-Retrospective.html"/>
    <id>http://mwop.net/blog/154-2007-Retrospective.html</id>
    <author>
      <name>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</name>
      <email>me@mwop.net</email>
      <uri>http://mwop.net</uri>
    </author>
    <content xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" type="xhtml">
      <xhtml:div xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><xhtml:p>2007 was a busy year, both personally and professionally. I
won't go into the personal too much, because, well, it's personal,
and some of the details are simply inappropriate for blogging
material.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Here's the short version:</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:ul>
<xhtml:li>One trip to Belgium and The Netherlands.</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>Two trips to Israel.</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>Two trips to Atlanta, GA (not counting the return trip from
Europe, when I was stranded for a day due to storms in the
Northeast).</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>Three different user groups attended, with three
presentations.</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>One major Zend Framework release</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>One PEAR release.</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>One podcast.</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>One webinar.</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>One book published.</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>One conference attended.</xhtml:li>
</xhtml:ul>
<xhtml:p>What follows is my month-by-month breakdown:</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:h3>January</xhtml:h3>
<xhtml:p>I finished up the last of my three chapters for <xhtml:a href="http://sitepoint.com/books/phpant2/">The PHP Anthology, 2nd
Edition</xhtml:a>, and promptly used my advance to buy the family a
Wii.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>I was also introduced to <xhtml:a href="http://jansch.nl/">Ivo
Jansch</xhtml:a> through work, and had him wow me with one of the
<xhtml:a href="http://ibuildings.nl">ibuildings</xhtml:a> products.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:h3>February</xhtml:h3>
<xhtml:p>Mid-month, my boss at <xhtml:a href="http://www.zend.com/">Zend</xhtml:a>,
Boaz, got the go-ahead to use the ibuildings WDE platform to build
our new website CMS; part of the plan would include training at the
ibuildings home office in Vlissingen, NL... which meant I had to
get my passport pronto.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Towards the end of the month, I was invited to <xhtml:a href="http://bostonphp.org">BostonPHP</xhtml:a> to present building a simple
<xhtml:a href="http://framework.zend.com/">Zend Framework</xhtml:a> CRUD
application, along with <xhtml:a href="http://hagunbu.ch/">Chuck
Hagenbuch</xhtml:a> of the <xhtml:a href="http://horde.org/">HORDE project</xhtml:a>.
While there, <xhtml:a href="http://cake.insertdesignhere.com/">Nate
Abele</xhtml:a> heckled me, and then joined Chuck and myself for an
impromptu framework panel; a good time was had by all.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:h3>March</xhtml:h3>
<xhtml:p>I flew to Brussels, Belgium, where I met my supervisor, Boaz, so
we could go to Vlissingen. We spent the day in Brussels, walking
around and visiting such sites as the Cathedral of St. Michael, La
Grand Place, and the Mannekin Pis.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Our visit to ibuildings was very productive, and I was very
impressed by the team there; everybody was very knowledgeable and
skilled. I presented a Zend Framework overview, as well as an
abbreviated version of the Best Practices talk I'd given with Mike
Naberezny at the 2006 ZendCon; the latter ignited a ton of
questions and enthusiasm.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>On returning home, I had a ton of work to do on the zend.com
CMS, and this continued in spurts through November. The job was
made much easier by the ibuildings WDE product.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>I closed out a ton of MVC issues in the Zend Framework, and we
released the first beta version late in the month.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:h3>April</xhtml:h3>
<xhtml:p>At the beginning of the month, our landlord threw us for a loop
and announced he was going to sell our apartment... meaning that we
either had to step up our plans to purchase a home, or start
looking for a new rental. Ultimately, we ended up looking for a
rental, due to time constraints. The next two months would be
highlighted with the look for a new place as well as countless
showings of our apartment to potential buyers.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Mid-month, we packed up the family and flew down to Atlanta, GA,
to visit my wife's family. While there, we were able to go to the
Atlanta Zoo and see Mei Lan, their baby panda -- way cute!</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:h3>May</xhtml:h3>
<xhtml:p>Mid-month, we found a new place in Richmond, VT -- a small
village about 10 minutes from Burlington, near where we originally
lived when we first moved to Vermont.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>During the first RC for Zend Framework, released at the end of
the month, I introduced the ViewRenderer, a feature for
auto-rendering views based on the current controller and action
name -- a feature common to many frameworks. However, it ostensibly
broke a ton of existing applications by being enabled by default --
not one of my more popular decisions. Since the 1.0.0 release, I've
heard little grumbling about it, and it's now often cited as an
ease-of-use feature -- go figure.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:h3>June</xhtml:h3>
<xhtml:p>The first week of June, I flew to Tel Aviv, Israel, to start
training people on the new CMS, as well as to work with our entire
ebiz team to finalize the work plan for completing the CMS. It was,
needless to say, my first time to Israel or the Middle East, and I
was constantly confronted with culture shock. Europe was an easy
transition to make, but Israel was completely foreign to me --
everything from the way people drove, to the architecture, to the
food was different. Unfortunately, I arrived a day late due to a
flight cancellation, and missed the tour of Jerusalem my supervisor
had planned for all of us. However, he took me to the city of Yafa,
an Arabic city where the Israeli's originally tried to settle
before building Tel Aviv to the north. The architecture was
amazing, as were the winding, narrow streets of the old city.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>I was also told during this trip that Andi had requested
transferring me full-time to the Zend Framework team. I would spend
the next week or two weighing my options, and ultimately decided to
do so.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>A week after I returned, we moved into our new rental in
Richmond. The kids love the new place, which has a bedroom for each
of them, a yard, and porches on each entrance.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Somehow, I also found time to record my first (and so far only)
<xhtml:a href="http://devzone.zend.com/article/2140-PHP-Abstract-Podcast-Episode-2---Backup-or-Die">
PHP Abstract podcast</xhtml:a>.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:h3>July</xhtml:h3>
<xhtml:p>We released <xhtml:a href="http://framework.zend.com/">Zend
Framework</xhtml:a> 1.0.0 at the beginning of the month, marking our
first stable release. While many still view it as incomplete, the
overwhelming feedback has been positive, and we've had over 2
million downloads to date.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>I accepted the transfer to the Zend Framework team, but the
condition was made that I would stay part-time on the ebiz team
until the new site was launched. This meant that the next 5 months
were spent splitting my time between the two projects, often
working late and on weekends to get work done.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Towards the end of the month, we took a long weekend camping in
Vermont's Northeast Kingdom. The weather was unseasonably wet, but
we persevered and had a great time. 5 days of offline time was
definitely needed!</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>I also finally released the first stable version of <xhtml:a href="http://pear.php.net/packages/File_Fortune">File_Fortune</xhtml:a> on
<xhtml:a href="http://pear.php.net/">PEAR</xhtml:a>, over a year since I'd
first proposed it. The package interfaces with mod_fortune files,
allowing both the ability to read and write such files, with full
binary compatability.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:h3>August</xhtml:h3>
<xhtml:p>Not much to report in August, except work, work, and more
work.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:h3>September</xhtml:h3>
<xhtml:p>My ebiz supervisor, Boaz, flew me to Tel Aviv for a second time,
this time to perform a "brain dump" for the rest of the team before
I transitioned fully out of the team, and also to help setup our
new data center and release procedures. This time, Boaz took me to
Jerusalem himself during my last full day in the country. If you've
never been to the city, you should definitely put it on your list
of things to do before you die. With my degree in religion, the
place was full of meaning for me, but it would be putting it
lightly to say that religion is palpable in the air there. We
visited the Wailing Wall, the Via Dolorosa, the Church of the Holy
Sepulchre, and listened to the muezzins sing the call to prayer for
the muslims. The tour was simply amazing.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>A few days after I returned, I flew down to New York City for a
special meeting of <xhtml:a href="http://nyphp.org/">NYPHP</xhtml:a>, where
<xhtml:a href="http://blogs.zend.com/author/mark/">Mark de Visser</xhtml:a>
presented on various Zend products and initiatives, and I gave a
Zend Framework overview.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>A week after the NYPHP presentation, I did a <xhtml:a href="http://www.zend.com/webinars">zend.com webinar</xhtml:a> on the Zend
Framework MVC layer.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:h3>October</xhtml:h3>
<xhtml:p>October was the month of <xhtml:a href="http://www.zendcon.con/">ZendCon</xhtml:a>. I presented a full-day
tutorial on best practices and unit testing with <xhtml:a href="http://sebastian-bergmann.de/">Sebastian Bergmann</xhtml:a> and <xhtml:a href="http://naberezny.com/">Mike Naberezny</xhtml:a>; despite the length and
subject matter, we were SRO for most of the day.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>I also did a main-stage presentation on Zend Framework's MVC
components, directly following <xhtml:a href="http://terrychay.com/blog/">Terry Chay</xhtml:a> -- an intimidating
situation at best. From the feedback I've seen, the presentation
was well-received, and I had somewhere between 120 and 150
attendees -- phenomenal! (Even more amazing was how many people
were familiar with MVC in general!)</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>One great thing about the conference was the fact that I got to
network with a number of framework developers, both Zend Framework
and otherwise, including Nate Abele of CakePHP as well as <xhtml:a href="http://paul-m-jones.com">Paul M. Jones</xhtml:a> of <xhtml:a href="http://solarphp.com">the Solar framework</xhtml:a>. Many good
conversations were had.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Late in the month, <xhtml:a href="http://sitepoint.com/books/phpant2/">The PHP Anthology, 2nd
Edition</xhtml:a>, my first published book as an author, was finally
released!</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:h3>November</xhtml:h3>
<xhtml:p>I spent much of the month working on <xhtml:a href="http://framework.zend.com/wiki/display/ZFPROP/Zend_Layout">Zend_Layout</xhtml:a>,
a much requested component that simplifies and automates Two Step
Views in Zend Framework. I also started work implementing <xhtml:a href="http://framework.zend.com/wiki/pages/viewpage.action?pageId=33071">
Zend_View Enhanced</xhtml:a>, a set of view helpers for making complex
views with Zend_View possible.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>I also started playing with <xhtml:a href="http://twitter.com/">Twitter</xhtml:a> a bit, and came up with a
<xhtml:a href="http://framework.zend.com/wiki/display/ZFPROP/Zend_Service_Twitter">
Zend_Service_Twitter</xhtml:a> proposal for interacting with the Twitter
API via PHP.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>And finally, the Sunday before Thanksgiving, we finally launched
the new <xhtml:a href="http://www.zend.com/">Zend.com</xhtml:a> site, which was
well-received in the blogosphere.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:h3>December</xhtml:h3>
<xhtml:p>A goal I've had for some time has been to form a PHP user group
in the Burlington area. A friend of mine pointed out to me sometime
this fall that there's actually already <xhtml:a href="http://groups.google.com/group/Burlington-VT-PHP">a Google
Group</xhtml:a> formed; he and the original founder started planning a
meeting for early December. I spoke at this inaugural meeting,
presenting Zend Framework's MVC layer yet again; a good time was
had by all, and a lot of enthusiasm for future meetings was
generated.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>I finished up Zend_Layout and Zend_View Enhanced with the help
of Ralph Schindler, and got a new proposal up for <xhtml:a href="http://framework.zend.com/wiki/display/ZFPROP/Zend_Form">Zend_Form</xhtml:a>,
just in time for my holidays to begin -- 11 days with family and
with little to no internet connectivity during a trip to Atlanta,
GA for one of only a handful of Christmases I've spent without
snow.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:h2>Summary</xhtml:h2>
<xhtml:p>This year was <xhtml:em>incredibly</xhtml:em> busy -- three cross-seas
trips, one cross-continent trip, a move, and several trips along
the Eastern Seaboard; three user group presentations, and eight
presentations over the course of the year; one conference; one
move; one PEAR release; one podcast; one webinar; one book; and
countless hours of programming.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>My goals for the coming year? I'm too tired to even think about
it ;-).</xhtml:p>
</xhtml:div>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[svn:externals]]></title>
    <published>2007-01-05T14:58:00+0000</published>
    <updated>2007-01-10T19:08:35+0000</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mwop.net/blog/132-svnexternals.html"/>
    <id>http://mwop.net/blog/132-svnexternals.html</id>
    <author>
      <name>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</name>
      <email>me@mwop.net</email>
      <uri>http://mwop.net</uri>
    </author>
    <content xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" type="xhtml">
      <xhtml:div xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><xhtml:p>I was recently working with someone who was using Zend Framework
in their project. To keep things stable and releasable, he was
doing an export of framework into his repository and checking it
in. Since files change so much in the ZF project currently, instead
of doing an rsync from a checkout into his own repository, he
decided instead to delete the directory from the repository and
re-add it everytime he was updating framework.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>This seemed really inefficient to me, especially considering
that it made it incredibly difficult to merge changes from his
development branch into his production branch (deleting and
re-adding directories breaks the merge process considerably). I
knew there had to be a better way.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>I'd heard of the svn:externals property before, but never really
played with it. As it turns out, it exists for just this very type
of situation. The problem is that the <xhtml:a href="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/nightly/en/svn-book.html#svn.advanced.externals">
documentation of svn:externals</xhtml:a> in the SVN book doesn't indicate
at all how the property should be set, and most howto's I've read
omit one or more very important details. I finally figured things
out through some trial and error of my own, so I'm going to share
the process so others hopefully can learn from the experience as
well.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>It's actually pretty easy. This assumes that your project layout
looks something like this:</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:pre>
project/
    branch/
        production/
    tag/
    trunk/
</xhtml:pre>
<xhtml:ul>
<xhtml:li>In the top of your project trunk, execute the following:
<xhtml:pre>
svn propedit svn:externals .
</xhtml:pre></xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>This will open an editor session. In the file opened by your
editor, each line indicates a different external svn repo to pull.
The first segment of the line is the directory where you want the
pull to exist. The last segment is the svn repo URL to pull. You
can have an optional middle argument indicating the revision to
use. Some examples:
<xhtml:ul>
<xhtml:li>Pull framework repo from head:
<xhtml:pre>
framework http://framework.zend.com/svn/framework/trunk
</xhtml:pre></xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>Pull framework repo from revision 2616:
<xhtml:pre>
framework -r2616 http://framework.zend.com/svn/framework/trunk
</xhtml:pre></xhtml:li>
</xhtml:ul>
</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>After saving and exiting, update the repo:
<xhtml:pre>
svn up
</xhtml:pre></xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>Commit changes:
<xhtml:pre>
svn commit
</xhtml:pre></xhtml:li>
</xhtml:ul>
<xhtml:p>One thing to note: any directory you specify for an
svn:externals checkout should <xhtml:b>not</xhtml:b> already exist in your
repository. If it does, you will get an error like the
following:</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:pre>
svn: Working copy 'sharedproject' locked
svn: run 'svn cleanup' to remove locks
</xhtml:pre>
<xhtml:p>I show using revisions above; you could also pin to tags by
simply checkout the external repository from a given tag. Either
way works well.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Then, when moving from one branch to another, or from the trunk
to a branch, you simply set a different svn:externals for each
branch. For instance, your current production might check from one
particular revision, but your trunk might simply track head; you
then simply determine what the current revision being used is on
your trunk, and update svn:externals in your production branch when
you're ready to push changes in.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Hope this helps some of you out there!</xhtml:p>
</xhtml:div>
    </content>
  </entry>
</feed>
