<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title type="text">Tag: programming :: phly, boy, phly</title>
  <updated>2009-01-05T01:00:49-06:00</updated>
  <generator uri="http://framework.zend.com" version="2.0.0beta3">Zend_Feed_Writer</generator>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mwop.net/blog/tag/programming.html"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://mwop.net/blog/tag/programming-atom.xml"/>
  <id>http://mwop.net/blog/tag/programming.html</id>
  <entry xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2008: The year in review]]></title>
    <published>2008-12-31T13:17:03-06:00</published>
    <updated>2009-01-05T01:00:49-06:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mwop.net/blog/203-2008-The-year-in-review.html"/>
    <id>http://mwop.net/blog/203-2008-The-year-in-review.html</id>
    <author>
      <name>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</name>
      <email>me@mwop.net</email>
      <uri>http://mwop.net</uri>
    </author>
    <content xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" type="xhtml">
      <xhtml:div xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><xhtml:p>That time of year again -- wrap-up time. Each year, it seems
like it's the busiest ever, and I often wonder if it will ever slow
down. As usual, I'm restricting myself to primarily professional
activities out of respect for the privacy of my family.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>The short, executive summary:</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:ul>
<xhtml:li>One trip to Israel</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>One trip to The Netherlands</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>One trip to California's Bay Area</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>One trip to Atlanta, GA</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>Three minor releases of Zend Framework</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>Seven webinars, six for zend.com and one for Adobe</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>Three conferences attended as a speaker, including:
<xhtml:ul>
<xhtml:li>One six-hour workshop</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>One three-hour tutorial (as a co-presenter)</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>Four regular sessions</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>Two panel sessions (one scheduled, one for an uncon)</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>Two uncon sessions (one as a co-presenter)</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>One foul-mouthed Pecha Kucha talk</xhtml:li>
</xhtml:ul>
</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>Ten Burlington, VT PHP User's Group meetings attended; I spoke
at many</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>One Bug Hunt week organized</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>Two books reviewed as a technical editor</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>Six articles for <xhtml:a href="http://devzone.zend.com/">DevZone</xhtml:a></xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>50 blog entries (including this one)</xhtml:li>
</xhtml:ul>
<xhtml:p>Read on for the gruesome, month-by-month breakdown.</xhtml:p>
</xhtml:div>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mumbles irssi integration]]></title>
    <published>2008-12-10T14:01:50-06:00</published>
    <updated>2008-12-12T14:19:50-06:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mwop.net/blog/197-Mumbles-irssi-integration.html"/>
    <id>http://mwop.net/blog/197-Mumbles-irssi-integration.html</id>
    <author>
      <name>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</name>
      <email>me@mwop.net</email>
      <uri>http://mwop.net</uri>
    </author>
    <content xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" type="xhtml">
      <xhtml:div xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><xhtml:p>I've been using IRC regularly for the past six to nine months,
in large part due to the growing ZF community on the <xhtml:a href="http://freenode.net/">Freenode</xhtml:a> #zftalk channel (unfortunately,
I simply don't have time to be in that particular channel any more,
but you can generally find me in #zftalk.dev), but also to keep in
contact with other peers, friends, and colleagues.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>One difficulty, however, is keeping productivity high while
staying on IRC. To me, the ultimate client would provide me
notifications when somebody mentions my name or a watch word -
allowing me to read the channel at my leisure, yet still respond to
people in a timely fashion.</xhtml:p>
</xhtml:div>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Vimgrep and Vim Project]]></title>
    <published>2008-10-21T06:36:49-05:00</published>
    <updated>2008-10-22T20:55:03-05:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mwop.net/blog/194-Vimgrep-and-Vim-Project.html"/>
    <id>http://mwop.net/blog/194-Vimgrep-and-Vim-Project.html</id>
    <author>
      <name>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</name>
      <email>me@mwop.net</email>
      <uri>http://mwop.net</uri>
    </author>
    <content xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" type="xhtml">
      <xhtml:div xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><xhtml:p>Chris Hartjes today was <xhtml:a href="http://www.littlehart.net/atthekeyboard/2008/10/20/vim-programming-bounty-fuzzyfind-inside-files/">
on a quest for a "find in project" feature for Vim</xhtml:a>. "Find in
Project" was a feature of Textmate that he'd grown accustomed to
and was having trouble finding an equivalent for.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>The funny thing is that Textmate is a newcomer, and, of course,
vim has had such a feature for years. The thing to remember with
vim, of course, is its unix roots; typically if you know the unix
command for doing something, you can find what you need in vim. In
this case, the key is the vimgrep plugin, which ships in the
standard vim distribution.</xhtml:p>
</xhtml:div>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[git-svn Tip: don't use core.autocrlf]]></title>
    <published>2008-09-24T11:16:27-05:00</published>
    <updated>2008-09-24T11:16:27-05:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mwop.net/blog/191-git-svn-Tip-dont-use-core.autocrlf.html"/>
    <id>http://mwop.net/blog/191-git-svn-Tip-dont-use-core.autocrlf.html</id>
    <author>
      <name>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</name>
      <email>me@mwop.net</email>
      <uri>http://mwop.net</uri>
    </author>
    <content xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" type="xhtml">
      <xhtml:div xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><xhtml:p>I've been playing around with <xhtml:a href="http://git.or.cz/">Git</xhtml:a> in the past couple months, and have
been really enjoying it. Paired with subversion, I get the best of
all worlds -- distributed source control when I want it (working on
new features or trying out performance tuning), and non-distributed
source control for my public commits.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p><xhtml:a href="http://github.com/guides/dealing-with-newlines-in-git">Github</xhtml:a>
suggests that when working with remote repositories, you turn on
the autocrlf option, which ensures that changes in line endings do
not get accounted for when pushing to and pulling from the remote
repo. However, when working with git-svn, this actually causes
issues. After turning this option on, I started getting the error
"Delta source ended unexpectedly" from git-svn. After a bunch of
aimless tinkering, I finally asked myself the questions, "When did
this start happening?" and, "Have I changed anything with Git
lately?" Once I'd backed out the config change, all started working
again.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>In summary: don't use "git config --global core.autocrlf true"
when using git-svn.</xhtml:p>
</xhtml:div>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Server Upgrades... lost entries...]]></title>
    <published>2008-05-16T08:05:13-05:00</published>
    <updated>2008-05-21T13:35:27-05:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mwop.net/blog/171-Server-Upgrades...-lost-entries....html"/>
    <id>http://mwop.net/blog/171-Server-Upgrades...-lost-entries....html</id>
    <author>
      <name>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</name>
      <email>me@mwop.net</email>
      <uri>http://mwop.net</uri>
    </author>
    <content xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" type="xhtml">
      <xhtml:div xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><xhtml:p>My good friend, Rob, hosts my site for me, in return for helping
with server maintenance. After being on Gentoo for the past three
years, though, we decided it was time to switch to something a
little easier to maintain, so last night we wiped the system
partitions and installed Ubuntu server.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>I'll say this: the setup is much faster! However, we had a few
gotchas that surprised us -- it didn't setup our RAID array
out-of-the-box, which led to a good hour of frustration as we tried
to verify that the install wouldn't wipe it, and then to verify
that we could re-assemble it. (We succeeded.) Additionally, we
second-guessed a few things we shouldn't have, which led to needing
to back out and reconfigure. But what was over a 12 hour install
with Gentoo we accomplished in a matter of a few hours with Ubuntu
server -- so it was a huge success that way.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Unfortunately, our mysqldump of all databases... wasn't, a fact
we discovered only after importing it into the new system. I ended
up losing my blog database and PEAR channel database. Fortunately,
the PEAR channel has not changed at all in the past year, so we had
an old backup that worked, and I had a snapshot of my blog database
from three weeks ago I was able to use. As a result, there are a
few missing entries, but for the most part, all works. If you
commented on one of those missing entries, my apologies.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Now that the install is done, I'm also finalizing some design
changes to my blog -- it's time to leave the black and white for
more colorful grounds. Look for a revamp in the coming weeks!</xhtml:p>
</xhtml:div>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Submitting Bug Reports]]></title>
    <published>2008-03-08T11:06:13-06:00</published>
    <updated>2008-03-09T09:18:36-05:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mwop.net/blog/161-Submitting-Bug-Reports.html"/>
    <id>http://mwop.net/blog/161-Submitting-Bug-Reports.html</id>
    <author>
      <name>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</name>
      <email>me@mwop.net</email>
      <uri>http://mwop.net</uri>
    </author>
    <content xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" type="xhtml">
      <xhtml:div xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><xhtml:p>Full disclosure: I am employed by <xhtml:a href="http://www.zend.com/">Zend</xhtml:a> to program <xhtml:a href="http://framework.zend.com/">Zend Framework</xhtml:a>. That said, the
following is all my opinion, and is based on my experiences with
Zend Framework, as well as answering questions on a variety of
mailing lists and with other OSS projects (PEAR, Solar, and Cgiapp
in particular).</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>One of my biggest pet peeves in the OSS world is vague bug/issue
reports and feature requests. I cannot count the number of times
I've seen a report similar to the following:</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:blockquote>&lt;Feature X&gt; doesn't work; you need to fix it
<xhtml:b>now!</xhtml:b></xhtml:blockquote>
<xhtml:p>If such a report comes in on an issue tracker, it's invariably
marked critical and high priority.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>What bothers me about it? Simply this: it gives those
responsible for maintaining Feature X absolutely no information to
work on: what result they received, what was expected, or how
exactly they were using the feature. The reviewer now has to go
into one or more cycles with the reporter fishing for that
information -- wasting everyone's time and energy.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Only slightly better are these reports:</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:blockquote>&lt;Feature X&gt; doesn't work -- I keep getting
&lt;Result X&gt; from it, which is incorrect.</xhtml:blockquote>
<xhtml:p>At least this tells the reviewers what they reporter is
receiving... but it doesn't tell them how they got there, or what
they're expecting.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>So, the following should be your mantra when reporting issues or
making feature requests:</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:ul>
<xhtml:li>What is the minimum code necessary to reproduce the issue or
show the desired API?</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>What is the expected result?</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>What is the actual result?</xhtml:li>
</xhtml:ul>
</xhtml:div>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Backwards Compatibility]]></title>
    <published>2008-02-07T08:56:11-06:00</published>
    <updated>2008-02-07T08:56:11-06:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mwop.net/blog/158-Backwards-Compatibility.html"/>
    <id>http://mwop.net/blog/158-Backwards-Compatibility.html</id>
    <author>
      <name>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</name>
      <email>me@mwop.net</email>
      <uri>http://mwop.net</uri>
    </author>
    <content xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" type="xhtml">
      <xhtml:div xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><xhtml:p><xhtml:a href="http://jansch.nl/">Ivo</xhtml:a> already pointed this out,
but I want to point it out again: Boy Baukema writes <xhtml:a href="http://www.ibuildings.nl/blog/archives/541-Backward-compatibility,-bane-of-the-developer.html">
a very nice entry regarding backwards compatibility</xhtml:a> on the
ibuildings.nl corporate blog.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Backwards compatibility (BC) is a tricky thing to support, even
when you strive hard to, as Boy puts it, "think hard about your
API" prior to release. Somebody will always come along and point
out ways it could have been done better or ways it could be
improved. I've had to wrestle with these issues a ton since joining
the Zend Framework team, and while it often feels like the wrong
thing to do to tell somebody, "too little, too late" when they have
genuinely good feedback for you, its often in the best interest of
the many users already using a component.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>I had the pleasure of meeting Boy last year when visiting the
ibuildings.nl offices, and he's got a good head on his shoulders.
He does a nice job outlining the issues and a number of approaches
to BC; if you develop a project for public consumption, you should
definitely head over and read what he has to say.</xhtml:p>
</xhtml:div>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Apache HOSTNAME on Clusters]]></title>
    <published>2008-01-25T16:38:16-06:00</published>
    <updated>2008-01-26T07:22:44-06:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mwop.net/blog/156-Apache-HOSTNAME-on-Clusters.html"/>
    <id>http://mwop.net/blog/156-Apache-HOSTNAME-on-Clusters.html</id>
    <author>
      <name>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</name>
      <email>me@mwop.net</email>
      <uri>http://mwop.net</uri>
    </author>
    <content xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" type="xhtml">
      <xhtml:div xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><xhtml:p>In an effort to debug issues on a cluster, I was trying to
determine which machine on the cluster was causing the issue. My
idea was that I could insert a header token identifying the
server.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>My first idea was to add the directive 'Header add X-Server-Ip
"%{SERVER_ADDR}e" in my httpd.conf. However, due to the nature of
our load balancer, Apache was somehow resolving this to the load
balancer IP address on all machines of the cluster -- which was
really, really not useful.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>I finally stumbled on a good solution, however: you can set
environment variables in apachectl, and then pass them into the
Apache environment using the PassEnv directive from mod_env; once
that's done, you can use the environment variable anywhere.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>In my apachectl, I added the line "export HOSTNAME=`hostname`".
Then, in my httpd.conf, I added first the line "PassEnv HOSTNAME",
followed by the directive 'Header add X-Server-Name
"%{HOSTNAME}e"'. Voila! I now had the hostname in the header, which
gave me the information I needed for debugging.</xhtml:p>
</xhtml:div>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2007 Retrospective]]></title>
    <published>2008-01-01T15:49:26-06:00</published>
    <updated>2008-01-03T05:22:35-06:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mwop.net/blog/154-2007-Retrospective.html"/>
    <id>http://mwop.net/blog/154-2007-Retrospective.html</id>
    <author>
      <name>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</name>
      <email>me@mwop.net</email>
      <uri>http://mwop.net</uri>
    </author>
    <content xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" type="xhtml">
      <xhtml:div xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><xhtml:p>2007 was a busy year, both personally and professionally. I
won't go into the personal too much, because, well, it's personal,
and some of the details are simply inappropriate for blogging
material.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Here's the short version:</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:ul>
<xhtml:li>One trip to Belgium and The Netherlands.</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>Two trips to Israel.</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>Two trips to Atlanta, GA (not counting the return trip from
Europe, when I was stranded for a day due to storms in the
Northeast).</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>Three different user groups attended, with three
presentations.</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>One major Zend Framework release</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>One PEAR release.</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>One podcast.</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>One webinar.</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>One book published.</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>One conference attended.</xhtml:li>
</xhtml:ul>
<xhtml:p>What follows is my month-by-month breakdown:</xhtml:p>
</xhtml:div>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[svn:externals]]></title>
    <published>2007-01-05T08:58:00-06:00</published>
    <updated>2007-01-10T13:08:35-06:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mwop.net/blog/132-svnexternals.html"/>
    <id>http://mwop.net/blog/132-svnexternals.html</id>
    <author>
      <name>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</name>
      <email>me@mwop.net</email>
      <uri>http://mwop.net</uri>
    </author>
    <content xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" type="xhtml">
      <xhtml:div xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><xhtml:p>I was recently working with someone who was using Zend Framework
in their project. To keep things stable and releasable, he was
doing an export of framework into his repository and checking it
in. Since files change so much in the ZF project currently, instead
of doing an rsync from a checkout into his own repository, he
decided instead to delete the directory from the repository and
re-add it everytime he was updating framework.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>This seemed really inefficient to me, especially considering
that it made it incredibly difficult to merge changes from his
development branch into his production branch (deleting and
re-adding directories breaks the merge process considerably). I
knew there had to be a better way.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>I'd heard of the svn:externals property before, but never really
played with it. As it turns out, it exists for just this very type
of situation. The problem is that the <xhtml:a href="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/nightly/en/svn-book.html#svn.advanced.externals">
documentation of svn:externals</xhtml:a> in the SVN book doesn't indicate
at all how the property should be set, and most howto's I've read
omit one or more very important details. I finally figured things
out through some trial and error of my own, so I'm going to share
the process so others hopefully can learn from the experience as
well.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>It's actually pretty easy. This assumes that your project layout
looks something like this:</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:pre>
project/
    branch/
        production/
    tag/
    trunk/
</xhtml:pre>
<xhtml:ul>
<xhtml:li>In the top of your project trunk, execute the following:
<xhtml:pre>
svn propedit svn:externals .
</xhtml:pre></xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>This will open an editor session. In the file opened by your
editor, each line indicates a different external svn repo to pull.
The first segment of the line is the directory where you want the
pull to exist. The last segment is the svn repo URL to pull. You
can have an optional middle argument indicating the revision to
use. Some examples:
<xhtml:ul>
<xhtml:li>Pull framework repo from head:
<xhtml:pre>
framework http://framework.zend.com/svn/framework/trunk
</xhtml:pre></xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>Pull framework repo from revision 2616:
<xhtml:pre>
framework -r2616 http://framework.zend.com/svn/framework/trunk
</xhtml:pre></xhtml:li>
</xhtml:ul>
</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>After saving and exiting, update the repo:
<xhtml:pre>
svn up
</xhtml:pre></xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>Commit changes:
<xhtml:pre>
svn commit
</xhtml:pre></xhtml:li>
</xhtml:ul>
<xhtml:p>One thing to note: any directory you specify for an
svn:externals checkout should <xhtml:b>not</xhtml:b> already exist in your
repository. If it does, you will get an error like the
following:</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:pre>
svn: Working copy 'sharedproject' locked
svn: run 'svn cleanup' to remove locks
</xhtml:pre>
<xhtml:p>I show using revisions above; you could also pin to tags by
simply checkout the external repository from a given tag. Either
way works well.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Then, when moving from one branch to another, or from the trunk
to a branch, you simply set a different svn:externals for each
branch. For instance, your current production might check from one
particular revision, but your trunk might simply track head; you
then simply determine what the current revision being used is on
your trunk, and update svn:externals in your production branch when
you're ready to push changes in.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Hope this helps some of you out there!</xhtml:p>
</xhtml:div>
    </content>
  </entry>
</feed>
