<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/">
  <channel>
    <title>Tag: tek09 :: phly, boy, phly</title>
    <description>Tag: tek09 :: phly, boy, phly</description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 13 May 2009 15:33:45 +0000</pubDate>
    <generator>Zend_Feed_Writer 2.1.1dev (http://framework.zend.com)</generator>
    <link>http://mwop.net/blog/tag/tek09.html</link>
    <atom:link rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" href="http://mwop.net/blog/tag/tek09-rss.xml"/>
    <item>
      <title>Speaking at php|tek</title>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 May 2009 15:33:45 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/219-Speaking-at-phptek.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/219-Speaking-at-phptek.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    I announced this earlier in the year, but for those that missed it, I'm
    speaking at <a href="http://tek.mtacon.com/">php|tek</a> next week.
</p>

<p style="text-align: center">
    <img src="/uploads/tek_09_badge_speaker.gif" 
        alt="Speaking at php|tek 2009" />
</p>

<p>
    I'll be co-presenting a workshop entitled <a
        href="http://tek.mtacon.com/c/schedule/talk/ts2/0">Practical SVN for PHP
        Developers</a> along with the lovely and talented 
    <a href="http://www.lornajane.net/">Lorna Jane Mitchell</a>. In a way, it's
    a continuation of the unconference session we did together at ZendCon08, and
    will provide much more in-depth information on the subject -- including how
    to create and organize your repositories, branching and tagging strategies,
    how and when to commit, as well as more basic usage of subversion for
    day-to-day use.
</p><p>
    I've also proposed two unconference sessions:
</p>

<ul>
    <li><a href="http://joind.in/talk/view/437">Using Git to take SVN
        offline</a> continues the version control theme. In it, I plan to
    demonstrate and discuss <kbd>git+svn</kbd>, a set of tools I use daily to
    allow me the benefits of a distributed versioning system backed by a
    non-distributed, canonical system.</li>

    <li><a href="http://joind.in/talk/view/436">Play-dough: How to Model Your
        PHP Objects</a> is a continuation of a series of blog posts I did
    earlier this year on creating models for your MVC systems. I plan to look at
    some common design patterns, including Service Layers, Domain Models, Data
    Mappers, Transaction Scripts, ActiveRecord, and Table and Row Data Gateways
    -- and where and when each may make sense in your application.</li>
</ul>

<p>
    If you're interested in either of the above two topics, follow the links and
    vote. Or, if you just want to see me run around like a chicken with its head
    cut off for two days as I scramble to put materials together, that works as
    well.
</p>

<p>
    If you're going to php|tek next week, please look me up. And if you're not,
    it's not too late <a href="http://tek.mtacon.com/c/signup">to register</a>!
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
