<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/">
  <channel>
    <title>Tag: ubuntu :: phly, boy, phly</title>
    <description>Tag: ubuntu :: phly, boy, phly</description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2008 18:35:27 +0000</pubDate>
    <generator>Zend_Feed_Writer 2.1.1dev (http://framework.zend.com)</generator>
    <link>http://mwop.net/blog/tag/ubuntu.html</link>
    <atom:link rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" href="http://mwop.net/blog/tag/ubuntu-rss.xml"/>
    <item>
      <title>Server Upgrades... lost entries...</title>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2008 18:35:27 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/171-Server-Upgrades...-lost-entries....html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/171-Server-Upgrades...-lost-entries....html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    My good friend, Rob, hosts my site for me, in return for helping with server
    maintenance. After being on Gentoo for the past three years, though, we
    decided it was time to switch to something a little easier to maintain, so
    last night we wiped the system partitions and installed Ubuntu server.
</p>

<p>
    I'll say this: the setup is much faster! However, we had a few gotchas that
    surprised us -- it didn't setup our RAID array out-of-the-box, which led to
    a good hour of frustration as we tried to verify that the install wouldn't
    wipe it, and then to verify that we could re-assemble it.  (We succeeded.)
    Additionally, we second-guessed a few things we shouldn't have, which led to
    needing to back out and reconfigure. But what was over a 12 hour install
    with Gentoo we accomplished in a matter of a few hours with Ubuntu server --
    so it was a huge success that way.
</p>

<p>
    Unfortunately, our mysqldump of all databases... wasn't, a fact we
    discovered only after importing it into the new system. I ended up losing my
    blog database and PEAR channel database. Fortunately, the PEAR channel
    has not changed at all in the past year, so we had an old backup that
    worked, and I had a snapshot of my blog database from three weeks ago I was
    able to use. As a result, there are a few missing entries, but for the most
    part, all works. If you commented on one of those missing entries, my
    apologies.
</p>

<p>
    Now that the install is done, I'm also finalizing some design changes to my
    blog -- it's time to leave the black and white for more colorful grounds.
    Look for a revamp in the coming weeks!
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gutsy Gibbon review</title>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Oct 2007 20:38:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/147-Gutsy-Gibbon-review.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/147-Gutsy-Gibbon-review.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    Early in the week, I decided to avoid the release rush and go ahead and
    update my laptop to <a href="http://www.ubuntu.com">Ubuntu's</a> Gutsy 
    Gibbon release. Overall, it's quite good, with one caveat I'll elaborate on
    later. 
</p><p>
    I'd been having some issues with fonts following a session at ZendCon where
    I hooked my laptop up to a widescreen display, and the updates fixed all
    those issues. Most things that worked before continued to work, and often in
    an improved way. The various new themes available -- from GDM to GTK to
    window manager themes -- make for some pretty displays, and I've found a new
    look for my desktop that I really like.
</p>

<p>
    Among the improvements, it installed 
    <a href="http://www.gnome.org/projects/tracker/">trackerd</a>, a desktop
    search tool. I'd tried installing this on my own before, but ran into a ton
    of dependency issues I couldn't fix. Prior to this, I'd used beagle, which
    worked okay, but tended to overlook a lot of files. Trackerd, on the other
    hand, indexed my entire box overnight, and stays on top of new files easily.
    Couple this with the 'deskbar', and I now have the type of desktop search
    I've only seen in Macs.
</p>

<p>
    Last night, I stumbled upon <a href="https://help.ubuntu.com/community/CompositeManager/Xgl#head-3138701daf76c1fd11c0b68bf5745c1d1ccacca5">a forum thread</a>
    detailing how to get X compositing working with ATI cards. This was
    something I've been continually disappointed with; my card supposedly
    supports it, but every time I've tried using it, I find it unusable -- lots
    of wierd screen artifacts, and a huge slowdown in responsiveness. After
    following the directions in the linked article, however, I now have
    compositing going -- window drop shadows, translucency for inactive windows,
    etc. It looks really nice, and doesn't seem to be slowing down the machine
    at all.
</p>

<p>
    No review would be complete without a gripe though, right? And I've got a
    big one. In the past, one of the strengths of ubuntu for me has been that
    suspend and hibernate have just worked. With this upgrade, however, they no
    longer work for me. Evidently, a new kernel option was enabled that is
    supposed to speed up these operations... However, the available ATI drivers
    do not support this option, which leads, in my case, to a complete inability
    to suspend or hibernate, and for others, lockup on resume. Supposedly ATI
    will be releasing new drivers that will fix the issue, but there's no
    published time frame for when that will happen. Additionally, ubuntu made no
    announcements about the issue, and provides no workarounds. To me, this is a
    huge BC break, and should have been addressed prior to the release,
    particularly as there were many, many complaints about it in the weeks prior
    to the release.
</p>

<p>
    Gripes aside, I find the new functionality fantastic, and look forward to
    ATI's release of new drivers for its Radeon series cards.  Perhaps this
    release will keep me happy enough that I won't keep lusting for a shiny new
    Macbook too much.
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
