<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title type="text">Tag: ubuntu :: phly, boy, phly</title>
  <updated>2008-05-21T13:35:27-05:00</updated>
  <generator uri="http://framework.zend.com" version="2.0.0beta4">Zend_Feed_Writer</generator>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mwop.net/blog/tag/ubuntu.html"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://mwop.net/blog/tag/ubuntu-atom.xml"/>
  <id>http://mwop.net/blog/tag/ubuntu.html</id>
  <entry xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Server Upgrades... lost entries...]]></title>
    <published>2008-05-16T08:05:13-05:00</published>
    <updated>2008-05-21T13:35:27-05:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mwop.net/blog/171-Server-Upgrades...-lost-entries....html"/>
    <id>http://mwop.net/blog/171-Server-Upgrades...-lost-entries....html</id>
    <author>
      <name>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</name>
      <email>me@mwop.net</email>
      <uri>http://mwop.net</uri>
    </author>
    <content xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" type="xhtml">
      <xhtml:div xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><xhtml:p>My good friend, Rob, hosts my site for me, in return for helping
with server maintenance. After being on Gentoo for the past three
years, though, we decided it was time to switch to something a
little easier to maintain, so last night we wiped the system
partitions and installed Ubuntu server.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>I'll say this: the setup is much faster! However, we had a few
gotchas that surprised us -- it didn't setup our RAID array
out-of-the-box, which led to a good hour of frustration as we tried
to verify that the install wouldn't wipe it, and then to verify
that we could re-assemble it. (We succeeded.) Additionally, we
second-guessed a few things we shouldn't have, which led to needing
to back out and reconfigure. But what was over a 12 hour install
with Gentoo we accomplished in a matter of a few hours with Ubuntu
server -- so it was a huge success that way.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Unfortunately, our mysqldump of all databases... wasn't, a fact
we discovered only after importing it into the new system. I ended
up losing my blog database and PEAR channel database. Fortunately,
the PEAR channel has not changed at all in the past year, so we had
an old backup that worked, and I had a snapshot of my blog database
from three weeks ago I was able to use. As a result, there are a
few missing entries, but for the most part, all works. If you
commented on one of those missing entries, my apologies.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Now that the install is done, I'm also finalizing some design
changes to my blog -- it's time to leave the black and white for
more colorful grounds. Look for a revamp in the coming weeks!</xhtml:p>
</xhtml:div>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Gutsy Gibbon review]]></title>
    <published>2007-10-20T06:55:00-05:00</published>
    <updated>2007-10-24T15:38:00-05:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mwop.net/blog/147-Gutsy-Gibbon-review.html"/>
    <id>http://mwop.net/blog/147-Gutsy-Gibbon-review.html</id>
    <author>
      <name>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</name>
      <email>me@mwop.net</email>
      <uri>http://mwop.net</uri>
    </author>
    <content xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" type="xhtml">
      <xhtml:div xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><xhtml:p>Early in the week, I decided to avoid the release rush and go
ahead and update my laptop to <xhtml:a href="http://www.ubuntu.com">Ubuntu's</xhtml:a> Gutsy Gibbon release. Overall,
it's quite good, with one caveat I'll elaborate on later.</xhtml:p>
</xhtml:div>
    </content>
  </entry>
</feed>
