<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/">
  <channel>
    <title>Tag: ubuntu :: phly, boy, phly</title>
    <description>Tag: ubuntu :: phly, boy, phly</description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2008 13:35:27 -0500</pubDate>
    <generator>Zend_Feed_Writer 2.0.0beta3 (http://framework.zend.com)</generator>
    <link>http://mwop.net/blog/tag/ubuntu.html</link>
    <atom:link rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" href="http://mwop.net/blog/tag/ubuntu-rss.xml"/>
    <item>
      <title>Server Upgrades... lost entries...</title>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2008 13:35:27 -0500</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/171-Server-Upgrades...-lost-entries....html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/171-Server-Upgrades...-lost-entries....html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    My good friend, Rob, hosts my site for me, in return for helping with server
    maintenance. After being on Gentoo for the past three years, though, we
    decided it was time to switch to something a little easier to maintain, so
    last night we wiped the system partitions and installed Ubuntu server.
</p>

<p>
    I'll say this: the setup is much faster! However, we had a few gotchas that
    surprised us -- it didn't setup our RAID array out-of-the-box, which led to
    a good hour of frustration as we tried to verify that the install wouldn't
    wipe it, and then to verify that we could re-assemble it.  (We succeeded.)
    Additionally, we second-guessed a few things we shouldn't have, which led to
    needing to back out and reconfigure. But what was over a 12 hour install
    with Gentoo we accomplished in a matter of a few hours with Ubuntu server --
    so it was a huge success that way.
</p>

<p>
    Unfortunately, our mysqldump of all databases... wasn't, a fact we
    discovered only after importing it into the new system. I ended up losing my
    blog database and PEAR channel database. Fortunately, the PEAR channel
    has not changed at all in the past year, so we had an old backup that
    worked, and I had a snapshot of my blog database from three weeks ago I was
    able to use. As a result, there are a few missing entries, but for the most
    part, all works. If you commented on one of those missing entries, my
    apologies.
</p>

<p>
    Now that the install is done, I'm also finalizing some design changes to my
    blog -- it's time to leave the black and white for more colorful grounds.
    Look for a revamp in the coming weeks!
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gutsy Gibbon review</title>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Oct 2007 15:38:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/147-Gutsy-Gibbon-review.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/147-Gutsy-Gibbon-review.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    Early in the week, I decided to avoid the release rush and go ahead and
    update my laptop to <a href="http://www.ubuntu.com">Ubuntu's</a> Gutsy 
    Gibbon release. Overall, it's quite good, with one caveat I'll elaborate on
    later. 
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
