<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title type="text">Tag: zencon08 :: phly, boy, phly</title>
  <updated>2008-09-27T16:06:11+0000</updated>
  <generator uri="http://framework.zend.com" version="2.1.1dev">Zend_Feed_Writer</generator>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mwop.net/blog/tag/zencon08.html"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://mwop.net/blog/tag/zencon08-atom.xml"/>
  <id>http://mwop.net/blog/tag/zencon08.html</id>
  <entry xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ZendCon08 Wrapup]]></title>
    <published>2008-09-26T03:11:30+0000</published>
    <updated>2008-09-27T16:06:11+0000</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mwop.net/blog/192-ZendCon08-Wrapup.html"/>
    <id>http://mwop.net/blog/192-ZendCon08-Wrapup.html</id>
    <author>
      <name>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</name>
      <email>me@mwop.net</email>
      <uri>http://mwop.net</uri>
    </author>
    <content xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" type="xhtml">
      <xhtml:div xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><xhtml:p>I'm a bit late on my <xhtml:a href="http://www.zendcon.com/">ZendCon'08</xhtml:a> wrapup; the conference
left me both exhausted and with a backlog of email and work that
has consumed me since it ended. However, this, too, is good, as it
has given me time to reflect... and to finally get my slides up on
SlideShare.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>ZendCon was alternately exhausting, rewarding, educational,
fruitful, infurating, and ultimately wonderful. I've been to every
single ZendCon so far -- I started at Zend a scant month before the
inaugural event -- and have spoken at each. My first time speaking
was a fluke; <xhtml:a href="http://www.sklar.com/">David Sklar</xhtml:a> had
just started at <xhtml:a href="http://www.ning.com/">Ning</xhtml:a> and had to
back out of his "Configuring PHP" tutorial session. <xhtml:a href="http://mikenaberezny.com/">Mike Naberezny</xhtml:a> and I were drafted
to take it over, and we had N+1 attendees, where N was the number
of speakers. Since that inauspicious beginning, I've gradually
taken on more sessions and stuck around to participate in the
conference more. I can honestly say that this was the biggest,
busiest, and most community focussed ZendCon I can remember.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>This year, I was involved in a marathon seven -- yes, that's
right, seven -- sessions over three days, and only finally got the
last day off. <xhtml:a href="http://mikenaberezny.com/">Mike</xhtml:a> and I
did our <xhtml:a href="http://www.slideshare.net/weierophinney/best-practices-of-php-development-presentation/">
Best Practices tutorial session</xhtml:a> on Monday, which was very well
attended. Based on the numbers of people raising their hands as we
asked if they were implementing or familiar with the various
practices we enumerated, we may be able to begin doing more
advanced, in-depth sessions in the future.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>On Tuesday, <xhtml:a href="http://inside.e-novative.de/">Stefan
Priebsch</xhtml:a> <xhtml:strike>roped me into</xhtml:strike> convinced me to help
with a "round table" UnConference session on the role of ORMs in
PHP. The consensus we had was that ORM tools are quite good for
prototyping and rapid development, but that any good ORM solution
should de-couple the data access layer to allow stubbing with
well-tuned SQL when performance becomes a consideration.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Later that morning, I did a presentation on <xhtml:a href="http://www.slideshare.net/weierophinney/getting-started-with-zend-framework-presentation/">
Getting Started with Zend Framework</xhtml:a>. I developed this
presentation to follow our newly re-launched <xhtml:a href="http://framework.zend.com/docs/quickstart">Quick Start</xhtml:a>. The
talk was very well attended, and I received some excellent
questions from attendees following the talk. I hope to streamline
it in the future so it can be presented as a screencast or webinar.
If you are interested in the material, I suggest heading to the
link above and downloading the quick start materials; they are
well-documented and will cover at least as much as I covered in the
talk.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>In the afternoon, I did another unconference session, this time
performing my <xhtml:a href="http://www.slideshare.net/weierophinney/rich-uis-and-easy-remoting-with-dojo-and-zend-framework-presentation/">
Rich UIs and Easy XHR with Dojo and Zend Framework</xhtml:a> talk. (Did I
mention that conference attendees could not seem to get enough Zend
Framework material?) I really enjoyed doing this talk <xhtml:em>live</xhtml:em>
this time (I've done it previously for a webinar) -- I received
some wonderful questions, but even better, I was able to gauge the
audience reactions to what I was presenting. I was pleased to see
people getting as excited about Dojo as I've become, and I hope to
see that enthusiasm grow. Dojo is truly a fantastic choice when it
comes to javascript toolkits, and I think I suitably demonstrated
how easy it is to use Dojo now from Zend Framework.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Tuesday afternoon, I presented my session on <xhtml:a href="http://www.slideshare.net/weierophinney/zendform-presentation/">Zend_Form</xhtml:a>.
We'd originally planned to do a talk on Zend_Layout and Zend_Form,
but there's at least two hours of material there that simply does
not condense to 1 hour. Instead, we had Ralph present a session on
Zend_Layout during an UnConference session, while I focussed on
Zend_Form. Again, it was fun to do this in front of a live audience
-- albeit one I could barely see from my perch on the mainstage. I
saw some places to trim for next time -- which will allow me to
show off Zend_Dojo integration with Zend_Form in the future.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Immediately following that, I headed off to do yet another
UnConference session with <xhtml:a href="http://lornajane.net/">Lorna
Jane</xhtml:a>. <xhtml:a href="http://caseysoftware.com/blog">Keith Casey</xhtml:a>
had approached me on Monday following the tutorial Mike and I
presented, indicating that there were requests for an "svn tips and
tricks" presentation for the UnCon. I told him to ask Lorna Jane if
she'd be interested, as I'd seen her do an excellent presentation
on the subject at the Dutch PHP Conference in June. After some back
and forth, we decided to do it together, and sketched out a rough
outline early Wednesday morning. The talk was very well attended,
and again had great audience participation. Doing the presentation
has inspired us to consider submitting a joint proposal for a
conference in the future.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>I quickly ran downstairs, only to find I was immediately wanted
for a "Meet the Team" session. This has become a staple at ZendCon,
and has had led to some... interesting... interchanges in the past.
This year, the session was packed, and we had some very good
discussions touching on every Zend product -- from Zend Framework
to Zend Platform. There were certainly some hecklers, but all of it
was in good fun, and we had a brilliant time. (Man, I think hanging
with the UK folk has worn off on my vocabulary.)</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>I actually attended fewer sessions than I was involved in, which
was unusual and strange. Every one I was able to attend was quite
good. Standouts for me include Jay Pipes' tutorial on Join Foo,
which raised many questions for me and sparked a number of
discussion points all week. Additionally, I was delighted to be
able to attend Alex Russell's Dojo talk; I've exchanged dozens of
emails with him over the past months while doing the ZF/Dojo
integration, and it was fascinating to hear his summary of the
state of HTML and browser support, as well as how he feels Dojo
fits in the ecosystem. I was fortunate enough to be able to grab
him afterwards so we could have lunch and talk shop -- and got an
even larger surprise to discover he was not only familiar with all
aspects of the Dojo support I'd done, but had used much of it!</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Being as busy as I was, I didn't have much chance to stop and
enjoy the community until Wednesday evening. And the community is
quite vibrant! I have often been behind in my slide preparations or
tied up in meetings and unable to "join the fun" that often marks
good PHP events. This time, I felt quite tapped into the community,
as well as welcomed by all. I had innumerable conversations, both
with people wholly unfamiliar to me, people I've seen yearly at
ZendCon, and people I've been "seeing" virtually on IRC and the
mailing lists. The strength of any open source project is only as
good as the community it attracts, and on this basis alone, PHP is
thriving.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>So, goodbye, ZendCon08 and all my new and old friends -- let's
hope we can meet again next year!</xhtml:p>
</xhtml:div>
    </content>
  </entry>
</feed>
