<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title type="text">Tag: zendcon09 :: phly, boy, phly</title>
  <updated>2009-10-12T18:40:51+0000</updated>
  <generator uri="http://framework.zend.com" version="2.1.4dev">Zend_Feed_Writer</generator>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mwop.net/blog/tag/zendcon09.html"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://mwop.net/blog/tag/zendcon09-atom.xml"/>
  <id>http://mwop.net/blog/tag/zendcon09.html</id>
  <entry xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Speaking at ZendCon 2009]]></title>
    <published>2009-10-12T12:30:00+0000</published>
    <updated>2009-10-12T18:40:51+0000</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mwop.net/blog/226-Speaking-at-ZendCon-2009.html"/>
    <id>http://mwop.net/blog/226-Speaking-at-ZendCon-2009.html</id>
    <author>
      <name>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</name>
      <email>me@mwop.net</email>
      <uri>http://mwop.net</uri>
    </author>
    <content xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" type="xhtml">
      <xhtml:div xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><xhtml:p>It's probably already a foregone conclusion, but I'm speaking
once again at <xhtml:a href="http://zendcon.com/">ZendCon</xhtml:a> this year
-- one week from today!</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p style="text-align: center;"><xhtml:a href="http://zendcon.com/"><xhtml:img src="/uploads/zendcon09_speakerbutton.jpg"/></xhtml:a></xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>I'm delivering three different talks this year:</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:ul>
<xhtml:li><xhtml:a href="http://zendcon.com/tutorials#session-12095">Introduction to Zend
Framework</xhtml:a>. In this tutorial, I'll look at what ZF is, how to
get and install it, some common utilities and patterns used
throughout the project, and spend the bulk of the time on building,
hands-on, a simple application.</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li><xhtml:a href="http://zendcon.com/tutorials#session-11790">Architecting Ajax
Applications with Zend Framework</xhtml:a>. Another tutorial session,
this one will focus not so much on the client-side of an Ajax
application, but how to architect the server-side to respond
appropriately to Ajax (and other service) requests. We'll look at
RPC services, REST, HTTP codes and headers, and how to weave them
into a robust and simple backend for use with your dynamic, "Web
2.0" applications.</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li><xhtml:a href="http://zendcon.com/tracks?tid=1357#session-11787">Architecting
Your Models</xhtml:a>. This regular track session is all about the M in
MVC: models. Many MVC frameworks and approaches have you tie the
data access directly to your models; in this session, I'll show you
approaches and strategies for de-coupling data access from your
models, why you might want to do so, and some cool things you can
do once you have.</xhtml:li>
</xhtml:ul>
<xhtml:p>I'll also be involved in two panel sessions:</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:ul>
<xhtml:li><xhtml:strong>Meet the Zend Team</xhtml:strong> (Wednesday evening). This
has been a popular session in past years; project leads from each
of the product teams at Zend will be available in a panel to answer
your questions. Some years have been rather... entertaining.
:)</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li><xhtml:strong>Framework Shootout</xhtml:strong> (Thursday, closing
keynote). I'm especially excited about this session, in which we
get myself, representing Zend Framework; Fabien Potencier,
representing Symfony; David Zuilke, representing Agavi; Nate Abele,
representing CakePHP; and Edward Finkler, representing CodeIgniter.
Eli White will be moderating a Q&amp;A style session in which you,
the audience, get to ask us about our respective frameworks and
where we compare (or don't!) in various functional areas. I did a
similar panel to this at PHP Quebec this year, and it was a great
time.</xhtml:li>
</xhtml:ul>
<xhtml:p>There will be a ton of sessions, with people presenting on a
huge variety of subjects, from version control to RDMS systems,
from JavaScript to Flash, from development to production. In
addition, there will be a parallel <xhtml:a href="http://zendcon.com/uncon">UnCon</xhtml:a>, being run by <xhtml:a href="http://caseysoftware.com/blog/">Keith Casey</xhtml:a>, featuring even
more topics and interesting ideas.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>I look forward to seeing you at ZendCon this year!</xhtml:p>
</xhtml:div>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why UnCons are Important]]></title>
    <published>2009-10-07T12:55:05+0000</published>
    <updated>2009-10-07T14:53:07+0000</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mwop.net/blog/225-Why-UnCons-are-Important.html"/>
    <id>http://mwop.net/blog/225-Why-UnCons-are-Important.html</id>
    <author>
      <name>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</name>
      <email>me@mwop.net</email>
      <uri>http://mwop.net</uri>
    </author>
    <content xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" type="xhtml">
      <xhtml:div xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><xhtml:p>My good friend, <xhtml:a href="http://caseysoftware.com/blog/">Keith
Casey</xhtml:a>, is once again chairing <xhtml:a href="http://zendcon.com/">Zendcon's</xhtml:a> <xhtml:a href="http://joind.in/event/zendcon09-uncon">UnCon</xhtml:a>. For those who
have never attended, it's basically one or more tracks running
parallel to the main conference, but with content pitched by
attendees -- sometimes presented by them, other times presented by
others who are knowledgeable in the field.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Why should you care? There are great sessions already selected
for the conference featuring some well-known speakers from the PHP
world; why would you want to either attend or present at the
uncon?</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:h2>Continue the Discussion</xhtml:h2>
<xhtml:p>Last year, I did a tutorial session with <xhtml:a href="http://mikenaberezny.com">Mike Naberezny</xhtml:a> covering PHP
development best practices. Following the session, several
attendees approached Keith and said they could really use a session
just on <xhtml:a href="http://subversion.tigris.org/">Subversion</xhtml:a>; the
material covered in the tutorial, while good, did not go into
enough depth for them.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Keith then approached me about doing an uncon session, and I in
turn tagged <xhtml:a href="http://www.lornajane.net">Lorna Jane
Mitchell</xhtml:a> about doing the session. We ended up doing it
together, after sitting down for about 10 minutes of planning. We
had the flexibility to both go over what we thought were core
basics everyone should know, as well as to answer very specific
questions. The session was very well attended, and those people who
gave us feedback indicated that it was exactly the amount of detail
they were looking for.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>So, in summary, the uncon allowed attendees to get more
information on a topic that was covered only briefly in another,
regular session.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:h2>Springboard to Speaking</xhtml:h2>
<xhtml:p>Was your talk rejected for the conference? Are you having
trouble getting accepted to any conferences at all?</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Conference organizers have a catch-22 they face every time they
put together a schedule. On the one hand, there may be some really
interesting talks submitted by unknown speakers; on the other,
scheduling known speakers helps put money on the table (attendees
want to hear from established experts). As a result, you see a lot
of the same speakers at each and every conference.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>So, how do <xhtml:em>you</xhtml:em> break in? You speak.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Speaking at area user groups is one way to break into the
system; good sessions often generate buzz that extends beyond your
user group. But an even better way is to speak at an uncon session
at an established conference. Oftentimes you'll have conference
organizers attending these, or friends of conference organizers,
and this can have a huge impact on your chances at speaking.
Additionally, I've seen a ton of buzz generated on twitter and
blogs by uncon sessions -- and this buzz gets noticed.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Don't believe me? Let's revisit that talk Lorna Jane and I gave.
We pitched it as a tutorial session for <xhtml:a href="http://tek.mtacon.com/">php|tek</xhtml:a> this spring... and it was
accepted, largely on the basis of our uncon session. It was the
only talk I pitched for that conference that was accepted. (Believe
it or not, I have to submit talks just like everyone else, and get
a fair share of rejections just like everyone else.)</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>At php|tek, I also pitched two uncon tracks, one on using Git
with SVN, and another on how to write domain models for your MVC
layers. This latter session, on models, generated a lot of buzz,
and was later picked up by MTA for a <xhtml:a href="http://codeworks.mtacon.com/">CodeWorks 2009</xhtml:a> webinar, which
was very well received. I also pitched it for ZendCon this year...
and will be presenting it there in two weeks.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>In short, if you want to speak at conferences, start by pitching
ideas to the uncon tracks at conferences you attend. Prepare well
for it, make a good impression, and you may be delivering it as a
regular session at another conference.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:h2>Explore new ideas</xhtml:h2>
<xhtml:p>Conference organizers, besides having to choose well-known
speakers, often also need to stick to known topics. Part of the
reason you see topics on the buzz words du jour is because people
want to see sessions on them. But what about things like PHP-GTK?
or using PHP to write CLI tools? or using PHP to connect to a
specific web service? These may all be interesting, but may not
attract crowds. But what if <xhtml:em>you</xhtml:em>, as an attendee, want to
hear about these topics?</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>One aspect of the uncon is that you can vote on topics and/or
suggest topics you want to hear about. This gives you a chance to
help shape the direction of the conference to cater to your own
interests. It also allows you to explore some areas of the language
you may not have known about, but, when you see the presentation
abstract, could benefit the work you do.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>So, use the uncon to explore the language!</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:h2>Vote now!</xhtml:h2>
<xhtml:p>If you're going to ZendCon, plan on speaking at or attending the
uncon! And help shape it, by heading over to Joind.in and <xhtml:a href="http://joind.in/event/zendcon09-uncon">voting for sessions</xhtml:a>
now! See you there!</xhtml:p>
</xhtml:div>
    </content>
  </entry>
</feed>
