<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title type="text">Tag: zendcon :: phly, boy, phly</title>
  <updated>2009-10-07T14:53:07+0000</updated>
  <generator uri="http://framework.zend.com" version="2.0.2">Zend_Feed_Writer</generator>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mwop.net/blog/tag/zendcon.html"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://mwop.net/blog/tag/zendcon-atom.xml"/>
  <id>http://mwop.net/blog/tag/zendcon.html</id>
  <entry xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why UnCons are Important]]></title>
    <published>2009-10-07T12:55:05+0000</published>
    <updated>2009-10-07T14:53:07+0000</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mwop.net/blog/225-Why-UnCons-are-Important.html"/>
    <id>http://mwop.net/blog/225-Why-UnCons-are-Important.html</id>
    <author>
      <name>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</name>
      <email>me@mwop.net</email>
      <uri>http://mwop.net</uri>
    </author>
    <content xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" type="xhtml">
      <xhtml:div xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><xhtml:p>My good friend, <xhtml:a href="http://caseysoftware.com/blog/">Keith
Casey</xhtml:a>, is once again chairing <xhtml:a href="http://zendcon.com/">Zendcon's</xhtml:a> <xhtml:a href="http://joind.in/event/zendcon09-uncon">UnCon</xhtml:a>. For those who
have never attended, it's basically one or more tracks running
parallel to the main conference, but with content pitched by
attendees -- sometimes presented by them, other times presented by
others who are knowledgeable in the field.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Why should you care? There are great sessions already selected
for the conference featuring some well-known speakers from the PHP
world; why would you want to either attend or present at the
uncon?</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:h2>Continue the Discussion</xhtml:h2>
<xhtml:p>Last year, I did a tutorial session with <xhtml:a href="http://mikenaberezny.com">Mike Naberezny</xhtml:a> covering PHP
development best practices. Following the session, several
attendees approached Keith and said they could really use a session
just on <xhtml:a href="http://subversion.tigris.org/">Subversion</xhtml:a>; the
material covered in the tutorial, while good, did not go into
enough depth for them.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Keith then approached me about doing an uncon session, and I in
turn tagged <xhtml:a href="http://www.lornajane.net">Lorna Jane
Mitchell</xhtml:a> about doing the session. We ended up doing it
together, after sitting down for about 10 minutes of planning. We
had the flexibility to both go over what we thought were core
basics everyone should know, as well as to answer very specific
questions. The session was very well attended, and those people who
gave us feedback indicated that it was exactly the amount of detail
they were looking for.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>So, in summary, the uncon allowed attendees to get more
information on a topic that was covered only briefly in another,
regular session.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:h2>Springboard to Speaking</xhtml:h2>
<xhtml:p>Was your talk rejected for the conference? Are you having
trouble getting accepted to any conferences at all?</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Conference organizers have a catch-22 they face every time they
put together a schedule. On the one hand, there may be some really
interesting talks submitted by unknown speakers; on the other,
scheduling known speakers helps put money on the table (attendees
want to hear from established experts). As a result, you see a lot
of the same speakers at each and every conference.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>So, how do <xhtml:em>you</xhtml:em> break in? You speak.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Speaking at area user groups is one way to break into the
system; good sessions often generate buzz that extends beyond your
user group. But an even better way is to speak at an uncon session
at an established conference. Oftentimes you'll have conference
organizers attending these, or friends of conference organizers,
and this can have a huge impact on your chances at speaking.
Additionally, I've seen a ton of buzz generated on twitter and
blogs by uncon sessions -- and this buzz gets noticed.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Don't believe me? Let's revisit that talk Lorna Jane and I gave.
We pitched it as a tutorial session for <xhtml:a href="http://tek.mtacon.com/">php|tek</xhtml:a> this spring... and it was
accepted, largely on the basis of our uncon session. It was the
only talk I pitched for that conference that was accepted. (Believe
it or not, I have to submit talks just like everyone else, and get
a fair share of rejections just like everyone else.)</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>At php|tek, I also pitched two uncon tracks, one on using Git
with SVN, and another on how to write domain models for your MVC
layers. This latter session, on models, generated a lot of buzz,
and was later picked up by MTA for a <xhtml:a href="http://codeworks.mtacon.com/">CodeWorks 2009</xhtml:a> webinar, which
was very well received. I also pitched it for ZendCon this year...
and will be presenting it there in two weeks.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>In short, if you want to speak at conferences, start by pitching
ideas to the uncon tracks at conferences you attend. Prepare well
for it, make a good impression, and you may be delivering it as a
regular session at another conference.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:h2>Explore new ideas</xhtml:h2>
<xhtml:p>Conference organizers, besides having to choose well-known
speakers, often also need to stick to known topics. Part of the
reason you see topics on the buzz words du jour is because people
want to see sessions on them. But what about things like PHP-GTK?
or using PHP to write CLI tools? or using PHP to connect to a
specific web service? These may all be interesting, but may not
attract crowds. But what if <xhtml:em>you</xhtml:em>, as an attendee, want to
hear about these topics?</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>One aspect of the uncon is that you can vote on topics and/or
suggest topics you want to hear about. This gives you a chance to
help shape the direction of the conference to cater to your own
interests. It also allows you to explore some areas of the language
you may not have known about, but, when you see the presentation
abstract, could benefit the work you do.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>So, use the uncon to explore the language!</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:h2>Vote now!</xhtml:h2>
<xhtml:p>If you're going to ZendCon, plan on speaking at or attending the
uncon! And help shape it, by heading over to Joind.in and <xhtml:a href="http://joind.in/event/zendcon09-uncon">voting for sessions</xhtml:a>
now! See you there!</xhtml:p>
</xhtml:div>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2007 Retrospective]]></title>
    <published>2008-01-01T21:49:26+0000</published>
    <updated>2008-01-03T11:22:35+0000</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mwop.net/blog/154-2007-Retrospective.html"/>
    <id>http://mwop.net/blog/154-2007-Retrospective.html</id>
    <author>
      <name>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</name>
      <email>me@mwop.net</email>
      <uri>http://mwop.net</uri>
    </author>
    <content xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" type="xhtml">
      <xhtml:div xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><xhtml:p>2007 was a busy year, both personally and professionally. I
won't go into the personal too much, because, well, it's personal,
and some of the details are simply inappropriate for blogging
material.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Here's the short version:</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:ul>
<xhtml:li>One trip to Belgium and The Netherlands.</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>Two trips to Israel.</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>Two trips to Atlanta, GA (not counting the return trip from
Europe, when I was stranded for a day due to storms in the
Northeast).</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>Three different user groups attended, with three
presentations.</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>One major Zend Framework release</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>One PEAR release.</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>One podcast.</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>One webinar.</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>One book published.</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li>One conference attended.</xhtml:li>
</xhtml:ul>
<xhtml:p>What follows is my month-by-month breakdown:</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:h3>January</xhtml:h3>
<xhtml:p>I finished up the last of my three chapters for <xhtml:a href="http://sitepoint.com/books/phpant2/">The PHP Anthology, 2nd
Edition</xhtml:a>, and promptly used my advance to buy the family a
Wii.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>I was also introduced to <xhtml:a href="http://jansch.nl/">Ivo
Jansch</xhtml:a> through work, and had him wow me with one of the
<xhtml:a href="http://ibuildings.nl">ibuildings</xhtml:a> products.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:h3>February</xhtml:h3>
<xhtml:p>Mid-month, my boss at <xhtml:a href="http://www.zend.com/">Zend</xhtml:a>,
Boaz, got the go-ahead to use the ibuildings WDE platform to build
our new website CMS; part of the plan would include training at the
ibuildings home office in Vlissingen, NL... which meant I had to
get my passport pronto.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Towards the end of the month, I was invited to <xhtml:a href="http://bostonphp.org">BostonPHP</xhtml:a> to present building a simple
<xhtml:a href="http://framework.zend.com/">Zend Framework</xhtml:a> CRUD
application, along with <xhtml:a href="http://hagunbu.ch/">Chuck
Hagenbuch</xhtml:a> of the <xhtml:a href="http://horde.org/">HORDE project</xhtml:a>.
While there, <xhtml:a href="http://cake.insertdesignhere.com/">Nate
Abele</xhtml:a> heckled me, and then joined Chuck and myself for an
impromptu framework panel; a good time was had by all.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:h3>March</xhtml:h3>
<xhtml:p>I flew to Brussels, Belgium, where I met my supervisor, Boaz, so
we could go to Vlissingen. We spent the day in Brussels, walking
around and visiting such sites as the Cathedral of St. Michael, La
Grand Place, and the Mannekin Pis.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Our visit to ibuildings was very productive, and I was very
impressed by the team there; everybody was very knowledgeable and
skilled. I presented a Zend Framework overview, as well as an
abbreviated version of the Best Practices talk I'd given with Mike
Naberezny at the 2006 ZendCon; the latter ignited a ton of
questions and enthusiasm.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>On returning home, I had a ton of work to do on the zend.com
CMS, and this continued in spurts through November. The job was
made much easier by the ibuildings WDE product.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>I closed out a ton of MVC issues in the Zend Framework, and we
released the first beta version late in the month.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:h3>April</xhtml:h3>
<xhtml:p>At the beginning of the month, our landlord threw us for a loop
and announced he was going to sell our apartment... meaning that we
either had to step up our plans to purchase a home, or start
looking for a new rental. Ultimately, we ended up looking for a
rental, due to time constraints. The next two months would be
highlighted with the look for a new place as well as countless
showings of our apartment to potential buyers.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Mid-month, we packed up the family and flew down to Atlanta, GA,
to visit my wife's family. While there, we were able to go to the
Atlanta Zoo and see Mei Lan, their baby panda -- way cute!</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:h3>May</xhtml:h3>
<xhtml:p>Mid-month, we found a new place in Richmond, VT -- a small
village about 10 minutes from Burlington, near where we originally
lived when we first moved to Vermont.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>During the first RC for Zend Framework, released at the end of
the month, I introduced the ViewRenderer, a feature for
auto-rendering views based on the current controller and action
name -- a feature common to many frameworks. However, it ostensibly
broke a ton of existing applications by being enabled by default --
not one of my more popular decisions. Since the 1.0.0 release, I've
heard little grumbling about it, and it's now often cited as an
ease-of-use feature -- go figure.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:h3>June</xhtml:h3>
<xhtml:p>The first week of June, I flew to Tel Aviv, Israel, to start
training people on the new CMS, as well as to work with our entire
ebiz team to finalize the work plan for completing the CMS. It was,
needless to say, my first time to Israel or the Middle East, and I
was constantly confronted with culture shock. Europe was an easy
transition to make, but Israel was completely foreign to me --
everything from the way people drove, to the architecture, to the
food was different. Unfortunately, I arrived a day late due to a
flight cancellation, and missed the tour of Jerusalem my supervisor
had planned for all of us. However, he took me to the city of Yafa,
an Arabic city where the Israeli's originally tried to settle
before building Tel Aviv to the north. The architecture was
amazing, as were the winding, narrow streets of the old city.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>I was also told during this trip that Andi had requested
transferring me full-time to the Zend Framework team. I would spend
the next week or two weighing my options, and ultimately decided to
do so.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>A week after I returned, we moved into our new rental in
Richmond. The kids love the new place, which has a bedroom for each
of them, a yard, and porches on each entrance.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Somehow, I also found time to record my first (and so far only)
<xhtml:a href="http://devzone.zend.com/article/2140-PHP-Abstract-Podcast-Episode-2---Backup-or-Die">
PHP Abstract podcast</xhtml:a>.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:h3>July</xhtml:h3>
<xhtml:p>We released <xhtml:a href="http://framework.zend.com/">Zend
Framework</xhtml:a> 1.0.0 at the beginning of the month, marking our
first stable release. While many still view it as incomplete, the
overwhelming feedback has been positive, and we've had over 2
million downloads to date.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>I accepted the transfer to the Zend Framework team, but the
condition was made that I would stay part-time on the ebiz team
until the new site was launched. This meant that the next 5 months
were spent splitting my time between the two projects, often
working late and on weekends to get work done.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Towards the end of the month, we took a long weekend camping in
Vermont's Northeast Kingdom. The weather was unseasonably wet, but
we persevered and had a great time. 5 days of offline time was
definitely needed!</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>I also finally released the first stable version of <xhtml:a href="http://pear.php.net/packages/File_Fortune">File_Fortune</xhtml:a> on
<xhtml:a href="http://pear.php.net/">PEAR</xhtml:a>, over a year since I'd
first proposed it. The package interfaces with mod_fortune files,
allowing both the ability to read and write such files, with full
binary compatability.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:h3>August</xhtml:h3>
<xhtml:p>Not much to report in August, except work, work, and more
work.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:h3>September</xhtml:h3>
<xhtml:p>My ebiz supervisor, Boaz, flew me to Tel Aviv for a second time,
this time to perform a "brain dump" for the rest of the team before
I transitioned fully out of the team, and also to help setup our
new data center and release procedures. This time, Boaz took me to
Jerusalem himself during my last full day in the country. If you've
never been to the city, you should definitely put it on your list
of things to do before you die. With my degree in religion, the
place was full of meaning for me, but it would be putting it
lightly to say that religion is palpable in the air there. We
visited the Wailing Wall, the Via Dolorosa, the Church of the Holy
Sepulchre, and listened to the muezzins sing the call to prayer for
the muslims. The tour was simply amazing.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>A few days after I returned, I flew down to New York City for a
special meeting of <xhtml:a href="http://nyphp.org/">NYPHP</xhtml:a>, where
<xhtml:a href="http://blogs.zend.com/author/mark/">Mark de Visser</xhtml:a>
presented on various Zend products and initiatives, and I gave a
Zend Framework overview.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>A week after the NYPHP presentation, I did a <xhtml:a href="http://www.zend.com/webinars">zend.com webinar</xhtml:a> on the Zend
Framework MVC layer.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:h3>October</xhtml:h3>
<xhtml:p>October was the month of <xhtml:a href="http://www.zendcon.con/">ZendCon</xhtml:a>. I presented a full-day
tutorial on best practices and unit testing with <xhtml:a href="http://sebastian-bergmann.de/">Sebastian Bergmann</xhtml:a> and <xhtml:a href="http://naberezny.com/">Mike Naberezny</xhtml:a>; despite the length and
subject matter, we were SRO for most of the day.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>I also did a main-stage presentation on Zend Framework's MVC
components, directly following <xhtml:a href="http://terrychay.com/blog/">Terry Chay</xhtml:a> -- an intimidating
situation at best. From the feedback I've seen, the presentation
was well-received, and I had somewhere between 120 and 150
attendees -- phenomenal! (Even more amazing was how many people
were familiar with MVC in general!)</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>One great thing about the conference was the fact that I got to
network with a number of framework developers, both Zend Framework
and otherwise, including Nate Abele of CakePHP as well as <xhtml:a href="http://paul-m-jones.com">Paul M. Jones</xhtml:a> of <xhtml:a href="http://solarphp.com">the Solar framework</xhtml:a>. Many good
conversations were had.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Late in the month, <xhtml:a href="http://sitepoint.com/books/phpant2/">The PHP Anthology, 2nd
Edition</xhtml:a>, my first published book as an author, was finally
released!</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:h3>November</xhtml:h3>
<xhtml:p>I spent much of the month working on <xhtml:a href="http://framework.zend.com/wiki/display/ZFPROP/Zend_Layout">Zend_Layout</xhtml:a>,
a much requested component that simplifies and automates Two Step
Views in Zend Framework. I also started work implementing <xhtml:a href="http://framework.zend.com/wiki/pages/viewpage.action?pageId=33071">
Zend_View Enhanced</xhtml:a>, a set of view helpers for making complex
views with Zend_View possible.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>I also started playing with <xhtml:a href="http://twitter.com/">Twitter</xhtml:a> a bit, and came up with a
<xhtml:a href="http://framework.zend.com/wiki/display/ZFPROP/Zend_Service_Twitter">
Zend_Service_Twitter</xhtml:a> proposal for interacting with the Twitter
API via PHP.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>And finally, the Sunday before Thanksgiving, we finally launched
the new <xhtml:a href="http://www.zend.com/">Zend.com</xhtml:a> site, which was
well-received in the blogosphere.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:h3>December</xhtml:h3>
<xhtml:p>A goal I've had for some time has been to form a PHP user group
in the Burlington area. A friend of mine pointed out to me sometime
this fall that there's actually already <xhtml:a href="http://groups.google.com/group/Burlington-VT-PHP">a Google
Group</xhtml:a> formed; he and the original founder started planning a
meeting for early December. I spoke at this inaugural meeting,
presenting Zend Framework's MVC layer yet again; a good time was
had by all, and a lot of enthusiasm for future meetings was
generated.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>I finished up Zend_Layout and Zend_View Enhanced with the help
of Ralph Schindler, and got a new proposal up for <xhtml:a href="http://framework.zend.com/wiki/display/ZFPROP/Zend_Form">Zend_Form</xhtml:a>,
just in time for my holidays to begin -- 11 days with family and
with little to no internet connectivity during a trip to Atlanta,
GA for one of only a handful of Christmases I've spent without
snow.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:h2>Summary</xhtml:h2>
<xhtml:p>This year was <xhtml:em>incredibly</xhtml:em> busy -- three cross-seas
trips, one cross-continent trip, a move, and several trips along
the Eastern Seaboard; three user group presentations, and eight
presentations over the course of the year; one conference; one
move; one PEAR release; one podcast; one webinar; one book; and
countless hours of programming.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>My goals for the coming year? I'm too tired to even think about
it ;-).</xhtml:p>
</xhtml:div>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ZendCon is over at last]]></title>
    <published>2007-10-12T00:50:47+0000</published>
    <updated>2007-10-18T07:19:41+0000</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mwop.net/blog/146-ZendCon-is-over-at-last.html"/>
    <id>http://mwop.net/blog/146-ZendCon-is-over-at-last.html</id>
    <author>
      <name>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</name>
      <email>me@mwop.net</email>
      <uri>http://mwop.net</uri>
    </author>
    <content xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" type="xhtml">
      <xhtml:div xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><xhtml:p><xhtml:a href="http://www.zendcon.com/">ZendCon '07</xhtml:a> is finally
over, the dust has settled, and I finally find myself with some
time alone... practically the first I've had since Sunday. The week
was fantastic, and I had many good conversations and brainstorming
sessions. Oh, and I ended up giving three different sessions, so
it's time for links to slides and materials:</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:ul>
<xhtml:li><xhtml:a href="/uploads/2007-ZendCon-BestPractices.odp">Best
Practices of PHP Development</xhtml:a>. <xhtml:a href="http://sebastian-bergmann.de/">Sebastian</xhtml:a>, <xhtml:a href="http://mikenaberezny.com/">Mike</xhtml:a>, and I presented a full-day
tutorial on PHP development best practices, focussing primarily on
testing and testing strategies, but also covering coding standards,
usage of SCM tools, and deployment. There were a ton of questions
from the attendees, and Sebastian even whipped out some extra
slides at the end showing new and little-known features of PHPUnit.
Basically, reading the slides won't really indicate what we
covered, but is more of a general outline. It was an honor and
pleasure to work with Sebastian and Mike on this, and I hope we can
do it again in the future some time.</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li><xhtml:a href="/uploads/2007-ZendCon-MVC.ppt">Zend Framework MVC
Quick Start</xhtml:a>. This was basically the same session I did in my
<xhtml:a href="http://www.zend.com/webinar">webinar</xhtml:a> a couple weeks
ago, with a few corrections and a small demonstration. Cal put me
on directly following <xhtml:a href="http://terrychay.com/blog">Terry
Chay</xhtml:a>, in the largest of the four session rooms -- the one where
all the keynotes occurred -- talk about intimidating! Amazingly,
the session was really well attended -- others I talked to estimate
between 100 and 150 people showed up. The most amazing part,
though, was that when I asked how many people knew what 'MVC' was,
I don't think there was a single person who didn't raise their hand
-- definitely a sign of how well accepted the pattern now is in
PHP.</xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li><xhtml:a href="/uploads/2007-ZendCon-AjaxPresentation.odp">AJAX-Enabling Your
Zend Framework Controllers</xhtml:a>. I did this talk for the <xhtml:a href="http://www.zendcon.com/wiki/index.php?title=Uncon">Unconference</xhtml:a>,
mainly because its a topic I've been interested in and wanted to
present. In it, I detailed how to ajax-enable an application
through some easy tricks with Action and View Helpers and using JS
to decorate your existing application. The reference app I used was
a pastebin, and I've got code for both <xhtml:a href="http://dojotoolkit.org">Dojo</xhtml:a> and <xhtml:a href="http://prototypejs.org">Prototype</xhtml:a> flavors available:
<xhtml:ul>
<xhtml:li><xhtml:a href="/uploads/PastebinDojo.tar.gz">Dojo pastebin</xhtml:a></xhtml:li>
<xhtml:li><xhtml:a href="/uploads/PastebinPrototype.tar.gz">Prototype
pastebin</xhtml:a></xhtml:li>
</xhtml:ul>
</xhtml:li>
</xhtml:ul>
<xhtml:p>The two highlight keynote speakers, for me, were definitely
<xhtml:a href="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/">Joel Spolsky</xhtml:a> and
<xhtml:a href="http://craphound.com/">Cory Doctorow</xhtml:a>. Neither spoke
about PHP, but both spoke about topics that PHP developers should
take to heart. Perhaps I'll elaborate on those in another post.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>Another bonus for me was the number of old and new friends alike
I got to see -- I had many good conversations with Paul M. Jones,
Nate Abele, Ivo Jansch, and Ralph Schindler, and opportunities to
finally meet fellow co-author Lig Turmelle, Ben Ramsey, Chris
Shifflet (dude, we've been to four conferences together, and never
yet met!), and many, many others. I was also overwhelmed by the
number of Zend Framework users who sought me out either to ask me
questions or simply thank me and the others on the team for the
project; I'm deeply honored that I can work on a project that
affects so many developers.</xhtml:p>
<xhtml:p>And now for some down time to recuperate...</xhtml:p>
</xhtml:div>
    </content>
  </entry>
</feed>
