<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/">
  <channel>
    <title>Tag: zendcon :: phly, boy, phly</title>
    <description>Tag: zendcon :: phly, boy, phly</description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 07 Oct 2009 14:53:07 +0000</pubDate>
    <generator>Zend_Feed_Writer 2.0.0 (http://framework.zend.com)</generator>
    <link>http://mwop.net/blog/tag/zendcon.html</link>
    <atom:link rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" href="http://mwop.net/blog/tag/zendcon-rss.xml"/>
    <item>
      <title>Why UnCons are Important</title>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Oct 2009 14:53:07 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/225-Why-UnCons-are-Important.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/225-Why-UnCons-are-Important.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    My good friend, <a href="http://caseysoftware.com/blog/">Keith Casey</a>, is
    once again chairing <a href="http://zendcon.com/">Zendcon's</a> <a
        href="http://joind.in/event/zendcon09-uncon">UnCon</a>. For those who
    have never attended, it's basically one or more tracks running parallel to
    the main conference, but with content pitched by attendees -- sometimes
    presented by them, other times presented by others who are knowledgeable in
    the field.
</p>

<p>
    Why should you care? There are great sessions already selected for the
    conference featuring some well-known speakers from the PHP world; why would
    you want to either attend or present at the uncon?
</p><h2>Continue the Discussion</h2>

<p>
    Last year, I did a tutorial session with <a
        href="http://mikenaberezny.com">Mike Naberezny</a> covering PHP
    development best practices. Following the session, several attendees
    approached Keith and said they could really use a session just on <a
        href="http://subversion.tigris.org/">Subversion</a>; the material
    covered in the tutorial, while good, did not go into enough depth for them. 
</p>

<p>
    Keith then approached me about doing an uncon session, and I in turn tagged
    <a href="http://www.lornajane.net">Lorna Jane Mitchell</a> about doing the
    session. We ended up doing it together, after sitting down for about 10
    minutes of planning. We had the flexibility to both go over what we thought
    were core basics everyone should know, as well as to answer very specific
    questions. The session was very well attended, and those people who gave us
    feedback indicated that it was exactly the amount of detail they were
    looking for.
</p>

<p>
    So, in summary, the uncon allowed attendees to get more information on a
    topic that was covered only briefly in another, regular session.
</p>

<h2>Springboard to Speaking</h2>

<p>
    Was your talk rejected for the conference? Are you having trouble getting
    accepted to any conferences at all?
</p>

<p>
    Conference organizers have a catch-22 they face every time they put together
    a schedule. On the one hand, there may be some really interesting talks
    submitted by unknown speakers; on the other, scheduling known speakers helps
    put money on the table (attendees want to hear from established experts). As
    a result, you see a lot of the same speakers at each and every conference.
</p>

<p>
    So, how do <em>you</em> break in? You speak.
</p>

<p>
    Speaking at area user groups is one way to break into the system; good
    sessions often generate buzz that extends beyond your user group. But an
    even better way is to speak at an uncon session at an established
    conference. Oftentimes you'll have conference organizers attending these, or
    friends of conference organizers, and this can have a huge impact on your
    chances at speaking. Additionally, I've seen a ton of buzz generated on
    twitter and blogs by uncon sessions -- and this buzz gets noticed.
</p>

<p>
    Don't believe me? Let's revisit that talk Lorna Jane and I gave. We pitched
    it as a tutorial session for <a href="http://tek.mtacon.com/">php|tek</a>
    this spring... and it was accepted, largely on the basis of our uncon
    session. It was the only talk I pitched for that conference that was
    accepted. (Believe it or not, I have to submit talks just like everyone
    else, and get a fair share of rejections just like everyone else.)
</p>

<p>
    At php|tek, I also pitched two uncon tracks, one on using Git with SVN, and
    another on how to write domain models for your MVC layers. This latter
    session, on models, generated a lot of buzz, and was later picked up by MTA
    for a <a href="http://codeworks.mtacon.com/">CodeWorks 2009</a> webinar,
    which was very well received. I also pitched it for ZendCon this year... and
    will be presenting it there in two weeks.
</p>

<p>
    In short, if you want to speak at conferences, start by pitching ideas to
    the uncon tracks at conferences you attend. Prepare well for it, make a
    good impression, and you may be delivering it as a regular session at
    another conference.
</p>

<h2>Explore new ideas</h2>

<p>
    Conference organizers, besides having to choose well-known speakers, often
    also need to stick to known topics. Part of the reason you see topics on the
    buzz words du jour is because people want to see sessions on them. But what
    about things like PHP-GTK? or using PHP to write CLI tools? or using PHP to
    connect to a specific web service? These may all be interesting, but may not
    attract crowds. But what if <em>you</em>, as an attendee, want to hear about
    these topics?
</p>

<p>
    One aspect of the uncon is that you can vote on topics and/or suggest topics
    you want to hear about. This gives you a chance to help shape the direction
    of the conference to cater to your own interests. It also allows you to
    explore some areas of the language you may not have known about, but, when
    you see the presentation abstract, could benefit the work you do.
</p>

<p>
    So, use the uncon to explore the language!
</p>

<h2>Vote now!</h2>

<p>
    If you're going to ZendCon, plan on speaking at or attending the uncon!
    And help shape it, by heading over to Joind.in and <a
        href="http://joind.in/event/zendcon09-uncon">voting for sessions</a>
    now! See you there!
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2007 Retrospective</title>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jan 2008 11:22:35 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/154-2007-Retrospective.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/154-2007-Retrospective.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    2007 was a busy year, both personally and professionally. I won't go into
    the personal too much, because, well, it's personal, and some of the details
    are simply inappropriate for blogging material.
</p>

<p>
    Here's the short version:
</p>

<ul>
    <li>One trip to Belgium and The Netherlands.</li>
    <li>Two trips to Israel.</li>
    <li>Two trips to Atlanta, GA (not counting the return trip from Europe, when
    I was stranded for a day due to storms in the Northeast).</li>
    <li>Three different user groups attended, with three presentations.</li>
    <li>One major Zend Framework release</li>
    <li>One PEAR release.</li>
    <li>One podcast.</li>
    <li>One webinar.</li>
    <li>One book published.</li>
    <li>One conference attended.</li>
</ul>

<p>
    What follows is my month-by-month breakdown:
</p><h3>January</h3>
<p>
    I finished up the last of my three chapters for 
    <a href="http://sitepoint.com/books/phpant2/">The PHP Anthology, 2nd Edition</a>, 
    and promptly used my advance to buy the family a Wii. 
</p>

<p>
    I was also introduced to <a href="http://jansch.nl/">Ivo Jansch</a> through
    work, and had him wow me with one of the 
    <a href="http://ibuildings.nl">ibuildings</a> products.
</p>

<h3>February</h3>
<p>
    Mid-month, my boss at <a href="http://www.zend.com/">Zend</a>, Boaz, got the
    go-ahead to use the ibuildings WDE platform to build our new website CMS;
    part of the plan would include training at the ibuildings home office in
    Vlissingen, NL... which meant I had to get my passport pronto.
</p>

<p>
    Towards the end of the month, I was invited to 
    <a href="http://bostonphp.org">BostonPHP</a> to present 
    building a simple <a href="http://framework.zend.com/">Zend Framework</a>
    CRUD application, along with <a href="http://hagunbu.ch/">Chuck Hagenbuch</a> 
    of the <a href="http://horde.org/">HORDE project</a>. While there, 
    <a href="http://cake.insertdesignhere.com/">Nate Abele</a> heckled me, and
    then joined Chuck and myself for an impromptu framework panel; a good time
    was had by all.
</p>

<h3>March</h3>
<p>
    I flew to Brussels, Belgium, where I met my supervisor, Boaz, so we could go
    to Vlissingen. We spent the day in Brussels, walking around and visiting
    such sites as the Cathedral of St. Michael, La Grand Place, and the Mannekin
    Pis. 
</p>

<p>
    Our visit to ibuildings was very productive, and I was very impressed by the
    team there; everybody was very knowledgeable and skilled. I presented a Zend
    Framework overview, as well as an abbreviated version of the Best Practices
    talk I'd given with Mike Naberezny at the 2006 ZendCon; the latter ignited a
    ton of questions and enthusiasm.
</p>

<p>
    On returning home, I had a ton of work to do on the zend.com CMS, and this
    continued in spurts through November. The job was made much easier by the
    ibuildings WDE product.
</p>

<p>
    I closed out a ton of MVC issues in the Zend Framework, and we released the
    first beta version late in the month.
</p>

<h3>April</h3>
<p>
    At the beginning of the month, our landlord threw us for a loop and
    announced he was going to sell our apartment... meaning that we either had
    to step up our plans to purchase a home, or start looking for a new rental.
    Ultimately, we ended up looking for a rental, due to time constraints. The
    next two months would be highlighted with the look for a new place as well
    as countless showings of our apartment to potential buyers.
</p>

<p>
    Mid-month, we packed up the family and flew down to Atlanta, GA, to visit my
    wife's family. While there, we were able to go to the Atlanta Zoo and see
    Mei Lan, their baby panda -- way cute!
</p>

<h3>May</h3>
<p>
    Mid-month, we found a new place in Richmond, VT -- a small village about 10
    minutes from Burlington, near where we originally lived when we first moved
    to Vermont. 
</p>

<p>
    During the first RC for Zend Framework, released at the end of the month, I
    introduced the ViewRenderer, a feature for auto-rendering views based on the
    current controller and action name -- a feature common to many frameworks.
    However, it ostensibly broke a ton of existing applications by being enabled
    by default -- not one of my more popular decisions. Since the 1.0.0 release,
    I've heard little grumbling about it, and it's now often cited as an
    ease-of-use feature -- go figure.
</p>

<h3>June</h3>
<p>
    The first week of June, I flew to Tel Aviv, Israel, to start training people
    on the new CMS, as well as to work with our entire ebiz team to finalize the
    work plan for completing the CMS. It was, needless to say, my first time to
    Israel or the Middle East, and I was constantly confronted with culture
    shock. Europe was an easy transition to make, but Israel was completely
    foreign to me -- everything from the way people drove, to the architecture,
    to the food was different. Unfortunately, I arrived a day late due to a
    flight cancellation, and missed the tour of Jerusalem my supervisor had
    planned for all of us. However, he took me to the city of Yafa, an Arabic
    city where the Israeli's originally tried to settle before building Tel Aviv
    to the north. The architecture was amazing, as were the winding, narrow
    streets of the old city.
</p>

<p>
    I was also told during this trip that Andi had requested transferring me
    full-time to the Zend Framework team. I would spend the next week or two
    weighing my options, and ultimately decided to do so.
</p>

<p>
    A week after I returned, we moved into our new rental in Richmond. The kids
    love the new place, which has a bedroom for each of them, a yard, and
    porches on each entrance.
</p>

<p>
    Somehow, I also found time to record my first (and so far only) 
    <a href="http://devzone.zend.com/article/2140-PHP-Abstract-Podcast-Episode-2---Backup-or-Die">PHP Abstract podcast</a>.
</p>

<h3>July</h3>
<p>
    We released <a href="http://framework.zend.com/">Zend Framework</a> 1.0.0 at
    the beginning of the month, marking our first stable release. While many
    still view it as incomplete, the overwhelming feedback has been positive,
    and we've had over 2 million downloads to date.
</p>

<p>
    I accepted the transfer to the Zend Framework team, but the condition was
    made that I would stay part-time on the ebiz team until the new site was
    launched.  This meant that the next 5 months were spent splitting my time
    between the two projects, often working late and on weekends to get work
    done.
</p>

<p>
    Towards the end of the month, we took a long weekend camping in Vermont's
    Northeast Kingdom. The weather was unseasonably wet, but we persevered and
    had a great time. 5 days of offline time was definitely needed!
</p>

<p>
    I also finally released the first stable version of 
    <a href="http://pear.php.net/packages/File_Fortune">File_Fortune</a> on 
    <a href="http://pear.php.net/">PEAR</a>, over a year since I'd first
    proposed it. The package interfaces with mod_fortune files, allowing both
    the ability to read and write such files, with full binary compatability.
</p>

<h3>August</h3>
<p>
    Not much to report in August, except work, work, and more work.
</p>

<h3>September</h3>
<p>
    My ebiz supervisor, Boaz, flew me to Tel Aviv for a second time, this time
    to perform a "brain dump" for the rest of the team before I transitioned
    fully out of the team, and also to help setup our new data center and
    release procedures. This time, Boaz took me to Jerusalem himself during my
    last full day in the country. If you've never been to the city, you should
    definitely put it on your list of things to do before you die. With my
    degree in religion, the place was full of meaning for me, but it would be
    putting it lightly to say that religion is palpable in the air there. We
    visited the Wailing Wall, the Via Dolorosa, the Church of the Holy
    Sepulchre, and listened to the muezzins sing the call to prayer for the
    muslims. The tour was simply amazing.
</p>

<p>
    A few days after I returned, I flew down to New York City for a special
    meeting of <a href="http://nyphp.org/">NYPHP</a>, where 
    <a href="http://blogs.zend.com/author/mark/">Mark de Visser</a> presented on
    various Zend products and initiatives, and I gave a Zend Framework overview.
</p>

<p>
    A week after the NYPHP presentation, I did a
    <a href="http://www.zend.com/webinars">zend.com webinar</a>
    on the Zend Framework MVC layer.
</p>

<h3>October</h3>
<p>
    October was the month of <a href="http://www.zendcon.con/">ZendCon</a>. I
    presented a full-day tutorial on best practices and unit testing with 
    <a href="http://sebastian-bergmann.de/">Sebastian Bergmann</a> and 
    <a href="http://naberezny.com/">Mike Naberezny</a>; despite the length and
    subject matter, we were SRO for most of the day. 
</p>
<p>
    I also did a main-stage presentation on Zend Framework's MVC components,
    directly following <a href="http://terrychay.com/blog/">Terry Chay</a> -- an
    intimidating situation at best. From the feedback I've seen, the
    presentation was well-received, and I had somewhere between 120 and 150
    attendees -- phenomenal! (Even more amazing was how many people were
    familiar with MVC in general!)
</p>

<p>
    One great thing about the conference was the fact that I got to network with
    a number of framework developers, both Zend Framework and otherwise,
    including Nate Abele of CakePHP as well as 
    <a href="http://paul-m-jones.com">Paul M. Jones</a> of 
    <a href="http://solarphp.com">the Solar framework</a>. Many good
    conversations were had.
</p>

<p>
    Late in the month, 
    <a href="http://sitepoint.com/books/phpant2/">The PHP Anthology, 2nd Edition</a>, 
    my first published book as an author, was finally released!
</p>

<h3>November</h3>
<p>
    I spent much of the month working on 
    <a href="http://framework.zend.com/wiki/display/ZFPROP/Zend_Layout">Zend_Layout</a>,
    a much requested component that simplifies and automates Two Step Views in
    Zend Framework. I also started work implementing 
    <a href="http://framework.zend.com/wiki/pages/viewpage.action?pageId=33071">Zend_View Enhanced</a>,
    a set of view helpers for making complex views with Zend_View possible.
</p>

<p>
    I also started playing with <a href="http://twitter.com/">Twitter</a> a bit,
    and came up with a 
    <a href="http://framework.zend.com/wiki/display/ZFPROP/Zend_Service_Twitter">Zend_Service_Twitter</a>
    proposal for interacting with the Twitter API via PHP.
</p>

<p>
    And finally, the Sunday before Thanksgiving, we finally launched the new 
    <a href="http://www.zend.com/">Zend.com</a> site, which was well-received in
    the blogosphere.
</p>

<h3>December</h3>
<p>
    A goal I've had for some time has been to form a PHP user group in the
    Burlington area. A friend of mine pointed out to me sometime this fall that
    there's actually already
    <a href="http://groups.google.com/group/Burlington-VT-PHP">a Google Group</a> 
    formed; he and the original founder started planning a meeting for early
    December. I spoke at this inaugural meeting, presenting Zend Framework's MVC
    layer yet again; a good time was had by all, and a lot of enthusiasm for
    future meetings was generated.
</p>

<p>
    I finished up Zend_Layout and Zend_View Enhanced with the help of Ralph
    Schindler, and got a new proposal up for 
    <a href="http://framework.zend.com/wiki/display/ZFPROP/Zend_Form">Zend_Form</a>,
    just in time for my holidays to begin -- 11 days with family and with little
    to no internet connectivity during a trip to Atlanta, GA for one of only a
    handful of Christmases I've spent without snow.
</p>

<h2>Summary</h2>
<p>
    This year was <em>incredibly</em> busy -- three cross-seas trips, one
    cross-continent trip, a move, and several trips along the Eastern Seaboard;
    three user group presentations, and eight presentations over the course of
    the year; one conference; one move; one PEAR release; one podcast; one
    webinar; one book; and countless hours of programming.
</p>

<p>
    My goals for the coming year? I'm too tired to even think about it ;-).
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ZendCon is over at last</title>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Oct 2007 07:19:41 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/146-ZendCon-is-over-at-last.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/146-ZendCon-is-over-at-last.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    <a href="http://www.zendcon.com/">ZendCon '07</a> is finally over, the dust
    has settled, and I finally find myself with some time alone... practically
    the first I've had since Sunday. The week was fantastic, and I had many good
    conversations and brainstorming sessions. Oh, and I ended up giving three
    different sessions, so it's time for links to slides and materials:
</p>
<ul>
    <li><a href="/uploads/2007-ZendCon-BestPractices.odp">Best Practices of PHP Development</a>. 
        <a href="http://sebastian-bergmann.de/">Sebastian</a>, 
        <a href="http://mikenaberezny.com/">Mike</a>, and I presented a full-day
        tutorial on PHP development best practices, focussing primarily on
        testing and testing strategies, but also covering coding standards,
        usage of SCM tools, and deployment. There were a ton of questions from
        the attendees, and Sebastian even whipped out some extra slides at the
        end showing new and little-known features of PHPUnit. Basically, reading
        the slides won't really indicate what we covered, but is more of a
        general outline. It was an honor and pleasure to work with Sebastian and
        Mike on this, and I hope we can do it again in the future some time.
    </li>

    <li><a href="/uploads/2007-ZendCon-MVC.ppt">Zend Framework MVC Quick Start</a>.
        This was basically the same session I did in my <a href="http://www.zend.com/webinar">webinar</a>
        a couple weeks ago, with a few corrections and a small demonstration.
        Cal put me on directly following <a href="http://terrychay.com/blog">Terry Chay</a>,
        in the largest of the four session rooms -- the one where all the
        keynotes occurred -- talk about intimidating! Amazingly, the session was
        really well attended -- others I talked to estimate between 100 and 150
        people showed up. The most amazing part, though, was that when I asked
        how many people knew what 'MVC' was, I don't think there was a single
        person who didn't raise their hand -- definitely a sign of how well
        accepted the pattern now is in PHP.
    </li>

    <li><a href="/uploads/2007-ZendCon-AjaxPresentation.odp">AJAX-Enabling Your Zend Framework Controllers</a>.
        I did this talk for the <a href="http://www.zendcon.com/wiki/index.php?title=Uncon">Unconference</a>,
        mainly because its a topic I've been interested in and wanted to
        present. In it, I detailed how to ajax-enable an application through
        some easy tricks with Action and View Helpers and using JS to decorate
        your existing application. The reference app I used was a pastebin, and
        I've got code for both <a href="http://dojotoolkit.org">Dojo</a> and 
        <a href="http://prototypejs.org">Prototype</a> flavors available:
        <ul>
            <li><a href="/uploads/PastebinDojo.tar.gz">Dojo pastebin</a></li>
            <li><a href="/uploads/PastebinPrototype.tar.gz">Prototype pastebin</a></li>
        </ul>
    </li>
</ul>

<p>
    The two highlight keynote speakers, for me, were definitely 
    <a href="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/">Joel Spolsky</a> and
    <a href="http://craphound.com/">Cory Doctorow</a>. Neither spoke about PHP,
    but both spoke about topics that PHP developers should take to heart.
    Perhaps I'll elaborate on those in another post.
</p>

<p>
    Another bonus for me was the number of old and new friends alike I got to
    see -- I had many good conversations with Paul M. Jones, Nate Abele, Ivo
    Jansch, and Ralph Schindler, and opportunities to finally meet fellow
    co-author Lig Turmelle, Ben Ramsey, Chris Shifflet (dude, we've been to four
    conferences together, and never yet met!), and many, many others. I was also
    overwhelmed by the number of Zend Framework users who sought me out either
    to ask me questions or simply thank me and the others on the team for the
    project; I'm deeply honored that I can work on a project that affects so
    many developers.
</p>

<p>
    And now for some down time to recuperate...
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
