<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/">
  <channel>
    <title>Tag: zendcon08 :: phly, boy, phly</title>
    <description>Tag: zendcon08 :: phly, boy, phly</description>
    <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2008 05:15:30 +0000</pubDate>
    <generator>Zend_Feed_Writer 2.0.0 (http://framework.zend.com)</generator>
    <link>http://mwop.net/blog/tag/zendcon08.html</link>
    <atom:link rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" href="http://mwop.net/blog/tag/zendcon08-rss.xml"/>
    <item>
      <title>Pastebin app and conference updates</title>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2008 05:15:30 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/189-Pastebin-app-and-conference-updates.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/189-Pastebin-app-and-conference-updates.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
    I have a number of updates and followups, and decided to post them in a
    single entry.
</p>

<p>
    First off, you may now <a
        href="http://www.zend.com/en/webinar/Framework-Dojo/Webinar-Rec-Framework-Dev-EN-ZFDojo-20080903.flv">view
        my Dojo Webinar online</a> (requires login and registration at
    zend.com). Attendance was phenomenal, and I've had some really good
    feedback. If you want to see it live, I'm giving the talk (with revisions!)
    at the <a href="http://www.zendcon.com/">ZendCon</a> UnConference, at 
    <a href="http://dojotoolkit.org/2008/07/10/dojo-developer-day-boston">Dojo Developer Day Boston</a> 
    later this month, and at 
        <a href="http://phpworks.mtacon.com/c/schedule/talk/d1s5/1">php|works</a>
    in November. I hope to be able to show new functionality at each
    presentation.
</p>

<p>
    Second, I've completed what I'm calling version 1.0.0 of the pastebin
    application I demo'd in the webinar. The PHP code is fully unit tested
    (though I haven't yet delved into using DOH! to test the JS), and
    incorporates a number of best practices and tips that Pete Higgins from Dojo
    was kind enough to provide to me. When using a custom build (and I provide a
    profile for building one), it simply flies.
</p>

<ul>
    <li><a href="/uploads/pastebin-1.0.0.tar.gz">Download the pastebin
        application</a></li>
</ul>

<p>
    The pastebin application showcases a number of features besides Dojo:
    <code>Zend_Test_PHPUnit</code> was used to test the application,
    and <code>Zend_Wildfire</code>'s FireBug logger and DB profiler are used to
    provide profiling and debug information.
</p>

<p>
    Finally, <a href="http://www.zendcon.com/">ZendCon</a> is next week! I'll be
    around, but already have a packed schedule (1 tutorial, 2 regular sessions,
    an UnCon session, a meet-the-developers session... and that's just what I
    know about!). I look forward to meeting ZF users and developers, though, so
    feel free to grab me and introduce yourself.
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Speaking at ZendCon 2008</title>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Aug 2008 18:06:54 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>http://mwop.net/blog/184-Speaking-at-ZendCon-2008.html</link>
      <guid>http://mwop.net/blog/184-Speaking-at-ZendCon-2008.html</guid>
      <author>me@mwop.net (Matthew Weier O'Phinney)</author>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Weier O'Phinney</dc:creator>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center"><a href=http://zendcon.com><img src="http://zendcon.s3.amazonaws.com/ZendCon08_speaker_badge.gif" border="0"/></a></p>
<p>
    I'll be speaking at <a href="http://www.zendcon.com/">ZendCon</a> again this
    year, and have a four-course meal of sessions to deliver:
</p>

<ul>
    <li>
        <p>
            <b>Best Practices of PHP Development</b>: <a href="http://mikenaberezny.com/">Mike Naberezny</a> 
            and I are teaming up for the fourth year running to deliver a
            tutorial session. While the session topic stays the same, he and I
            have each been developing a number of new practices over the past
            year that we look forward to presenting, including new work with
            PHPUnit for functional testing of your applications.
        </p>
    </li>

    <li>
        <p>
            <b>Getting Started with Zend Framework</b>: This will build off our
            <a href="http://framework.zend.com/docs/quickstart">Quick Start</a>,
            providing background on ZF as well as the basic tools and
            information needed to get your first ZF application up and running.
            I also hope to demonstrate how the current preview of Zend_Tool can
            simplify this dramatically.
        </p>
    </li>

    <li>
        <p>
            <b>Zend_Layout and Zend_Form</b>: This session will show off
            features of Zend_Layout and Zend_Form. (Note: the subject matter may
            change.)
        </p>
    </li>

    <li>
        <p>
            <b>UnCon: Rich UIs and Easy XHR with Dojo and Zend Framework</b>:
            For those unable to attend my webinar next week, or who simply want
            to see this in person, I'll be presenting my Dojo and Zend Framework
            talk during an UnCon session. I have developed a simple app to
            showcase various features of the Dojo/ZF integration, and to show
            how easy it is to quickly develop and then scale applications that
            have great, dynamic interfaces.
        </p>
    </li>
</ul>

<p>
    Looking forward to seeing you in California in September!
</p>]]></content:encoded>
      <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
